<P>AC 136 Elementary Accounting I 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course in double-entry methods of accounting for service and merchandising enterprises. This includes the complete accounting cycle, special journals, notes and interest, accruals and deferrals, receivable, inventory and plant assets. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>AC 137 Elementary Accounting II 3 credits </P>

<P>A continuation of Accounting 136, with emphasis on </P>

<P>partnerships and corporations. The basics of financial analysis, cost accounting and managerial accounting are also included. PREREQUISITE: AC 136. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>AC 186 Payroll Accounting 3 credits </P>

<P>This course covers the basics of payroll preparation and the filling out of forms that must be filed quarterly and annually by most businesses. (OSP) </P>

<P>AC 206 Computer Accounting 3 credits </P>

<P>This course uses computers to apply the basic principles and procedures of accrual accounting with a sophisticated accounting software program. Computer accounting applications include general ledger, accounts receivable, accounts payable, invoicing, payroll, inventory and job cost. (OF) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Agriculture &amp; Natural Resources </H3>

<P>AG 100 Introduction to Agribusiness Systems 3 credits </P>

<P>An introduction to the Agribusiness Systems career pathway. Topics covered include an overview of the agribusiness industry, economic principles in agribusiness, and retail agribusiness sales. (SP) </P>

<P>AG 103 Soils &amp; Fertilizers 3 credits </P>

<P>A basic study of soils formation, morphology, relationship to water, physical properties, chemical properties, organic matter, classification, erosion and soils relationship to the environment. Plant growth requirements, fertilizers and soil testing are also covered. (SP) </P>

<P>AG 104 Soils &amp; Fertilizers Laboratory 1 credit </P>

<P>Laboratory course including practical experiences related to soil texture, structure, morphology, and chemistry. Other topics include: land classification and legal descriptions, USDA Web Soil Survey, soil testing, and interpreting soil tests. Taken in conjunction with AG103. (SP) </P>

<P>AG 105 Plant Science 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course in agronomy; areas of study include plant morphology, growth processes, growth and development, crop investment, climate, and nutrition. (F) </P>

<P>AG 106 Plant Science Lab 1 credit </P>

<P>Lab activities involving plant and seed identification, seed germination, plant growth and plant nutrition; taken in conjunction with AG 105. (F) </P>

<P>AG 107 Animal Science 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course in animal science; areas of study include genetics, reproduction, nutrition, health and management of meat and companion animals. (F, SP) </P>

<P>AG 108 Animal Science Laboratory 1 credit </P>

<P>Laboratory including practical experiences with anatomy and physiology, live animal and meat grading, animal reproduction, and animal health; taken in conjunction with AG107. (F, SP) </P>

<P>AG 109 Pork Production &amp; Management 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of management decisions related to the breeding, feeding, marketing and management of commercial and purebred swine. (DD) </P>

<P>AG 112 Beef Production &amp; Management 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of management decisions related to the breeding, feeding, marketing and management of commercial and purebred beef operations. (SP) </P>

<P>AG 114 Crop Science 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of management decisions related to germination, seed selection, and tillage and seedbed preparation, planning methods, fertility, pest control, harvest and storage, and marketing of grain, oilseed and forage crops. (SP) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>AG 117 Agricultural Mathematics 3 credits </P>

<P>An intensive review of the fundamentals of basic arithmetic, fractions, percentages, geometric and algebraic solutions as applied to the field of agriculture. PREREQUISITE: appropriate ACT or placement test score, or completion of DS 048. (SP) </P>

<P>AG 124 Horses &amp; Horsemanship 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of the scope and role of the light horse industry, breeds, development of the horse and its use, selection, breeding, feeding, anatomy and foot care, tack and unsoundness. Visits to stables and equine events will be included. (DD) </P>

<P>AG 125 Light Horse Production 3 credits </P>

<P>This course will explore in detail the important aspects of light horse production including breeding and reproduction, feeds and feeding, stable management, horse health and behavior, selection and judging for commercial or purebred horses. (Lab fee) (SP) </P>

<P>AG 130 Farm &amp; Environmental Safety 2 credits </P>

<P>A study of the mechanical, chemical, electrical, livestock structural and environmental hazards in a farm or natural resource environment. Students will demonstrate the safe operation of tractors, implements, lawn mowers, chain saws, ATV, and pickup with livestock trailer. Basic first-aid is also covered. Students earning passing scores will receive a certificate of training from the U. S. Department of Labor. (F, SP) </P>

<P>AG 132 Agriculture Mechanics 4 credits </P>

<P>A study of basic agriculture mechanics including shop safety and operation, tool identification and use, arc and oxyacetylene welding, oxyacetylene and plasma cutting, woodworking, concrete and plumbing, and machinery and engine maintenance. (F) </P>

<P>AG 148 Agriculture Sales 3 credits </P>

<P>Students will study how to become effective sales representatives for agribusiness. (SP) </P>

<P>AG 163 Agriculture Credit and Finance 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey of the principles, concepts and functions of credit and finance as related to agriculture. (SP) </P>

<P>AG 215 Ag &amp; Natural Resources Internship 6 credits </P>

<P>Applied training in a production agriculture operation, an agriculturally related business, or natural resource management agency following a prearranged training plan arrived at cooperatively by the employer, the student and the College, with experiences appropriate for the student and training enterprise. Periodic visits by instructor for conferences with the student and employer. PREREQUISITE: Instructor permission. A minimum of 45 credit contact hours is required for every hour of credit. (SP, SU) </P>

<P>AG 223 Agriculture Economics 3 credits </P>

<P>An introduction to the basic concepts and issues of economics as they relate to the food and fiber industry and management of natural resources. Additional projects involving global agricultural trade are included. </P>

<P>(F) </P>

<P>AG 224 Principles of Light Horse Training 2 credits </P>

<P>Lectures will pertain to horse behavior and training methods. Students will learn the principles, theory and practical experience of the training of foals up to two years old. (Lab fee) (SP) </P>

<P>AG 225 Advanced Light Horse Training 2 credits </P>

<P>Students will develop further expertise in training, managing, feeding and preparing two-year-old horses. Each student is assigned a horse to take through basic training stages from haltering to riding. (Lab fee) (SP) </P>

<P>AG 227 Feeds &amp; Feeding 3 credits </P>

<P>A basic study of the fundamentals of animal nutrition and feeding requirements, calculation and preparation of balanced rations, and methods of feeding. (DD) </P>

<P>AG 230 Agricultural Marketing 3 credits </P>

<P>Principles, methods and techniques utilized in marketing agricultural products. Special emphasis will be placed on the marketing options and their use. Guest speakers and field trips will be used in addition to discussions. (DD) </P>

<P>AG 240 Soil &amp; Farm Water Management 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of planning water management practices for soil productivity, farm surveying, design, layout and maintenance of conservation practices utilized in cropland, pasture/ hay land, woodland and land uses. (DD) </P>

<P>AG 270 Farm Mgmt. &amp; Records Analysis 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of economic principles related to the management and operation of farm businesses; purposes and methods of keeping farm records and analysis of the farm business. (F) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Allied Health </H3>

<P>AH 102 Human Body: Health &amp; Disease 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide fundamental information in human anatomy and physiology for those entering health-related fields of study. It includes education regarding all the body systems, common pathology/diseases, diagnostic and treatment modalities. (Does not meet science requirement for AA degree.) (OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>AH 106 Math for Allied Health Sciences 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is primarily designed to provide the allied health student with the knowledge needed to calculate safe drug dosages. Specific instruction is given on oral and parenteral drug dosages, intravenous drip flow rates and pediatric formulas. Additionally, emphasis is placed on interpreting physician’s orders, reading drug labels and safe medication administration. (F,SP,OF,OSP,OSU) </P>

<P>AH 125 Intro. Anatomy &amp; Physiology for Allied Health 4 credits </P>

<P>Introduction to the structure and function of the cells, tissues, organs, and organ systems of the human body. Focus and terminology used is intended for students entering specific allied health programs; does not fulfill nursing program requirement. (OSU) </P>

<P>AH 160 Basic Medical Terminology 3 credits </P>

<P>A course designed for students who wish to enter the healthcare field or for those presently employed who wish to upgrade current skills of understanding and utilizing medically related terms. Approach is from the general use of roots, prefixes and suffixes of terms most frequently encountered and related to specific body systems. (OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>AH 200 Principles of Pharmacology (Non-nursing) 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is the study of the principles of pharmacology and their application to allied health professionals (non-nursing). Mathematics skills are reviewed for the safe administration of medications. The nursing process, critical thinking and therapeutic communication in a community-based health care system are included. Cultural and ethnic variations are discussed. Emphasis is placed on committing to lifelong learning in the continually changing area of health care. PREREQUISITE: DS048 or appropriate math placement score within last three years. (Lab fee) (OSP) </P>

<P>AH 202 Health Insurance Billing 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to introduce students to major nationwide medical insurance programs, provide students with a basic knowledge of national diagnosis and procedure coding systems, and simplify the process of filing claim forms. (OF) </P>

<P>AH 210 Medical Assisting: Clinical Procedures 3 credits </P>

<P>This course teaches the medical assistant student the principles and importance of asepsis and infection control; procedures for specimen collection and processing; clinical office diagnostic testing procedures; principles of patient care; how to take a medical history; how to perform a basic physical examination; and the principles of radiology. This course requires students to travel to campus for four labs throughout the semester. PREREQUISITES: AH 102, AH 200; co-requisite: AH 222 (Lab fee) (OSP) </P>

<P>AH 211 Medical Law and Ethics 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to expose professional to the dynamic legal and ethical aspects of employment in a health care setting. The various components of medical law and ethics will be explored in a way that is applicable to the healthcare profession. This course will provide insight to help the student gain confidence in dealing with legal and ethical problems that occur as a member of the healthcare system. (OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>AH 222 Medical Assistant Internship 3 credits </P>

<P>This internship is designed to place students in a variety of ambulatory care and acute care settings and is available to students who have completed the course requirements for the Medical Assistant AAS program. The student applies principles and skills for filing health insurance, billing, diagnostic and procedural coding, business office skills, as well as records management through virtual simulation training and then through real-life experiences. Students are mentored by the supervisor or designated person at the approved internship site. Students are not paid for the hours spent in the internship by the College nor the internship site. The internship is a total of 90 clinical hours. PREREQUISITE: Requires “C” or above in all courses and program advisor’s permission. (OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>AH 223 First Aid &amp; Emergency Procedures 2 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to help students recognize an emergency, prepare for emergencies, recognize signs and symptoms of acute illness and injury, and how to care for the patient in each situation. (Lab fee) (OF, OSP) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Applied Technology </H3>

<P>AT 240 Industrial Hygiene &amp; Safety 3 credits </P>

<P>This course outlines real-world illustrations and solutions in safety training that utilize performance-based occupational safety concepts. As well as workplace safety and training, the course covers changing the workplace culture while improving communication. (DD) </P>

<P>Art </P>

<P>AR 102 Appreciation of the Arts 1-3 credits </P>

<P>Offered on occasion on various special topics, with specific content indicated by course subtitle. Credit hours determined by contact hours, activities and assignments as appropriate to content. (DD) </P>

<P>AR 104 Art Appreciation 3 credits </P>

<P>A broad survey of the visual arts guiding the student toward an awareness of art in relation to the environment. Includes the examination of motivations for creating art, the study of various artistic processes and the chronological study of the history of art. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR ARTS 100 – ART APPRECIATION </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>AR 105 Design I 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course about two-dimensional design principles and elements and how they relate to the other arts. (F) </P>

<P>AR 106 Drawing I 3 credits </P>

<P>A basic course emphasizing the elements of drawing and the interpretation of visual properties of form and space through drawing. No painting or color involved. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (F, SP) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PERF 105D – STUDIO ART – INTRODUCTION TO DRAWING </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>AR 109 Beginning Oil Painting 3 credits </P>

<P>Beginning Oil Painting introduces the student to the basic fundamentals of oil painting as a means for student development. Students will develop skills in using painting materials, as well as solving problems in basic compositions. (DD) </P>

<P>AR 111 Painting I 3 credits </P>

<P>Introduction to painting through exploration of a variety of techniques, focusing on acrylic and oil mediums. A great deal of attention will be paid to drawing skills in relation to the painting process. Emphasis on studio work. PREREQUISITE: AR 106 or instructor approval. (SP) </P>

<P>AR 112 Water Color Media 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides experience with selected water-based painting media: water color, casein, tempera and acrylics. (DD) </P>

<P>AR 205 Design II 3 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on the characteristics of color within design. The application of color to the design process through various instruction and projects will engage students in the theory and practice of color design. PREREQUISITE: AR 105. (SP) </P>

<P>AR 206 Drawing II 3 credits </P>

<P>Experience in interpretation of the visual elements from all sources of design: landscape, plant life, man-made and geometric forms, and animal and human forms. Emphasis on creative problems and composition. Use of varied drawing media. PREREQUISITE: AR 106. (F, SP) </P>

<P>AR 211 Painting II 3 credits </P>

<P>Painting II provides a focus on the compositional, technical and stylistic approach to form and content in paint media. Emphasis on composition and expressive originality. PREREQUISITE: AR 111. (SP) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Behavioral Health Support </H3>

<P>BH 201 Introduction to Behavioral Health Support credits </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is for students to become familiar with the many roles and functions of behavioral health support workers. Emphasis will be placed on the following: history of mental health agencies, current practices of the agencies where behavioral support workers are employed, skills and dispositions needed by behavioral health workers, and common clinical encounters facilitated by behavioral health workers. This course is the first in a series designed to train students to become professionals in the behavioral health field. (DD) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>BH 210 Motivational Interviewing &amp; Behavioral Modification 3 credits </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is to explore the philosophy, principles, and procedures of behavior modification and motivational interviewing and to illustrate evidence-based applications of each across a variety of contexts. The applications of these techniques will be discussed in relation to not only the reduction of undesirable behavior, but also the enhancement of desirable behavior. PREREQUISITES: PY121 (DD) </P>

<P>BH 220 Wellness Coaching 3 credits </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is introduce students to the process of wellness coaching. Students will learn a set of techniques designed to help future clients achieve and maintain optimal emotional, financial, social, spiritual, occupational, physical, intellectual, and environmental wellness. (DD) </P>

<P>BH 230 Systems of Care and Support 3 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on identifying and building relationships with community resources. Students will learn to identify, coordinate and link community resources with client needs. Students will gain knowledge of services offered by public and private providers as well as funding sources. Students will also </P>

<P>learn about how one’s culture can impact the receiving </P>

<P>and seeking of various services. At the end of the course students will a have a resource portfolio. PREREQUISITES: SO107 (DD) </P>

<P>BH 240 Diagnosis of Identified Populations 3 credits </P>

<P>This course will provide a comprehensive overview of common mental health disorders, how symptoms manifest in everyday life, and the risk and protective factors related to these disorders. In addition, students will learn about the instruments used by licensed mental health professionals when making diagnoses. (DD) </P>

<P>BH 250 Evidence-based Treatments 3 credits </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is to expose future behavioral health support workers to commonly used mental health prevention and intervention approaches. A special emphasis is given to those evidence based treatment approaches most commonly used by community behavioral health agencies and substance abuse facilities. (DD) </P>

<P>BH 260 Conflict Resolution 3 credits </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is for students to learn conflict resolution skills that they will be able to use in their work as behavioral health support workers. This course will discuss the resolution of both interpersonal and intrapersonal conflict, as well as address the theories, concepts, and models of mental health crisis intervention. (DD) </P>

<P>BH 280 Behavioral Health Support Clinical Practicum I 3 credits </P>

<P>Students participate with social service agencies in order to learn the structure and function of public services agencies. Students will engage in supervised behavioral health activities in a social service agency that serves individuals, families and communities. The practicum experience provides students the opportunity to integrate and apply theory into their practice. Students must complete 120 hours of practical work experience. PREREQUISITES: BH201 (DD) </P>

<P>BH 290 Behavioral Health Support Clinical Practicum II 4 credits </P>

<P>This course offers continued applied experience in an agency setting. Students will engage in supervised behavioral health activities in a social service agency that serves individuals, families and communities. The practicum experience provides students the opportunity to integrate and apply theory into their practice. Students must complete 150 hours of practical work experience. PREREQUISITES: BH280 (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Biological Science </H3>

<P>Biological science courses require placement scores that must be less than three years old. </P>

<P>BI 100 General Biology 5 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on the general principles of biology, including ecology, cell biology, biochemistry, genetics, microbiology, botany, and zoology. Structure, function and life application are stressed as components of each unit of study. Natural Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program biology requirements. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: EN101W and DS049 or appropriate placement test scores. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR BIOL 100L – ESSENTIALS IN BIOLOGY WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>BI 101 General Botany 5 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on a fundamental study of plant structure, physiology, ecology, economic importance, life histories, and taxonomy. Natural Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program biology requirements. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: DS 049 and EN101W or appropriate placement test scores. (SP) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR BIOL 150L – BIOLOGY WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>BI 103 General Zoology 5 credits </P>

<P>A general study of animal phyla with a focus on structure, ecology, behavior, taxonomy, and defining characteristics. Natural Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program biology requirements. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: DS 049 and EN101W or appropriate placement test scores. (F) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR BIOL 150L – BIOLOGY WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>BI 110 Ecology 5 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on the general principles of ecology (populations, communities, and ecosystems) and field technique. The inter-relationships of the following natural resources will be stressed: air, water, soils, forests, grasslands, wildlife, fish, and endangered species. Natural Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program biology requirements. Lecture and laboratory. (F) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR BIOL 150L – BIOLOGY WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>BI 205 Current Topics in Biology 1 credit </P>

<P>Articles addressing timely topics in biology are studied in this course. Summarization, verification of information, experimental design, and study of human and environmental impact of the topics will be covered. (DD) </P>

<P>BI 210 Special Topics in Life Science 1-3 credits </P>

<P>A special topics course developed to further studies in Life Science. The subtitle of the course will indicate specific content. Credit varies from one to three hours depending on course design. This course may be repeated if the content changes. (DD) </P>

<P>BI 238 Anatomy and Physiology 8 credits </P>

<P>This course is a study of the structure and function, including homeostatic mechanism of the chemicals, cells, tissues, and organs of the human integumentary, skeletal, muscular, nervous, endocrine, cardiovascular, lymphatic, respiratory, digestive, urinary, and reproductive systems. Does not satisfy the life science general education requirement. Lecture and Laboratory. (Lab Fee) (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>BI 240 Human Anatomy 4 credits </P>

<P>This course is a study of the structure of the cells and tissues of the human integumentary, skeletal, muscular, nervous, endocrine, cardiovascular, lymphatic, respiratory, digestive, urinary, and reproductive systems. Natural Sciences credit. Lecture and laboratory. (Lab fee) (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LIFS 150L – HUMAN BIOLOGY WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>BI 241 Human Chemistry 3 credits </P>

<P>The emphasis of this course is the chemistry and physiology of the cells and tissues within the human integumentary, skeletal, muscular, respiratory, digestive, urinary, cardiovascular, immunological, endocrine, nervous, and reproductive systems. Does not satisfy the life science general education requirement. Lecture and laboratory. (CBA) </P>

<P>BI 242 Human Physiology 4 credits </P>

<P>This course is a study of the function including homeostatic mechanisms of the chemicals, cells, and tissues of the human integumentary, skeletal, muscular, nervous, endocrine, cardiovascular, lymphatic, respiratory, digestive, urinary, and reproductive systems. Natural Sciences credit. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: BI 240 with a minimum grade of “C”. (SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LIFS 150L – HUMAN BIOLOGY WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>BI 243 Microbiology 4 credits </P>

<P>This course is a study of microorganisms emphasizing morphology, reproduction, biochemical activities, culture techniques, pathogenicity and control. Does not satisfy the life science general education requirement. Lecture and laboratory. (OF, OSP, OSU) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Business Management </H3>

<P>BA 101 Introduction to Business 3 credits </P>

<P>To introduce the student to the characteristics, functions and problems of the business world. (F, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>BA 110 Current Issues in Business 3 credits </P>

<P>An orientation to practices and principles of marketing and industrial decisions that affect national and international businesses that contribute to social, economic and environmental changes. (F, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>BA 150 Principles of Management 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course in management principles and functions. This course includes the history of management; the processes of planning, departmental organizing, directing, and controlling; and management’s relationship with the community and the environment. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>BA 154 Principles of Marketing 3 credits </P>

<P>Marketing foundations represent the basic skills and understandings of the marketing concept within the business environment and the management systems within which it is implemented. Concepts include the marketing mix, consumer behavior, market segmentation, targeted marketing and distribution. The development of a marketing plan is the focal point of the course. (F, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>BA 160 Intro to Sport Management 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide students with an overview of the sports media and communications field. Course range encompasses the place of sport communication within the larger field of sport management and administration, personal and organizational aspects of sport communication, the different segments of sport media, plus the services and support systems associated within sport communication. (DD) </P>

<P>BA 161 Human Resource Management 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a comprehensive review of essential personnel management concepts, law, controversies, and techniques of success currently being used in business. PREREQUISITE: BA 150. (SP, OF) </P>

<P>BA 176 Business Management Internship 4 credits </P>

<P>Seminar-type courses which are based on the application of fundamental business principles and curriculum competencies at both a local internship training station and in the classroom. Must be taken sequentially thereafter. Membership to Delta Epsilon Chi is required. PREREQUISITE: Instructor permission. A minimum of 45 contact hours is required for every hour of credit. (DD) </P>

<P>BA 204 Credit &amp; Finance 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of the organization and operation of credit departments, consumer and commercial credit, collections, and business finance. (SP, OF) </P>

<P>BA 220 Structure and Governance of Sport 3 credits </P>

<P>This course takes a look at the governance structures of sport organizations and the power and politics within these structures as well as current policy issues and the ethical issues in these structures. Area of topics that will be covered are the governance of sport, sport ethics, policy development, collegiate governance, competitive balance, disability sport issues, commercialization of sport, gender equity, and globalization. (DD) </P>

<P>BA 221 Business Law 3 credits </P>

<P>An introduction to statutory and administration regulations governing business conduct for small businesses and individuals. Emphasis is placed on contracts, negotiable instruments, employer/employee relationship, sale of personal and real property and insurance. (F, OSP) </P>

<P>BA 269 Entrepreneurship 3 credits </P>

<P>Each student identifies a business opportunity and prepares all the plans and analyses which would be necessary to develop the proposed business with instructional guidance and assistance. (SP, OF) </P>

<P>BA 279 Special Topics in Business 1-3 credits </P>

<P>A course offered in response to a specific situation; a variable issue-oriented course which has its content described in a subtitle. Credit and prerequisite as announced. (DD) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>BA 280 International Business 3 credits </P>

<P>This course introduces students to the world of international business and management by studying cultural influences, government, and business structures in our global economy. Students will also learn about trade relations, international finance and legal and labor agreements. Also covered are topics on information needs, production systems, marketing and promotion and career planning. PREREQUISITES: BA 154 or BA 176. (DD) </P>

<P>BA 281 International Business Travel 1 credit </P>

<P>This course is offered as a continuation of BA 280 International Business. The student will be given the opportunity to experience concepts learned in their International Business course by traveling abroad. The course will offer experiences in a business outside the United States, experiences in a different culture and language, and different cultural business practices. The trip will be offered during the Spring Break week only. PREREQUISITES: BI 110 or BA 280; or BA 280; may be taken concurrently with at least a C average in the course. (DD) </P>

<P>BA 285 Business Ethics 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is to serve as an introduction to the many topics involving ethics as they specifically relate to business. The student will also study major ethical theories and learn to apply these theories to contemporary issues. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Business Technology </H3>

<P>BT 110 Business Mathematics 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to give students basic arithmetic fundamentals that will apply in their personal and business lives. (F, OSP) </P>

<P>BT 130 Business Communications 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to give the student a basic understanding of the principles involved in verbal and written business correspondence. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>BT 160 Microcomputer Applications I 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to introduce students to software in the Windows environment, using current word processing, graphics presentation, spreadsheet and database software programs. The course is also designed to introduce students to the elements of Information Management that entail finding information efficiently, evaluating information critically, and using information ethically. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>BT 170 Database Concepts 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides a comprehensive presentation of Microsoft Access 2007. Topics include creating, querying, and maintaining a database; creating a data access page, reports, forms, combo boxes; using OLE fields, hyperlinks, and subforms; creating an application system using the Switchboard Manager; creating a report using design view; customizing forms using VBA; working with charts and pivot table objects; administering a database, SQL and Access data, in other applications. PREREQUISITE: BT 160 or instructor approval. (F, OSP) </P>

<P>BT 180 Digi Tools 2 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to prepare students to work with tools in the digital world, starting with an in-depth use of practical keyboarding techniques. In addition, use of PDAs and tablet computers, cellular technologies, digitizers/scanners and other digital tools will be demonstrated/practiced on. (SP, OF) </P>

<P>BT 190 Spreadsheet Applications 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to give the student a basic understanding of the principles and software involved in spreadsheet applications. This course is designed to give each student the basic tools in 10-key. Much of the </P>

<P>student’s success is up to the individual as the software </P>

<P>must be practiced. PREREQUISITE: BT 160. (OSP, OF) </P>

<P>BT 200 Desktop Publishing 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to prepare the student to create professional looking custom publications through real life exercises and examples. Publications for both print and internet will be examined and studied. (SP) </P>

<P>BT 210 Web Page Design I 3 credits </P>

<P>This course will introduce students to software using current desktop publishing and web page design software programs. PREREQUISITE: BT 160 or instructor approval. (F, OSP) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>BT 215 Web Page Design II 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a continuation of the basic design principles used in Web Design. The course will also introduce new software, advanced animation and other advanced web features. PREREQUISITES: BT 160 and BT </P>

<P>210. (F) </P>

<P>BT 225 Sports Media and Communications 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide students with an overview of the sports media and communications field. Course range encompasses the place of sport communication within the larger field of sport management and administration, personal and organizational aspects of sport communication, the different segments of sport media, plus the services and support systems associated within sport communication. (DD) </P>

<P>BT 230 Office Procedures 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides the skills needed to prepare the college trained administrative assistant to meet the requirements necessary for administrative positions in </P>

<P>today’s competitive job market. This course will help </P>

<P>the student develop good decision making skills and exercise good human relations. Areas emphasized in </P>

<P>this course include: today’s electronic office, technology </P>

<P>and procedures, document creation and distribution, research and organization of business reports, travel and conference planning, employment and career advancement. (DD) </P>

<P>BT 240 Employment Strategies 1 credit </P>

<P>This course is designed to prepare the student in beginning their job search. It will give them the tools needed to utilize and find information in today’s competitive job market. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>BT 250 Word Processing II 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed for the student to learn advanced word processing concepts and applications. The student will continue to receive hands-on experience on a sophisticated visual display word processing system. PREREQUISITE: BT 160. (OF) </P>

<P>BT 260 Microcomputer Applications II 3 credits </P>

<P>This course will offer students an introduction to an array of multimedia concepts and technology components. PREREQUISITE: BT 160. (OSP) </P>

<P>BT 270 Business Technology Internship 4 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to help the student gain experience in a real business situation so as to improve job performance of beginning workers. It is a capstone experience for student interested in the business technology area. Visitation by college faculty ensures coordination of instruction and on-the-job training. PREREQUISITE: at least 30 hours must be completed in the Business Technology program with a 2.0 GPA or approval by instructor. A minimum of 45 contact hours is required for every hour of credit. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Chemistry </H3>

<P>NOTE: Physical Science courses require placement scores of less than three yrs. old. </P>

<P>CH 107 Introduction to Chemistry 4 credits </P>

<P>A beginning chemistry course primarily for non-science majors. An introduction to the basic principles of chemistry emphasizing the importance of chemistry in the real world and its impact on society and the environment. Natural Sciences credit. Lecture and laboratory. Lecture and laboratory. (F, SP, SU, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR CHEM 100L – ESSENTIALS IN CHEMISTRY WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>CH 110 General Chemistry I 5 credits </P>

<P>A rigorous introductory chemistry course primarily for science, engineering, and science education majors. An introduction to the elementary principles of modern chemistry emphasizing structure and properties of matter, stoichiometry, nomenclature and bonding. Natural Sciences credit. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: MT110, or CH107, or meet the ACT or placement scores to enroll in MT122 (F, SP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR CHEM 150L – CHEMISTRY I WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>CH 112 General Chemistry II 5 credits </P>

<P>A continuation of General Chemistry I. Topics to be studied include properties of solutions, acids and bases, kinetics, thermodynamics, equilibrium and electrochemistry. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: CH 110. (SP, SU) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>College Skills </H3>

<P>CS 102 College Seminar 1 credit </P>

<P>College Seminar is an academic course designed to introduce students to the North Central Missouri College community and collegiate environment. The course emphasizes strategies that promote student retention and academic success. This course will: foster an appreciation for the privileges, rights, and responsibilities associated with a college education; acclimate students to college resources and utilization of information technology such as course management software; equip students with the learning skills necessary for success; and cultivate the ability for students to monitor their own learning and academic progress. (F, S, OF, OS) </P>

<P>CS 105 Information Literacy 1 credit </P>

<P>This course is designed to teach students how to locate information efficiently, evaluate information critically, and utilize information effectively. The focus is on a basic understanding of the research process, the use of print and online resources, and the effective utilization of the Internet. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Computer Science &amp; Information Systems </H3>

<P>IT 110 Introduction to Computers 3 credits </P>

<P>An introduction to the basic concepts of information processing and the hardware and software used. The course is designed to familiarize the student with the computer through hands-on experience and classroom lecture. (DD) </P>

<P>IT 113 Windows Concepts 3 credits </P>

<P>Provides an in-depth study on the microcomputer environment with an emphasis placed on MS Windows. Basic keyboarding skills required. (DD) </P>

<P>IT 125 Programming Concepts and Problem Solving 3 </P>

<P>credits This course in an introduction to many computer science topics including algorithms, problem solving, operating system concepts, computer architecture, and beginning programming techniques for those seeking a career in this industry. An overview of computer concepts, ethics and responsibilities and career options are also provided. (SP, FA) IT 182 Visual Basic I 3 credits </P>

<P>This is a beginning course in the Windows environment using the visual BASIC language. It is intended to </P>

<P>develop the student’s ability to design programs and </P>

<P>windows objects using algorithms and coding in structured programs as well as an understanding of Windows properties. PREREQUISITE: Basic keyboarding skills, IT113 or demonstrated familiarity with the Windows environment. Prior completion of Intermediate or College Algebra recommended. (SP) </P>

<P>IT 185 Python Programming 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is an introduction to the Python programming language. The course is designed to cover aspects such as: data types and structures, objects, functions, modularity, file and database interaction, loops and conditionals. (SP) </P>

<P>IT 243 Programming I 3 credits </P>

<P>A hands-on introduction to structured, object-oriented programming in the C++ environment. Includes a study of data types, functions classes, selection and looping. PREREQUISITES: Basis keyboarding skill. Intermediate or College Algebra recommended. (DD) </P>

<P>IT 268 Unix/Linux 3 credits </P>

<P>This course introduces the fundamentals of the UNIX operating system. The course guides students through the basics of UNIX system concepts, architecture and administration. The course also includes networking essentials commonly used in the UNIX environment. Standard UNIX networking tools will be covered, as well as the different “flavors” of UNIX, including Linux. (SP) </P>

<P>IT 270 Computer Science &amp; Information Systems Internship 4 credits </P>

<P>Seminar-type courses which are based on the application of fundamental computer science principles and curriculum competencies at both a local internship training station and in the classroom. (SP, FA) </P>

<P>IT 275 Networking Concepts 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of the installation, configuration, and administration of a microcomputer network using Novell Netware, UNIX, Windows NT and other networking operating systems. The students will learn to plan a network configuration, install network software, create users, and establish and administer networking services. (SP) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>IT 280 Computer Hardware 3 credits </P>

<P>This course offers a detailed study of microcomputer systems hardware modules. Combining theory and practice, the course will cover module level maintenance, repair, replace and retrofit and upgrading trade-off decision parameters; and introductory troubleshooting. Students will identify and replace defective modules, perform hardware upgrades and install software with attendant hardware boards. Students will gain experience in the assembly and disassembly of microcomputer systems. (FA) </P>

<P>IT 290 Object Oriented Programming: Java 3 credits </P>

<P>This course will introduce students to modern object-oriented techniques. Java will be used for the course, and although primarily known as a tool to develop applets for Web pages, it can be used as a general purpose programming language. Java is object-oriented and has been designed for maximum portability while incorporating automatic storage management, exception handling and integrated support for multi-threading. PREREQUISITE: IT182 or IT243 or instructor approval. (SP) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Criminal Justice </H3>

<P>CJ 118 Procedural Law 3 credits </P>

<P>Laws of criminal procedure regulating law enforcement and criminal law process. This course will include a study of the fundamental concepts of constitutional and criminal law. Elements of local, state and federal jurisdiction, venue and procedure as they apply to law enforcement. Law of arrest, search and seizure. (FO, OSO) </P>

<P>CJ 125 Criminal Justice Ethics and Liability 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course studying ethical decisions, law of negligence, and tort liability within the American criminal justice system. Students will explore ethical decisions within law enforcement, courts, and corrections as well as civil liability for these agencies. (SO, OSE) </P>

<P>CJ 126 Introduction to Criminal Justice 3 credits </P>

<P>Surveys of the philosophical and historical background of the criminal justice system. Principles of organization and roles of police and legal systems in relation to activities of local, state and federal agencies. Human relations and social control devices are also studied. (FE, OFO) </P>

<P>CJ 140 Criminal Investigations 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of modern criminal investigation procedures including methods of investigation, sources of information, questioning and interviews, collection and preservation of evidence, preliminary and follow-up investigation, and case preparation. (FO, OSE) </P>

<P>CJ 170 Introduction to Juvenile Law 3 credits </P>

<P>An examination of the origins, philosophy and objectives of the juvenile justice system. Studies the delinquent juvenile as an individual and the impact on society; investigates delinquency, causation, the role of the law enforcement officer, the juvenile officer, the juvenile court and juvenile corrections. (SE, OSE) </P>

<P>CJ 218 Criminology 3 credits </P>

<P>An examination of theories of crime and its causes including interrelationships between specific crimes, types of offenders and correctional theories. (SE, OFE) </P>

<P>CJ 219 Criminal Evidence 3 credits </P>

<P>Students will study the nature, types and degrees of criminal evidence; rules governing admissibility; competency; and relevancy of evidence. (SO, OFE) </P>

<P>CJ 226 Introduction to Corrections 3 credits </P>

<P>Historical analysis of the development of corrections and the influence of social thought and philosophy of this development. Current trends in corrections, court decisions and the role of corrections within the criminal justice system. (SO, OSE) </P>

<P>CJ 235 Criminal Law 3 credits </P>

<P>Explores the origin, development and classification of substantive criminal law. This course will review the rules of evidence important at the operational level of law enforcement with emphasis on criminal procedures in arrest, use of force, and search and seizure. (SE, OSO) </P>

<P>CJ 239 Police Organization and Management 3 credits </P>

<P>Introductory survey of current administrative methodology; reviews the organization of the police service, police functions, principles of police management and operational services within the police agencies. Will include the study of administrative theory as it relates to organizations within the criminal justice system. (FE, OSO) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>CJ 246 Criminal Justice Communications 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a presentation of psychological tactics and techniques used to obtain admissible confessions as evidence in criminal cases. (FE, OSO) </P>

<P>CJ 250 Criminal Justice Practicum 3 credits </P>

<P>Students participate with various public sector criminal justice agencies (e.g. Circuit Court, Juvenile Court, Probation and Parole, local police departments, etc.) in order to gain knowledge about the structure and function of public services agencies. The field placement must be program related. PREREQUISITE: Minimum of thirty hours course work in the program and permission of the instructor. (DD) </P>

<P>CJ 260 Constitutional Aspects of Criminal Justice 3 credits </P>

<P>Selected constitutional aspects of law enforcement including the law of arrest, search, freedom from electronic eavesdropping, self-incrimination and the right to counsel. (FO, OFE) </P>

<P>CJ 298 Deviant Behavior 3 credits </P>

<P>A course to look at the problems of breaking norms set by culture and society. Through this examination, students will explore several sociological theories behind cries and other deviant behaviors. Some topics include domestic violence, mental illness, drug and alcohol usage, organized crime, sexual crimes, suicide, and other deviant acts found in America society today. PREREQUISITE: SO 107. (SO, OFO) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Developmental Studies </H3>

<P>NOTE: DS courses are college preparatory and do not apply toward any degree requirement in any program at NCMC and are not designed to transfer. All Developmental Studies courses are graded Pass/Fail. </P>

<P>DS 048 Pre-Algebra 3 credits </P>

<P>Student learning objectives include: whole number, fraction, and decimal operations and properties, ratios and proportions, signed number operations, basic geometry concepts, units of measurement and introduction to statistics. (Pass/Fail) (OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>DS 049 Basic Algebra 3 credits </P>

<P>Student learning objectives include: order of operations, solving linear equations and inequalities, introduction to graphing in a rectangular coordinate system, simplifying polynomial expressions, factoring and solving quadratic equations with an emphasis on problem solving. Appropriate placement score required. (Pass/Fail) (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>DS 049W Basic Algebra with Workshop 6 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed for students who do not meet DS 049 Basic Algebra requirements. Student learning objectives include: order of operations, solving linear equations and inequalities, introduction to graphing in a rectangular coordinate system, simplifying polynomial expression, factoring, and solving quadratic equations with an emphasis on problem solving. Includes a three credit hour workshop designed to give students customized support to provide just-in-time academic support to help their learning and success of the course. (This course is not designed to transfer). (F, S) </P>

<P>DS 080 Introduction to Keyboarding 2 credits </P>

<P>This self-paced, hands-on computer course teaches students the alphabetic, numeric and symbol keys, as well as the 10-key pad. Students will develop speed and accuracy through the touch system. (Pass/Fail) (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Early Childhood Development </H3>

<P>CD 101 Parents as Teachers 1 credit </P>

<P>This course is designed to help parents become better </P>

<P>observers of their children’s development, to acquaint parents with the basic neuroscience behind a child’s </P>

<P>development, and to help parents engage their pre-Kindergarten children in activities that promote language, cognitive, social/emotional and motor development. (DD) </P>

<P>CD 110 Child Development Portfolio 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides a step-by-step approach of the activities necessary to complete Child Development Associate credential requirements. This course is a review of the 13 functional areas of the Child Development Associate credential. Completion of the Professional Resource File is a requirement for this course. Upon completion of this course students will be prepared for the CDA application process. (OF) </P>

<P>CD 112 Childhood Development 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a study of human development from conception to age eight. It will provide an overview of physical, cognitive, social, emotional, creative, and language development with emphasis on interrelationship of growth and behavior of young children. Theories and philosophical viewpoints will be introduced to help students determine a personal philosophy of how children grow and learn. Students will observe children of different ages in a variety of settings using multiple assessment and data told. This course will provide 40 hours of training for CDA. Co-requisites CD130 Foundations of Early Childhood Education &amp; CD205 Health, Nutrition and Safety. (OF) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>CD 120 Organization/Administration of Early Childhood Programs 3 credits </P>

<P>An examination of licensing, staffing, facilities, equipment, and material for early childhood programs. Course includes program development, personnel management, facilities/equipment concerns, parent involvement and community relationships. A study of the skills and techniques in managing early care and education programs, including legal and ethical issues, personnel management, advocacy, professionalism, planning and budgeting, parent education/partnerships, and CACFP food program. (OF) </P>

<P>CD 130 Foundations of Early Childhood Education 3 credits </P>

<P>An introduction to the profession of early care and education including historical foundations, ethical guidelines, and trends. Licensing rules and regulation will be reviewed along with a broad range of current program and accreditation systems. Students will examine the qualities and skills necessary for working with young children and receive an overview of appropriate curriculum. Students will learn to observe and record the behavior, teacher, and environment of young children. Students will learn strategies to work effectively with families to meet the needs of the child. This course will provide 40 hours of training for CDA. Co-Requisites CD112 Child Development &amp; CD205 Health, Nutrition and Safety (OF) </P>

<P>CD 140 Creative Expression and Play 3 credits </P>

<P>This course will explore a child-directed approach to education and the role of creativity in cognitive development while blending theory and research with practical application. The course will review topics and issues related to the creative experience including: planning, developing, implementing, assessing creative activities, creating a stimulating environment, as well as, strategies for developing an anti-bias curriculum. (OSP) </P>

<P>CD 150 Special Topics in Early Childhood Education 1-3 credits </P>

<P>A course offered in response to a specific situation; a variable, issue-oriented course which has its content described in a subtitle. Credit and prerequisites as announced. (DD) </P>

<P>CD 205 Health, Nutrition and Safety 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to give information about current concepts in the field of health, safety and nutrition for children birth to eight years old in relationship to their family and community. This course will prepare the early childhood educator to meet the physical needs of young children through the creation of a safe environment, planned routines, and positive experience. Topics include health assessment, first aid, safety, basic nutrition, nutrition educations, meals and snacks for children. This course will provide 40 hours of training for a CDA. Must have or obtain First Aid/CPR Certification. Co-Requisites: CD130, CD112. (OF) </P>

<P>CD 207 Children with Special Needs 3 credits </P>

<P>This course will provide an overview of laws regarding children with special needs, developmentally appropriate curriculum, and current issues related to special needs children. Students will examine appropriate ways to gather data when teaching children with special needs. Students will study Individual Education Plans (IEPs) and Individual Family Service Plans (IFSPs) applying knowledge of differentiated instruction to individual case studies. (OSP) </P>

<P>CD 209 Preschool Literature 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to present a survey of children’s literature, to establish guidelines for evaluating that literature, to help students become aware of the educational opportunities literature provides, and to develop educational experiences based on literature. (OF) </P>

<P>CD 211 Music for Children 3 credits </P>

<P>Students will learn how early childhood teachers can provide a wide variety of musical activities to stimulate </P>

<P>and enhance a child’s innate musical abilities. Students </P>

<P>will become aware of all aspects of the music curriculum and will learn how to develop lesson plans incorporating these essential areas towards making music education fun, but skill-driven. (DD) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>CD 213 Exploring Science &amp; Math in the Early Childhood Setting 3 credits </P>

<P>This course covers theoretical foundation for teaching science and mathematics in the early childhood setting. Strategies for implementing, nurturing, assessing and supporting early childhood science and math learning environments will be covered. Concepts covered are based on the national Science Education Standards (NSES), the National Council of Teachers of Mathematics (NCTM), Principles and Standards for School Mathematics and Missouri Early Learning Goals (MELS). (DD) </P>

<P>CD 220 Emergent Language and Literacy 3 credits </P>

<P>An overview of early literacy based on appropriate literacy standards. Students will learn about emergent literacy such as emergent speaking, emergent writing, and emergent reading. Strategies for enhancing and assessing literacy curriculum in each of these areas will be discussed. Family literacy and its importance will also be included in the coursework. (OF) </P>

<P>CD 230 Family, School &amp; Community 3 credits </P>

<P>This course explores the impact of the community and society on children and families. Cultural and socio economic factors and the realities of the changing family and society including family systems, child rearing, and parenting styles are surveyed. Students will examine strategies to promote family and community involvement. Community agency programs and their benefits for parents will also be discussed. (OSP) </P>

<P>CD 240 Infant &amp; Toddler Curriculum with Field </P>

<P>Experience 3 credits This course is designed to survey and give students the knowledge and skills of a variety of curriculum, and teaching strategies needed to provide developmentally appropriate learning opportunities to children birth to 36 months of age. Application of intentional teaching for developmental and academic areas will be discussed. Reflection on students own practice to promote positive outcomes for children will be emphasized. Students will meet in class 3 hours per week with an additional 10 hours of field experience in a preapproved child care setting with children birth to 36 months of age. Field Experience hours will address observing, documenting, and applying knowledge to create developmentally appropriate lesson plans for all children. (OSP) CD 242 Preschool Curriculum &amp; Field Experience 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to survey and give students the knowledge and skills of a variety of curriculum and teaching strategies needed to provide developmentally appropriate learning opportunities for children 3 to 5 years of age. Application of intentional teaching for developmental and academic areas will be discussed. Reflection on students own practice to promote positive outcomes for children will be emphasized. Students will meet in class 3 hours per week with an additional 10 hours of field experience in an approved preschool, Head Start, or School District setting with children 3 to 5 years of age. The filed experience will address observing, documenting, and applying knowledge to creating developmentally appropriate curriculum for children 3 to 5 years of age. (OF) </P>

<P>CD 250 Observation and Assessment 3 credits </P>

<P>This course consists of supervised observation in conjunction with classroom lecture. Students will complete a total of 2 hours/week of lecture/instruction and students will observe one child in a single facility for a total of 45 hours throughout the semester. The student, with the teacher, field advisor, and parent approval will observe one child with various developmentally appropriate observation methods. The culminating experience for this course will be the compilation of the observations into a full report on the child’s developmental level in each of the following areas: physical, creativity, social, emotional, cognitive, and language development. The students will meet with the instructor at the end of the semester to share experiences and bring closure to the observation to prepare for the internship. (OSP) </P>

<P>CD 260 Early Childhood Development Practicum /Field Experience 3 credits </P>

<P>The student will actively participate, under supervision, for a minimum of 150 clock hours in a Head Start, accredited or public classroom setting. Students will observe and practice using developmentally appropriate teaching strategies with preschool children. Students will plan and implement curriculum components for young children in conjunction with supervising teacher. A minimum of 50 contact hours is required for every hour of credit </P>

<P>CD 280 Professionalism in Early Childhood Education 3 credits </P>

<P>This capstone course is for the Early Childhood Development AAS degree seeking students. Students will create a portfolio connecting early childhood practices in the six NAEYC Professional Standards and Missouri Vocational Pathway Outcomes as a required component for this degree. Knowledge of ethical standards and other elements of professional guidelines will be examined. The course will cover career management topics (resume, interviewing skills, and employment soft skills) along with exploration of employment opportunities. Completion of a program assessment is a requirement of this course. PRE-or COREQUISITE: CD260 (OSP) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect/>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Economics </H3>

<P>EC 252 Microeconomics 3 credits </P>

<P>An introduction to basic microeconomic fundamentals with emphasis on economic reasoning, supply and demand analysis, market structure, globalization and trade, government intervention in markets, economics and government policy and income distribution. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. (F, SP, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR ECON 102 – INTRODUCTION TO MICROECONOMICS </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EC 253 Macroeconomics 3 credits </P>

<P>An introduction to basic macroeconomic fundamentals with emphasis on growth, business cycles, unemployment and inflation, Gross Domestic Product, macroeconomic models, monetary and fiscal policy and international effects of domestic policy. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. (F, SP, OF, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR ECON 101 – INTRODUCTION TO MACROECONOMICS </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Education </H3>

<P>Child Psychology and Adolescent Psychology are listed under Psychology (PY). </P>

<P>ED 200 Foundations of Education in a Diverse Society 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to examine educational practice from diverse historical, philosophical, sociological, economic, and legal perspectives. The course will address issues of educational equity, sociocultural influences on teaching and learning, and how teachers and schools can contribute to interpersonal and intercultural understanding and respect, social justice, and democratic citizenship. Students will explore the nature of school environments, the fundamental goals of education in the American public school, English Language Learners, the relationship between school and a diverse society, the organization of school curricula, and characteristics of effective schools and instruction in grades P-12. PREREQUISITE: EN 101. AAT core course. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>ED 201 Teaching Profession with Field Experience credits </P>

<P>This course includes an introductory, minimum 35 hours of school field experience in accredited P-12 classroom(s) that provide opportunities to observe and contribute to teaching and learning. This course allows pre-service teachers to connect first-hand school experience with an emerging professional knowledge base. The course develops professional knowledge of diverse educational settings through observation, instruction, experience, and reflection. This course is designed to assist students in determining if a career in teaching is an appropriate goal. Requirements for teacher preparation and certification are reviewed. PREREQUISITE: EN 101. AAT core course. (Background check fee) (F, SP, OF, OSP) </P>

<P>ED 265 Multicultural Education 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to examine the multicultural context of education and prepare students to understand and teach learners from diverse backgrounds, with diverse characteristics, and with differing social identities. The course will address issues of educational equity, sociocultural influences on teaching and learning, and how teachers and schools can contribute to interpersonal and intercultural understanding and respect, social justice, and democratic citizenship. PREREQUISITE: EN101 (OSU, OF, OSP) </P>

<P>ED 270 Educational Psychology 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to help students relate theories and principles of educational psychology to teaching, learning, and assessment. This course focuses on the diversity of learning and learning processes, as well as teacher characteristics, classroom strategies, and data analysis in the P-12 classrooms. Appropriate strategies for increasing motivation, multi-dimensional development, and academic achievement for all learners are introduced </P>

<P>PREREQUISITE:PY121. AAT core course. (F, SP) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>ED 275 Educational Technology 3 credits </P>

<P>In this course, students will learn how to integrate instructional technology into the P-12 classrooms. Students will study a variety of software programs, presentation technology, telecommunication tools and assistive technology. The focus will also be on social, ethical, legal and human issues surrounding the use of technology. PREREQUISITE: EN 101. AAT core course. (F, SP) </P>

<P>ED 280 Special Topics in Education 1-3 credits </P>

<P>A course offered in response to a specific situation; a variable topic-oriented course that has its content described in a subtitle. Credit and prerequisites as announced. (DD) </P>

<P>ED 283 Health &amp; PE Methods for Elementary Teachers 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide the elementary education teacher candidate with knowledge and practical experiences with content and methods for teaching health and physical education at the elementary school level. (SP) </P>

<P>ED 285 Education of Exceptional Learners 3 credits </P>

<P>This survey course is an introduction to exceptional learners and their education in grades P-12. Students will gain a comprehensive understanding of the characteristics of people with special needs in addition to strategies of educating and including all learners in general education and special education settings. Students will research and discuss complex issues related to compliance with state and federal education laws, such as the Individuals with Disabilities Educational Act (IDEA) and the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA) as well learn to navigate special education processes, such as referral, eligibility, reevaluation, and IEPs. This course requires a 15-hour special education field experience component. PREREQUISITE: ED200 </P>

<P>ED 295 Education Capstone 1 credit </P>

<P>This course introduces students to the preparation of the teaching portfolio. Students will prepare and submit a portfolio of teaching artifacts by discussing, analyzing and reflecting on the 9 MoSPE standards for teacher preparation. PRE or COREQUISITE: ED200, ED201, ED270, ED275. (F, SP) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>English </H3>

<P>EN 101 English I 3 credits </P>

<P>An introduction to expository and argumentative writing, emphasizing reading, critical thinking and analytical writing skills. Several short papers are assigned, with emphasis on the writing process. PREREQUISITE: Appropriate placement score or successful completion of DS 025. Written Communications credit (F, SP, SU, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR ENGL 100 – COMPOSITION I </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EN 101W English I with Workshop 6 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed for students who do not meet EN101 English I requirements. An introduction to expository and argumentative writing, emphasizing reading, critical thinking, and analytical writing skills. Several short papers are assigned, with emphasis on the writing process. General education credit. Includes a three credit hour workshop designed to give students customized support to provide just-in-time academic support to help their learning and success of the course. PREREQUISITE: Appropriate placement score.. (F, SP, SU, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>EN 102 English II 3 credits </P>

<P>A continuation of EN 101, emphasizing longer and more impersonal and critical writing forms. Organizational skills are developed through the outline and summary units; analytical reading and critical thinking are stressed. A thorough use of library and online resources is required for the bibliography unit and the final research paper. Written Communications credit. PREREQUISITE: EN 101. (F, SP, SU, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR ENGL 200 – COMPOSITION II </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EN 110 Creative Writing I 3 credits </P>

<P>A beginning course including theory and practical experience in writing short fiction, nonfiction, poetry and the one-act play. Students are required to concentrate on one of the four genres. A major emphasis is on process. Students must submit a number of pieces and revise a portion of their work for possible publication. English elective credit. (DD) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>EN 180 Introduction to Literature 3 credits </P>

<P>This course introduces students to the college-level study of literature by focusing on a thematically arranged selection of literary texts. Students will read poetry, plays, short fiction, and a novel, will respond to the literature analytically and responsively, and will learn to value their own as well as others’ interpretations. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. PREREQUISITE: EN101 or concurrent enrollment in EN101. (OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LITR 100 – INTRODUCTION TO LITERATURE </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EN 196 Literature for Children 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is an introduction to the selection and presentation of literature for preschool and elementary </P>

<P>level children. Students will be exposed to children’s </P>

<P>books in various genres. The course emphasizes the importance of cultural literacy and early and continuous exposure to literature. Does not fulfill Humanities credit. (DD) </P>

<P>EN 211 Studies in Literature 1-3 credits </P>

<P>A special topics course in communication, which may include Women Writers, Popular Literature, or the Broadway Show. The subtitle on schedule of courses for a particular semester indicates specific content. Credit varies from one to three hours. This course may be repeated if the content changes. (DD) </P>

<P>EN 230 English Literature I 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey of some significant works of English literature from Beowulf to Pope. Selected authors within this time frame will vary to offer as wide an overview of genres and perspectives as possible during the semester. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. PREREQUISITE: EN 101 or concurrent enrollment in EN 101. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LITR 103 – BRITISH LITERATURE I </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EN 240 English Literature II 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey of some significant works of English literature from the Romantics to the 20th century. Selected authors within this time frame will vary to offer as wide an overview of formal developments and changes in class, race and gender perspectives as possible during the semester. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. PREREQUISITE: EN 101 or concurrent enrollment in EN </P>

<P>101. EN 230 is not a prerequisite for EN 240. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LITR 104 – BRITISH LITERATURE II </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EN 242 Introduction to Shakespeare 3 credits </P>

<P>This course introduces students to the college-level study of William Shakespeare. We will focus on several of his plays and sonnets as well as taking a look at the Renaissance and how this period shaped his writings. (F, SP, OF, OSP) </P>

<P>EN 251 World Literature: Beginning to the Renaissance 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey of world literature from the beginnings through the Renaissance in Europe. Selections from various cultures are examined for the intellectual trends of the period, for literary and cross-cultural elements, and for artistic design. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. PREREQUISITE: EN101 or concurrent enrollment in EN </P>

<P>101. (DD) MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LITR 200 – WORLD LITERATURE </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EN 252 World Literature: Enlightenment to the Present 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey of world literature from the European Enlightenment through the twentieth century. Selections from various cultures are examined for the intellectual trends of the period, for literary and cross-cultural elements, and for artistic design. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. PREREQUISITE: EN 101 or concurrent enrollment in EN 101. EN 251 is not a prerequisite for EN 252. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LITR 200 – WORLD LITERATURE </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>EN 261 American Literature Before 1865 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey of precolonial, eighteenth century and early nineteenth century literature with emphasis on the varied responses to the contexts of American experience, including voices of the dominant as well as minority cultures. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. PREREQUISITES: EN 101 or concurrent enrollment in EN </P>

<P>101. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LITR 101 – AMERICAN LITERATURE I </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EN 262 Intro to American Literature After 1865 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey of late nineteenth century, modern and contemporary literature with emphasis on the varied responses to the contexts of American experience, including voices of the dominant as well as minority cultures. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. PREREQUISITE: EN 101 or concurrent enrollment in EN </P>

<P>101. EN 261 is not a prerequisite for EN 262. (OF, OSP, </P>

<P>OSU) MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LITR 102 – AMERICAN LITERATURE II </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EN 280 Introduction to Literature 3 credits </P>

<P>NOTE: Effective Spring 2019, the course number will change to EN180.) This course introduces students to the college-level study of literature by focusing on a thematically arranged selection of literary texts. Students will read poetry, plays, short fiction, and a novel, will respond to the literature analytically and responsively, and will learn to value their own as well as others’ interpretations. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. PREREQUISITE: EN101 or current enrollment in EN101. (OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LITR 100 – INTRODUCTION TO LITERATURE </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>EN 282 Introduction to Short Stories 3 credits </P>

<P>This course introduces students to the college-level study of the short story genre. Students will read a variety of short stories and analytically respond to various texts. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LITR 100 – INTRODUCTION TO LITERATURE </P>

<P>EN 296 Young Adult Literature 3 credits </P>

<P>Trends, censorship and the history of young adult literature will be considered as students read and evaluate classic and contemporary literature suitable for middle and senior high school students. PREREQUISITE: EN 101. Does not fulfill Humanities credit. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Foreign Language </H3>

<P>FL 100 Elementary Spanish I 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course in Spanish stressing conversation, basic structural patterns of the language and comprehension of grammatical concepts. Initiates awareness of Hispanic cultures along with the ability to understand simple conversation in Spanish and to communicate basic needs and activities. Not open to students whose native language is Spanish. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LANG 103 – SPANISH I </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>FL 101 Elementary Spanish II 3 credits </P>

<P>Conversation, grammar and reading are stressed. Oral practice and repetition are used as an aid to pronunciation. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. PREREQUISITE: FL100. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LANG 104 – SPANISH II </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>FL 110 Elementary German 4 credits </P>

<P>This is an introductory course in German with an emphasis on speaking the language. Pronunciation, simple grammatical usage, syntax, vocabulary and idioms in carefully graded reading material. This is a first course in basic German language; not open to students whose native language is German. (DD) </P>

<P>FL 111 Elementary German II 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a continuation of FL 110 Elementary German I, using the same text and classroom materials. Conversation, grammar and reading are stressed. Oral practice and repetition are used as an aid to pronunciation. PREREQUISITE: FL 110. (DD) </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>FL 120 Elementary French I 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course in French emphasizing conversational speaking and comprehension, pronunciation, and the accumulation of basic vocabulary. Simple grammatical concepts are also introduced. Not open to students whose native language is French. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LANG 101 – FRENCH I </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>FL 122 Elementary French II 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a continuation of FL 120, Elementary French I, using the same text and classroom materials. PREREQUISITE: FL 120. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR LANG 102 – FRENCH II </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>FL 155 American Sign Language I (ASL I) 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is an introduction to the receptive and expressive usage of American Sign Language (vocabulary, finger spelling and numbers). The purpose of this course is to enable the student to communicate with the deaf and hard of hearing people who use signs. This course will help prepare persons interested in preparing for beginning entry into interpreter programs. The history of American Sign Language will also be explored. (DD) </P>

<P>FL 255 American Sign Language II (ASL II) 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a continuation of American Sign Language emphasizing on expanding the receptive and expressive sign vocabulary and usage of conversation. The purpose of this course is to give a stronger foundation to the student to communicate with the deaf and hard of hearing community. This course will help persons prepare for entry into interpreter programs. PREREQUISITE: FL 155. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Geography </H3>

<P>GE 106 Introduction to World Geography 3 credits </P>

<P>This course surveys the world’s major developed </P>

<P>regions and their physical and human characteristics from a geographic perspective. The physical environment includes landforms and climate while the human landscape is characterized by language, religion, population characteristics and economic development. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. (OSE, SO) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR GEOG 101 – WORLD REGIONAL GEOGRAPHY </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Health Information Management </H3>

<P>HM 125 Medical Coding I 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide students an overview of clinical vocabularies, coding classification systems, and nomenclatures. The International Classification of Diseases, 10th revision, Clinical Modification (ICD-10CM) will be explained with application of chapter-specific diagnosis code assignments. PREREQUISITES: AH 160 &amp; AH 125. (OF) </P>

<P>HM 225 Medical Coding II 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide students an overview of procedural coding guidelines and structure of the Current Procedural Terminology (CPT), Health care Common Procedure Coding System (HCPCS), and the International Classification of Diseases 10th edition, Procedure Coding System (ICD-10-PCS). Inpatient guidelines for reporting diagnoses and procedures will be reviewed. PREREQUISITES: AH 160, HM 125. (OSP) </P>

<P>HM 226 Electronic Health Systems 3 credits </P>

<P>This course introduces students to electronic health systems and applications such as clinical, administrative, and management support systems. Social and government initiatives for implementing electronic health record systems along with confidential and security measures will be explored. Students will gain experience in completing an electronic health record simulation. PREREQUISITES: BT 160 (OSP) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>History </H3>

<P>HI 101 Western Civilization to 1700 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a survey of the social, intellectual, religious, political and economic institutions and traditions developed by groups of people who first lived around the Mediterranean Sea and branched out into Europe and the Western Hemisphere. The time span of the course is from prehistory to approximately 1715. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (F, OSP) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR WCIV 101 – WESTERN CIVILIZATION I </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>HI 102 Western Civilization Since 1700 3 credits </P>

<P>A continuation of the survey of institutions, traditions and history of Western Civilization with emphasis on European developments and their interaction with non-western cultures and traditions. The time span for this course is from approximately 1715 to the present. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (SP, OF) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR WCIV 102 – WESTERN CIVILIZATION II </P>

<P>HI 104 American History Since 1877 3 credits </P>

<P>A continuation of HI 103. A survey course considering national growth and development, and the constantly broadening sphere of American participation in world affairs from Reconstruction to the present time. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. Civics credit (meets the Constitution requirement). PREREQUISITE: Appropriate placement score or successful completion of EN101W. </P>

<P>(F) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR HIST 102 – AMERICAN HISTORY II </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>HI 203 World History to 1600 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory survey course of the history of the world and of world civilizations from ancient times to the Renaissance and Reformation era. This course includes examinations of the social, cultural, political, religious, and economic institutions and traditions of pre-industrial civilizations with emphasis on regional and global interactions. The focus of this course is the development of civilizations prior to the Industrial Revolution. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR HIST 201 – WORLD HISTORY I </P>
</Sect>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<Sect>
<P>HI 204 World History Since 1600 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory survey course of the history of the world and of world civilizations since the Renaissance/Reformation era. This course includes examinations of the social, cultural, political, religious, and economic institutions and traditions of industrial civilizations with emphasis on regional and global interactions. The focus of this course is the development of civilizations during and following the Industrial Revolution, including its byproducts such as: industrialization, democratization, imperialism, global wars, globalization, and modernization. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR HIST 202 – WORLD HISTORY II </P>

<P>HI 103 American History to 1877 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey course of the history of the United States covering European backgrounds, the colonial and Constitution periods, national expansion and development through Reconstruction. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. Civics credit (meets the Constitution requirement). PREREQUISITE: Appropriate placement score or successful completion of EN101W. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR HIST 101 – AMERICAN HISTORY I </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Humanities </H3>

<P>HU 110 Humanities: Pre-Renaissance 3 credits </P>

<P>An integrated course in western culture encompassing an introduction to literature, painting, music, sculpture and architecture, as well as the discipline of philosophy presented as interrelated and integrated manifestations of human creativity. Employing methodologies associated with the study of cultural and intellectual history, the course seeks to create an understanding of why we are the way we are. (DD) </P>

<P>HU 111 Humanities: Renaissance to Present 3 credits </P>

<P>An integrated course in western culture from Renaissance period to the present. The course encompasses an introduction to literature, painting, music, sculpture and architecture, as well as the discipline of philosophy presented as interrelated and integrated manifestation of human creativity. Employing methodologies associated with the study of cultural and intellectual history, the course seeks to create an understanding of why we are the way we are. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Manufacturing Technology </H3>

<P>MF 104 Applied Technical Math 3 credits </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is to develop skills in basic math areas, such as measurement in standard and metric units, conversions, scientific and engineering notation, ratio and proportion, decimals, fractions, percentages, formulas, equations, basic geometry, Pythagorean Theory, right triangle trigonometry and introductory statistical process control. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 104W Applied Technical Math with Workshop 6 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed for students who do not meet MF 104 Applied Technical Math requirements. The purpose of this course is to develop skills in basic math areas, such as measurement in standard and metric units, conversions, scientific and engineering notation, ratio and proportion, decimals, fractions, percentages, formulas, equations, basic geometry, Pythagorean Theory, right triangle trigonometry and introductory statistical process control. Includes a three credit hour workshop designed to give students customized support to provide just-in-time academic support to help their learning and success of the course. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 111 Industrial Print Reading 3 credits </P>

<P>This course covers reading and interpreting basic blueprints commonly found in manufacturing. Practical application of fractions and geometry. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 120 Introduction to Electricity &amp; Electronics credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide a solid foundation for the study of electricity/ electronics by introducing the fundamental laws of scientific atomic structure, electricity and electrical safety. It builds upon those fundamentals by the study of Ohm’s Law, current, voltage, resistance, power sources, and DC measuring instruments. An introduction to complete series, parallel and series-parallel circuits, the laws, mathematical formulas, and methods used to analyze these circuits are introduced in this class. A study of how AC voltages and currents are generated, introducing the science of magnetism, and the effect of AC on electronic components such as inductors and capacitors, AC testing procedures will be emphasized. PREREQUISITE DS048 or appropriate math placement score (DD) </P>

<P>MF 121 Industrial Electricity (DC) 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is an extensive hands-on study of industrial electricity. Students will study electricity and its </P>

<P>sources, resistors (as simulated circuit loads), Ohm’s </P>

<P>Law, series circuits, parallel circuits, combination circuits, meters, conductors, insulators and batteries. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 122 Basic Electricity I 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a hands-on study of fundamental electricity principles and applications. Student will study electricity and its applications using resistors (as </P>

<P>simulated circuit loads), Ohm’s Law, series circuits, </P>

<P>parallel circuits, and combination circuits. The course will also include electrical wiring techniques, system installation, an introduction into raceways, conduit bending, conductors, disconnects, and over-current protection. (Lab fee) (DD) </P>

<P>MF 125 Industrial Electricity (AC) 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is an extensive hands-on study of Industrial Electricity. Students will study magnetism, induction, AC voltage and current, inductors and capacitors. PREREQUISITE: MF 121 or MF 122. (DD) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>MF 126 Basic Electricity II 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a level two, hands-on study of electricity principles and applications. Students will study grounding and bonding of electrical systems, motor theory, application, and motor controls. PREREQUISITE: MF 121 or MF 122. (Lab fee) (DD) </P>

<P>MF 128 Motor Controls 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is an extensive hands-on study of basic motor control circuits; including electrical symbols, line diagrams, manual motor starters, magnetic motor starters, time delay circuits, motor reversing circuits, electro-mechanical and solid-state rays, photoelectric and proximity controls, preventive maintenance and trouble shooting. (Lab fee) (DD) </P>

<P>MF 141 Programmable Logic Controllers 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides students the basic knowledge of </P>

<P>Programmable Logic Controllers (PLC’s) and their </P>

<P>application in industry today. This is a hands-on study of PLC programming applications such as sequencing, timers, counter, hydraulic and pneumatic actuators, indicator lamps and motor controls. At the completion of the course, students will be able to program and troubleshoot a PLC for typical industry applications using Allen-Bradley Control Logix software. (Lab fee) (DD) </P>

<P>MF 145 Basic Fluid Power 3 credits </P>

<P>This course introduces the basic components and functions of hydraulic and pneumatic systems. Topics include standard symbols, pumps, control valves, control assemblies, actuators, maintenance procedures, and switching and control devices. Upon completion, students should be able to understand the operation of a fluid power system, including design, application, and troubleshooting. (Lab fee) (DD) </P>

<P>MF 150 Principles of Safety 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides students the basic knowledge of OSHA safety requirements and the skills required to ensure a safe and healthy workplace. Students will develop an understanding of safety concerns, issues, and compliance in a work environment. The course also provides an introduction to manufacturing, customer communication skills, high performance production teams and work-readiness skills. This course meets the safety pre-requisite as part of the Wind program. A Manufacturing Skills Standards Council certificate will be provided pending a successful final assessment of this course. The industry-recognized MSSC-Certified Production Technician certification requires successful completion of all four modules and the final assessment. (Lab fee) (DD) </P>

<P>MF 155 Principles of Maintenance Awareness 3 credits </P>

<P>This on-line course provides insights into the basics of good maintenance practices for manufacturing. Students will also develop an understanding of electrical, mechanical and fluid power systems. This course is not a maintenance training course, but rather targets production workers who want to excel in a high-performance manufacturing setting. A Manufacturing Skills Standards Council certificate will be provided pending a successful final assessment of this course. The industry-recognized MSSC-Certified Production Technician certification requires successful completion of all four modules and the final assessment. (Lab fee) (DD) </P>

<P>MF 160 Principles of Quality Practices 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides knowledge and skills related to effective quality systems used in today’s manufacturing industry. Students will develop an understanding of quality philosophy, practices, and methods as well as quality audits, tools, and blueprint reading. Manufacturing Skills Standards Council certificate will be provided pending a successful final assessment of this course. The industry-recognized MSSC-Certified Production Technician certification requires successful completion of all four modules and the final assessment. (Lab fee) (DD) </P>

<P>MF 165 Principles of Manufacturing Processes and Production 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides students a broad understanding of manufacturing sub-industries and their related products, processes, challenges and best practices. Students will develop an understanding of common production principles, processes and practices, as well inventory management, packaging, and distribution. A Manufacturing Skills Standards Council certificate will be provided pending a successful final assessment of this course. The industry-recognized MSSC-Certified Production Technician certification requires successful completion of all four modules and the final assessment. (Lab fee) (DD) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>MF 170 Industrial Mechanics 3 credits </P>

<P>This course presents fundamentals of maintenance and repair on industrial equipment including fans, motors, and conveyors. Belt and chain drives, lubrication, replacement of seals and bearings, and shaft alignment using manual dial and laser methods will be covered. Correct application and selection of hand and power tools. (lab fee) PREREQUISITE: MF155 (DD) </P>

<P>MF 205 Digital Electronics 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides students with advanced electronic skills used in maintaining, installation and development of the complex equipment used in the modern manufacturing environment. Topics covered include number systems, logic gates, flip-flops, registers and counters, analog-to-digital, and digital-to-analog data conversions. Prior completion of Vo-Tech industrial maintenance program and/or appropriate prior experience recommended. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 220 AutoCAD I 3 credits </P>

<P>This is the first course in the use of the Computer Aided Drafting software AutoCAD. It includes development in the skills of File, Draw, Text and Editing commands while working in the Cartesian workspace. File handling and plotting are stressed. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 221 AutoCAD II 3 credits </P>

<P>A continuation of AutoCAD I (MF 220) in the study of application of AutoCAD in the industrial world. To include the topics of three-dimensional modeling, Scaling, Paper Space, Geometric Calculator and Customization of AutoCAD. PREREQUISITE: MF 220 (DD) </P>

<P>MF 225 Advanced Programmable Logic Controllers 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides students with the advanced skills and applications of Programmable Logic Controllers used in increasing quantities in the industrial process today. Training in timers, counters, and data manipulation will be covered. PREREQUISITE: MF141 or instructor permission. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 227 Introduction to 3D Printing 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides awareness and familiarization with 3D printing, an additive manufacturing process. Students will learn how it can be used in rapid pro-typing, customizable product lines and individualized medical appliances. Students will also learn how to </P>

<P>become “makers” through the use of 3D modeling </P>

<P>software and 3D printers. Students will design and then print physical objects using what they learn in the course. Students will also participate in educational outreach at North Central Missouri College and the community to pass on some of what they have learned. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 235 Industrial Robotics 3 credits </P>

<P>This class provides students with the skills and applications of Industrial Robots used in increasing quantities in the manufacturing process today. Programming, integration into current systems, flexible manufacturing and production topics, as applied to robots, will be covered in this course. MF 220 and MF 221 may be substituted with advisor approval. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 240 Advanced Motor Controls 3 credits </P>

<P>This class provides students with advanced motor control skills, control panel wiring, frequency drives, timers and counters will be studied. PREREQUISITE: Completion of AVTS program or instructor permission. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 251 Statistical Process Control 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of Statistical Process Control to improve the quality of products in industry. Course discusses the need for S.P.C. instruction in the use of X and R charts, attribute charts and methods of chart analysis. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 260 Maintenance Management 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a study of modern maintenance management practices, reliability statistical applications, practical preventive and predictive maintenance techniques, Total Productive Maintenance (TPM), computer maintenance management techniques, total Productive Maintenance (TPM), computer maintenance management systems, (CMMS), failure prevention and productivity improvements, as well as basic interpersonal management skills. (DD) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>MF 271 Manufacturing Technology Internship 3 credits </P>

<P>The internship is designed to give the Manufacturing and Applied Technology student practical working experience following a pre-approved training plan arrived at cooperatively by the employer, student and instructor. A minimum of 45 contact hours is required for every hour of credit. (DD) </P>

<P>MF 299 Special Topics in Manufacturing Technology 1-5 credits </P>

<P>This course is offered on various special topics, with specific content indicated by course subtitle. Credit hours are determined by contact hours, activities and assignments as appropriate to content. The course may be repeated if the content varies. PREREQUISITE: Consent of instructor. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Mathematics </H3>

<P>Math and Physical Science courses require placement scores taken in the last three years. College preparatory courses in mathematics can be found in the Developmental Studies section. </P>

<P>MT 110 Intermediate Algebra 3 credits </P>

<P>Student learning objectives include: basic algebra fundamentals, linear equations, linear inequalities, linear functions and their graphs, systems of equations and inequalities, operations with polynomial functions and factoring, quadratic equations and functions and their graphs, operations with rational expressions, and radical equations. This course will use algebra to model and solve real-world problems. PREREQUISITE: DS 049 or appropriate placement test scores taken within the last three years. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MT 110W Intermediate Algebra with Workshop 6 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed for students who do not meet MT 110 Intermediate Algebra requirements. Student learning objectives include: basic algebra fundamentals, linear equations and linear inequalities, linear functions and their graphs, systems of equations and inequalities, operation with polynomial functions and factoring, quadratic equations and functions and their graphs, operations with rational expressions, and radical equations. This course will use algebra to model and solve real-world problems. This is a prerequisite course for College Algebra and Math Concepts. Includes a three credit hour workshop designed to give students customized support to provide just-in-time academic support to help their learning and success in the course. Prerequisites: DS048 or appropriate math placement test score taken within the last three years. Three credit hours will count in some academic plans. (F, SP) </P>

<P>MT 119 Contemporary Math 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey of mathematics used in our world, including fundamentals of statistics, problem-solving strategies and decision making, and proportional reasoning. Deeper understanding of information presented in mathematical terms through critical thinking in quantitative-based situations adds to a student’s capabilities. Other topics will be considered as time permits. Mathematical Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program math requirements. PREREQUISITE: DS049 or appropriate math placement score, taken in last three years. (F, SP) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR MATH 120 – Mathematical Reasoning and Modeling </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>MT 119W Contemporary Math with Workshop 6 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed for students who do not meet MT 119 Contemporary Mathematics requirements. A survey of mathematics used in our world, including fundamentals of statistics, problem-solving strategies and decision making, and proportional reasoning. Deeper understanding of information presented in mathematical terms through critical thinking in quantitative-based situations adds to a student’s capabilities. Other topics will be considered as time permits. Includes a three credit hour workshop designed to give students customized assistance to provide just-in-time academic support to help their learning and success in the course. PREREQUISITE: Appropriate placement test score taken within the last three years. Three credit hours will count toward degree requirements in some academic plans. (F) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR MATH 120 – Mathematical Reasoning and Modeling </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>MT 121 Math Concepts 3 credits </P>

<P>Student learning objectives include: basic concepts of set theory, numeration and mathematical systems, number theory, real number operations, applications of fractions, decimals, and percentages, basic concepts of algebra, graphs, functions, systems of equations and inequalities, and geometry. Recommended for Elementary Education majors. Mathematical Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program math requirements. PREREQUISITE: MT 110 or appropriate math placement score within the last three </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>years. (SP, OSU) MOTR Equivalent: MOTR MATH 120 – Mathematical Reasoning and Modeling </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>MT 122 College Algebra 3 credits </P>

<P>Student learning objectives include: graphing, analyzing, and solving linear, quadratic, polynomial, rational, logarithmic and exponential functions and equations, solving systems of equations and inequalities, matrices, and other topics as time permits. Mathematical Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program math requirements. PREREQUISITE: MT110 or appropriate math placement score no older than three years. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR MATH 130 – PRE-CALCULUS ALGEBRA </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>MT 122W College Algebra with Workshop 6 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed for students who do not meet MT 122 College Algebra requirements. Student learning objectives include: graphing, analyzing, and solving linear, quadratic, polynomial, rational, logarithmic and exponential functions and equations, solving systems of equations and inequalities, matrices and other topics as time permits. A three credit hour workshop designed to give students customized, just-in-time academic support to help their learning and success of the course is included. Mathematical Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program math requirements. PREREQUISITE: DS049 or appropriate placement score. Appropriate math placement score, taken within the last three years. Three credit hours will count toward degree requirements. (F, SP) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR MATH 130 – PRE-CALCULUS ALGEBRA </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>MT 123 Finite Mathematics 3 credits </P>

<P>This course utilizes a practical application approach to the following: linear and quadratic equations, graphs and functions including exponential and logarithmic functions, mathematics of finance, annuities, sinking funds and mortgages, linear programming, counting methods and probability, basic statistics, and other topics as time permits. PREREQUISITE: MT 122 or appropriate placement test scores. ACT or placement scores must be less than three years old. (DD) </P>

<P>MT 125 Elementary Statistics 3 credits </P>

<P>This course provides students with a valuable framework in which to learn and apply statistical concepts. Student learning outcomes include but are not limited to: the nature of probability and statistics, frequency distributions and graphs, data description, confidence intervals, hypothesis testing, correlation and regression. Mathematical Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program math requirements. PREREQUISITE: DS049 or appropriate math placement test score taken within the last three years. (F, SP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR MATH 110 – STATISTICAL REASONING </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>MT125W Elementary Statistics with Workshop 6 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed for students who do not meet requirements to take MT125 Elementary Statistics. Course provides students with valuable framework in which to learn and apply statistical concepts. Student learning outcomes include but are not limited to the nature of probability and statistics, frequency distributions and graphs, data description, confidence intervals, hypothesis testing, and correlation and regression. Includes a 3 credit hour workshop designed to give students customized, just-in-time academic support. Mathematical Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program math requirements. PREREQUISITE: DS 048 or appropriate math placement test score taken within the last three years. Three credit hours will count toward degree requirements in some academic plans. (SP) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR MATH 110 – STATISTICAL REASONING </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>MT 132 Trigonometry 3 credits </P>

<P>Student learning objectives include: geometric foundations of trigonometry, unit circle, graphs of trigonometric functions, identities, equations and inequalities, inverse functions, law of sines and cosines, </P>

<P>vectors, complex numbers and DeMoivre’s theorem. </P>

<P>PREREQUISITE: MT 110 Intermediate Algebra or appropriate placement test scores. Math placement scores must be less than three years old. (DD) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>MT 148 Pre-Calculus 5 credits </P>

<P>This is a preparatory course for the Calculus sequence. Student learning outcomes include: algebraic, trigonometric, exponential and logarithmic equations and inequalities; systems of equations and inequalities; matrices; solutions of triangles; inverses of algebraic and trigonometric functions, trigonometric identities; and an introduction to analytic geometry. Mathematical Sciences credit; consult transfer catalog for specific program math requirements. PREREQUISITE: MT 110 with a grade of A or B, or appropriate placement score taken within last three years. MT 122 is recommended. Three credit hours will count toward degree requirements in some academic plans. (F) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR MATH 150 – PRE-CALCULUS </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>MT 150 Geometry &amp; Calculus I 5 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed for students in engineering, economics, life and physical sciences, and mathematics, focusing on functions, limits and their properties, differentiation and integration, including logarithmic and exponential functions. Mathematical Sciences credit. PREREQUISITES: MT 148 or both MT 122 and MT 132 or instructor permission. (SP) </P>

<P>MT 222 Discrete Mathematics 4 credits </P>

<P>This course is an introduction to discrete models. Topics include: sets, symbolic logic, relations, combinatorics, mathematical induction, probability, matrices, graph theory and Boolean algebra. Mathematical Sciences credit. PREREQUISITES: MT 122 or MT 148. (DD) </P>

<P>MT 250 Geometry &amp; Calculus II 5 credits </P>

<P>This course is a continuation of Geometry &amp; Calculus I. It includes techniques and applications of the integral, sequences, series, polar functions, conic sections and additional topics as time permits. Mathematical Sciences credit. PREREQUISITE: MT 150 with a grade of C or better. (F) </P>

<P>MT 260 Geometry and Calculus III 5 credits </P>

<P>This course is a continuation of Geometry and Calculus </P>

<P>II. It includes the study of solid analytic geometry, vectors and vector calculus, partial differentiation, and multiple integrals. Mathematical Sciences credit. PREREQUISITES: MT 250 with a grade of C or better. (SP) </P>

<P>MT 270 Special Topics in Mathematics 1-3 credits </P>

<P>This course is offered on various special topics, with specific content indicated by course subtitle. Credit hours are determined by contact hours, activities and assignments as appropriate to content. The course may be repeated if the content varies. PREREQUISITE: Instructor permission. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Medical Laboratory Technician </H3>

<P>Medical Laboratory Technician classes are restricted to students accepted to the MHPC MLT Program. </P>

<P>ML 150 Introduction to Laboratory Science Methods 2 credits </P>

<P>This course orients the student to the concepts encompassed in the laboratory environment, to include safe specimen handling, testing procedures, reporting results, basic quality control, laboratory organization and professionalism. (F) </P>

<P>ML 210 Immunology 3 credits </P>

<P>The course consists of the principles and theories of antigen and antibody reactions and the immune system as related to diagnostic serologic procedures. (F) </P>

<P>ML 220 Clinical Chemistry and Urinalysis 5 credits </P>

<P>This course introduces the student to methods of analysis of chemical components found in the human body, the testing methodologies for those constituents and the results as applied to normal and abnormal disease states. (SP) </P>

<P>ML 250 Hematology and Coagulation 5 credits </P>

<P>This course studies the cellular structures in blood, normal and abnormal cell development, alterations present in disease and the mechanisms of coagulation. </P>

<P>(F) </P>

<P>ML 260 Phlebotomy 2 credits </P>

<P>This course covers various procedures in performing venipuncture and other specialized collection techniques in addition to laws and regulations for safe phlebotomy practices. (F) </P>

<P>ML 270 Immunohematology 5 credits </P>

<P>This course consists of concepts, applications and discrepancies of blood group testing, screening and cross match procedures and identifying unexpected antibodies. </P>

<P>(SP) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>ML 280 Clinical Microbiology 4 credits </P>

<P>This course consists of the role of pathogenic bacteria and other microorganisms which will include bacterial culturing, differentiation and identification of human normal flora and disease-causing microorganisms. (SP) </P>

<P>ML 290 Parasitology, Mycology and Virology 1 credit </P>

<P>This course introduces the student to parasites, fungus and viruses and their role in human health and disease. (SP) </P>

<P>ML 291 Hematology and Coagulation Practicum 2 credits </P>

<P>Supervised clinical practice coordinated by the Consortium, in the hematology lab of selected clinical affiliates. (F) </P>

<P>ML 292 Clinical Chemistry Practicum 2 credits </P>

<P>Supervised clinical practice coordinated by the Consortium, in the clinical chemistry lab of selected clinical affiliates. (SU) </P>

<P>ML 293 Clinical Microbiology Practicum 2 credits </P>

<P>Supervised clinical practice coordinated by the Consortium, in the microbiology lab of selected clinical affiliates. (SU) </P>

<P>ML 294 Clinical Immunohematology Practicum 2 credits </P>

<P>Supervised clinical practice coordinated by the Consortium, in the immunohematology lab of selected clinical affiliates. (SU) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Music </H3>

<P>MU 101 Applied Voice 1 credit </P>

<P>This course is for students who have little or no training in voice. The class will help students develop and understand vocal technique and basic musicianship. (DD) </P>

<P>MU 103 Chorus I 1 credit </P>

<P>A vocal ensemble for all interested in choral singing. Music representative of all periods, and both secular </P>

<P>and sacred is used at the director’s discretion. This class </P>

<P>is called upon to perform on various occasions. (DD) MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PERF102C – MUSIC PERFORMANCE -CHOIR </P>

<P>MU 104 Chorus II 1 credit </P>

<P>A vocal ensemble for all interested in choral singing. The following musical skills for ensemble singing will be stressed: proper breathing, pleasant vocal production, blend and balance, expansion of range, good intonation, ear training and sight-reading. This chorus builds upon the skill development in Chorus I. Participation may include public performances on various occasions. (DD) </P>

<P>MU 109 Music Appreciation 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course concerned with the elements of music, the important musical masterpieces and the significant composers up to the present age. A portion of the class time is devoted to listening to recordings. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (F, SP, SU, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR MUSC 100 – MUSIC APPRECIATION </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>MU 110 Applied Music 1 credit </P>

<P>Private instruction for credit. Students are expected to pay a variable fee to the private instructor over and above the cost of course credit. Students must complete 30 hours of instruction to earn one credit hour. Maximum 4 credits, 1 credit per semester. This course does not meet any general education requirements. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Occupational Therapy Assistant </H3>

<P>Occupational Therapy classes are restricted to students accepted into the OTA program. </P>

<P>OT 200 Foundations of Occupational Therapy 4 credits </P>

<P>This course presents an introduction to occupational therapy including history, philosophical base, values, ethics, practice framework, and clinical reasoning. Students will learn selected theories and frames of reference as they pertain to interventions in mental health, physical disabilities, pediatrics, and community practice areas. An overview of the occupational therapy process, including assessment, treatment planning, treatment implementation, and discontinuation of intervention will be presented. Role delineation and collaboration of the occupational therapy assistant with other occupational therapy and health care personnel are discussed. (SP) </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>

<P>OT 205 Medical Conditions in Occupational Therapy 3 OT 220 Pediatric and Adolescent Practice 4 credits </P>

<Sect>
<P>credits </P>

<P>This course will provide a framework for students to learn about common medical conditions seen by occupational therapy practitioners and to facilitate learning of these conditions from an occupational therapy perspective. It is not intended to emphasize treatment of a diagnosis; however, students will learn about specific factors unique to given conditions that </P>

<P>may impact an individual’s occupational roles and </P>

<P>functions. These factors must be understood and analyzed regarding the relative impact on the individuals’ occupational performance. The knowledge gained from this course in a necessary pre-requisite to Physical Disabilities Practice. (SP) </P>

<P>OT 210 Analysis of Occupations 2 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to foster a beginning exposure to individuals experiencing a variety of physical or mental disabilities, including caregivers of individuals with disabilities, through community experiences. Through these experiences, students will develop skills in observation, analysis, interview, assessment, and data collection, and relational skills. Students will complete writing assignments with an emphasis on their observations, analysis, and performance of human occupation across the lifespan, with an emphasis on contextual factors impacting occupational performance. Through the written assignments, students will learn the style of professional writing required for OTAs. Professional and therapeutic relationships will be emphasized throughout the course. (SP) </P>

<P>OT 215 Mental Health and Psychosocial Practice 4 credits </P>

<P>This course presents the role of the Occupational Therapy Assistant in the psychosocial area of Occupational Therapy practice. Students will learn selected frames of reference, and explore the effects of psychosocial dysfunction on areas of occupation. Students will learn skills necessary to assess, implement and document intervention in a variety of mental health settings. Client factors, including culture and diversity, therapeutic interactions and methods are studied. Students will develop skills in administering individual and group interventions, professional communication, conflict negotiation, and advocacy. Course activities, site visits and PN fieldwork opportunities will enable students to participate in and apply psychosocial principles to practice. (SP) Treatment of pediatric and adolescent conditions. Normal and delayed development of the infant, child and adolescent are explored. The lab component incorporates theoretical principles and provides opportunities for students to develop assessment, intervention planning and implementation, and documentation skills to address a range of childhood sensory-motor, cognitive and psychosocial performance deficits. Students will learn to adapt the environment, tools, materials, and occupations to meet the self-care, work/play, and leisure needs of the pediatric and adolescent population. Lab activities, site visits and PN fieldwork opportunities will enable students to participate in and apply pediatric and adolescent treatment principles to practice. Lecture and laboratory. (SP) </P>

<P>OT 250 Functional Kinesiology 2 credits </P>

<P>In this course, students use and apply their knowledge of anatomy and physiology to study muscle groups and their function relative to performing various activities. Analysis of functional movement patterns required for work, self-care, play, and leisure activities are emphasized. Manual muscle testing, range of motion, goniometry and basic transfer skills are practiced. Principles of energy conservation, joint protection and work simplification are presented. Prevention, health maintenance and safety procedures relevant to functional mobility are reviewed. (SU) </P>

<P>OT 255 Physical Disabilities Practice 4 credits </P>

<P>The course provides in-depth opportunities for students to develop assessment, intervention planning, intervention, and documentation skills to address a wide range of adult and geriatric physical disabilities and conditions typically treated by occupational therapy and fractures and joint replacements, head injury, dementias. The use of splinting, orthotics, modalities, and assistive technology in treatment will also be presented. Students will learn to adapt the environment, tools, materials, and occupations to meet the self-care, work/play, and leisure needs of the adult and geriatric population. Lab activities, site visits, and PN fieldwork opportunities will enable students to participate in and apply physical disabilities treatment principles to practice. (SU) </P>

<P>OT 260 Community Practice 3 credits </P>

<P>Class activities, site visits and PN fieldwork opportunities will enable students to participate in and apply occupational therapy assessment and intervention principles to a wide range of community settings including vocational, vocational rehabilitation, home health, and emerging community practice areas. </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>Emphasis will be on community settings in the students’ </P>

<P>state and geographic region. The course also provides a broad exposure to the social, political, legislative, economic and cultural factors that influence service delivery. (SU) </P>

<P>OT 265 Ethics, Management and Leadership 3 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on the OTA role in managing and directing occupational therapy services. II covers ethical provision of services, departmental operations, program development, supervisory requirements, personnel development and supervision, professional team building, quality assurance, compliance with regulations, reimbursement and national and state credentialing requirements. Techniques for developing a resume and job interview skills are practiced. The importance and responsibility for on-going OTA professional development, ethical practice, contributing to research and evidence based practice, attention to emerging practice issues and areas, and international perspectives are explored. (SU) </P>

<P>OT 270 Professional Skills 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to foster practical professional skills in critical thinking, using literature to make evidence-based practice decisions and recommendations, and using theory to guide practice, all through the completion of a professional portfolio. (SU) </P>

<P>OT 290 OTA Fieldwork A 8 credits </P>

<P>Full-time clinical fieldwork experience in mental health, physical disabilities, geriatric, pediatric and/or community based practice working under the supervision of an OTR and/or COTA. Focus is on achieving entry-level competence in planning and implementing interventions. (SU) </P>

<P>OT 295 OTA Fieldwork B 8 credits </P>

<P>Full-time clinical fieldwork experience in mental health, physical disabilities, geriatric, pediatric and/or community based practice working under the supervision of an OTR and/or COTA. Focus is on achieving entry-level competence in planning and implementing interventions. (SU) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Pharmacy Technician </H3>

<P>PM 101 Pharmacy Calculations 3 credits </P>

<P>Accuracy in calculation is essential to safe pharmaceutical practice. This course will help broaden a </P>

<P>student’s knowledge in pharmacy calculations thus </P>

<P>allowing them to provide assistance to pharmacists. You will master accurate computation in dispensing, pricing, systems of measure, introduction to compounding (focuses on the art of making and preparing medication) and parenteral products as they apply in pharmacy. Study focus is on core concepts and the foundation of what every pharmacy technician needs to know to ensure safe medication administration. Mathematics skills, critical thinking, therapeutic communications in community-based health care system are included. (OSO) </P>

<P>PM 105 Pharmacy Practice I 4 credits </P>

<P>You will be introduced to the role of pharmacy, the pharmacist and the pharmacy technician in the health care delivery system. The course incorporates the history of pharmacy practice, law &amp; ethics, terminology, routes, dosage formulations, Anatomy &amp; Physiology, medications and operations of community based and institutional pharmacies. Cultural and ethnic variations in relationship to medications in a multidisciplinary setting are addressed. Emphasis is placed on committing to lifelong learning in a continually changing environment. Lecture and laboratory. (OSO) </P>

<P>PM 205 Pharmacy Practice II 4 credits </P>

<P>You will be introduced to the role of pharmacy, the pharmacist and the pharmacy technician in the health care delivery system. The course incorporates the history of pharmacy practice, laws and ethics, terminology, routes, dosage information, A &amp; P, medications, and operations of community based and institutional pharmacies. Cultural and ethnic variations in relationship to medications in a multi-disciplinary setting are addressed. Emphasis is placed on committing to lifelong learning in a continually changing environment. Pre-requisites: PM 101 &amp; PM 105. (OSO) </P>

<P>PM 220 Pharmacy Technician Internship 4 credits </P>

<P>This course teaches the Pharmacy Technician student the principles and importance of pharmacy technician procedures: accurate computation in dispensing, pricing, systems of measure, compounding mixtures and solutions, preparing parenteral products, aseptic techniques, law &amp; ethics and operations of community based and institutional pharmacies. </P>
</Sect>

<P>The internship is to provide the student with real-life PE 105 Health Education 2 credits </P>

<Sect>
<P>experiences with an opportunity to practice learned theory and clinical skills. Students will work under supervision at the internship site. The benefits to the students include the opportunity to practice learned theoretical and clinical skills, by being exposed to different situations and to have the opportunity to demonstrate (at their internship site) their abilities, which could lead to future employment. </P>

<P>During the 90 hours of the internship, your relationship with other professionals and consumers of services in hospitals and the community will be emphasized. PREREQUISITE: PM 205 (may be taken concurrently). (OSO) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Philosophy </H3>

<P>PH 101 Introduction to Ethics 3 credits </P>

<P>This course examines the major theories of value and moral obligation, and how they illuminate such contemporary issues as abortion, euthanasia, sexual morality, discrimination, medical ethics, privacy, individual freedom, violence and war. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PHIL 102 – INTRODUCTION TO ETHICS </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>PH 102 Introduction to Philosophy 3 credits </P>

<P>This study of philosophy will expose the student to critical thinking and help in the understanding of such fundamental questions as these: How do we know? (Epistemology); what is real? (Metaphysics); and what is of value? (Axiology). Readings from the major philosophers are included. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (F, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PHIL 102 – INTRODUCTION TO PHILOSOPHY </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Physical Education </H3>

<P>A maximum of two credit hours of physical education activities will apply toward any degree. </P>

<P>PE 104 Varsity Sports I 1 credit </P>

<P>A course for students participating in intercollegiate sports. (PE activity credit) PREREQUISITE: Consent of the coach. (F, SP) A course that addresses personal health concerns from a holistic standpoint and emphasizes strategies to adapt or change our behavior to promote health and prevent disease. (Not applicable to medical curriculum). (F, OF, OSP) </P>

<P>PE 106 Weight Training 1 credit </P>

<P>The course is designed to teach students weight lifting techniques, different weight training systems, a variety of exercises, muscle groups and how each affects the body. Weight lifting terminology will also be introduced. (PE activity credit) (DD) </P>

<P>PE 112 Sports Officiating 2 credits </P>

<P>A course designed to prepare students to pass the officials test for the MSHSAA standards of basketball and softball. The course will address officiating ethics, sports psychology and strategies. Does not meet physical education activity requirement. (DD) </P>

<P>PE 115 Team Sports I 1 credit </P>

<P>An activity course designed to teach scoring, proper technique, rules and strategy for softball, flag football and soccer. (PE activity credit) (DD) </P>

<P>PE 117 Personal Fitness 1 credit </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is to provide the student instruction in individual fitness and wellness. Emphasis is placed on cardiovascular endurance, muscular strength and muscular endurance. Other components will include designing and implementing a personal exercise prescription in relation to individual goals. May be taken up to two times for a total of two credit hours. (PE activity credit) (OF, OSP) </P>

<P>PE 119 Introduction to Clay Target Shooting 1 credit </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is to introduce students to the clay target shooting sports of trap and skeet. Emphasis is placed on gun safety, gun and ammunition care, rules and range procedures, and how to properly use equipment for each sport. (PE activity credit) (DD) </P>

<P>PE 123 Horseback Riding I 1 credit </P>

<P>An activity class designed to introduce the student to horseback riding. Emphasis is placed upon basic skills of horsemanship, rules of safety and the care of horses. (Lab fee) (PE activity credit) (F, SP) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>PE 124 Horseback Riding II 1 credit </P>

<P>A continuation of Horseback Riding I. (Lab fee) (PE activity credit) (DD) </P>

<P>PE 204 Varsity Sports II 1 credit </P>

<P>A course for students participating in a second season of intercollegiate sports. (PE activity credit) PREREQUISITE: Consent of the coach. (F, SP) </P>

<P>PE 220 Introduction to Recreation 3 credits </P>

<P>An introductory course designed to provide an analysis of the total field of recreation and leisure. The course includes description of its current scope and organizational practices, as well as the historical, sociological, psychological, philosophical and economic aspects of recreation and leisure. (OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>PE 225 Introduction to Sport Psychology 3 credits </P>

<P>Study of physical, affective, and cognitive behaviors associated with participation in sport or exercise. Exploration of the psychological makeup of sport participants; explanation of psychological factors influencing involvement and performance in sport. Provides skills and knowledge about sport and exercise psychology applicable to everyday life. (DD) </P>

<P>PE 230 Recreation Development 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to give the student an overview of the principles of program planning and roles of the leader, administrator and community in program planning. Special considerations or programs are necessitated by various recreational settings, short-term seasonal, and year-round program planning. (DD) </P>

<P>PE 240 Techniques of Recreation Leadership 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to develop student competencies in the area of recreation leadership. The course will emphasize a theoretical understanding of leadership principles and techniques and will provide opportunities for practical application of these principles. (DD) </P>

<P>PE 250 Recreation Internship 3 credits </P>

<P>The recreation internship is designed to provide the student with practical, on-the-job training in the recreation field. The internship will include 150 contact hours by the student. A minimum of 45 contact hours is required for every hour of credit. (F, SP, SU) </P>

<P>PE 260 Foundations of Physical Education 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of the field of physical education/health, its foundational principles, aims, objectives, contributions, future directions, problems and career possibilities. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Physical Science </H3>

<P>NOTE: For other physical science courses, see course descriptions under Chemistry (CH). Physical Science and Math courses require placement scores within past three years. </P>

<P>PS 101 Introduction to the Physical Sciences 4 credits </P>

<P>A survey course for non-science majors introducing the important concepts that govern the fields of physics, chemistry, meteorology, geology and astronomy. The impact of these sciences on the environment and human activities will also be considered. Natural Sciences credit. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: DS 048 or appropriate math placement score. (F, SP, SU, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PHYS 110L – ESSENTIALS IN PHYSICAL SCIENCES WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>PS 104 Special Topics in Physical Science 1-3 credits </P>

<P>Independent study on a current topic in the physical sciences as demand warrants. Credit hours determined by the number of in-class contact hours and any activities assigned outside the classroom appropriate to content. (DD) </P>

<P>PS 108 Introduction to Physics 4 credits </P>

<P>A course in physics surveying the fundamental concepts of mechanics, waves, electricity, magnetism and optics. Natural Sciences credit. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: DS 049 or MF 104 or appropriate math placement score taken within the last three years. (OSU, DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PHYS 100L – ESSENTIALS IN PHYSICS WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>PS 120 Introduction to Astronomy 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a one-semester introduction to astronomy covering Earth-sky relationships, an overview of the Solar System, the Sun, the stars, our Galaxy, other galaxies, the large-scale structure of the Universe, and cosmology. Natural Sciences credit. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR ASTR 100 – ASTRONOMY </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>PS 185 College Physics I 4 credits </P>

<P>A rigorous non-calculus introductory physics course primarily for students majoring in the life and environmental sciences and science education. A classical treatment of Newtonian mechanics, fluids, heat and thermodynamics. Natural Sciences credit. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: MT 148 or both MT 122 and MT 132. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PHYS 150L –PHYSICS I WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>PS 186 College Physics II 4 credits </P>

<P>A continuation of College Physics I. Topics to be covered include sound and waves, electricity, magnetism, optics, and topics in modern physics as time permits. Lecture and laboratory. PREREQUISITE: PS 185. (DD) </P>

<P>PS 210 General Physics I 5 credits </P>

<P>Calculus-based physics designed for those students majoring in Chemistry, Physics or Engineering. The fundamental principles and theories of classical physics topics including kinematics, dynamics, statics, fluids, oscillations, wave mechanics and thermodynamics, based on calculus and vector manipulations. A laboratory course is included to emphasize and reinforce the principles and theories. Natural Sciences credit. PREREQUISITE: MT 150 and co-requisite: MT 250. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PHYS 200L – ADVANCED PHYSICS WITH LAB </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>PS 212 General Physics II 5 credits </P>

<P>Continuation of General Physics I (PS 210). The fundamental principles and theories of classical physics topics including, electricity, electrostatics, elementary circuits, magnetism, electromagnetic phenomena, optics and modern physics, based on calculus and vector manipulations. A laboratory course is included to emphasize and reinforce the principles and theories. PREREQUISITE: PS 210. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>PN Nursing </H3>

<P>Nursing courses are restricted to students accepted to the NCMC PN Nursing Program. </P>

<P>PN 100 Foundations of Nursing 6 credits </P>

<P>This course provides an introduction to nursing and roles of nurse, as well as concepts related to patient care and the profession of nursing. Emphasis is placed on the knowledge and skills needed to provide safe, quality patient care. The theoretical foundation for basic assessment and nursing skills is presented, and the students is given an opportunity to demonstrate these skills in a clinical laboratory setting. An introduction to the nursing process provides a decision-making framework to assist students in developing effective clinical judgment skills. (F, SP) </P>

<P>PN 101 Nursing of Adults 1A 6 credits </P>

<P>Nursing Care of Adults IA is the first of two medical-surgical nursing courses and builds upon basic nursing content and skills learned in Foundations of Nursing. This course focuses on the care of adult patients with select health alterations that require medical and/or surgical intervention. Concepts of patient-centered care, pharmacology, nutrition, cultural sensitivity, informatics, quality improvement, and professionalism are integrated throughout the course. Teamwork and collaboration utilizing evidenced based practice is emphasized. Clinical experiences provide the student an opportunity to apply theoretical concepts and implement safe patient care to adults in a variety of settings. (SP, F, SU) </P>

<P>PN 102 Nursing of Adults 1B 4 credits </P>

<P>Nursing Care of Adults IB is a continuation of the Nursing Care of Adults IA course with a continued focus on the care of adult patients with select health alterations that require medical and/or surgical intervention. A continued emphasis is placed on the concepts of patient-centered care, pharmacology, nutrition, cultural sensitivity, informatics, quality improvement and professionalism. Students will assume leadership, delegation, teamwork and collaboration roles utilizing evidence based practice. Clinical experiences will continue to provide the student an opportunity to apply theoretical concepts and implement safe patient care to adults in a variety of settings. (F, SU) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>PN 103 Introduction to Pharmacology 2 credits </P>

<P>This course provides an introduction to the principles of pharmacology, including: pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, medication interactions and potential adverse medication reactions. Emphasis is placed on drug classifications and nursing care related to the safe administration of medication to patients across the life span. (F, SP) </P>

<P>PN 104 Personal &amp; Vocational Concepts 1 credits </P>

<P>This course facilitates the transition of the student to the role of a LPN. Emphasis is placed on issues related to nursing and health care as well as developing the skills necessary to provide care to multiple patients and assign tasks to other LPNs and unlicensed personnel. Concepts related to leadership and management are presented as well as career development options that enhance career mobility. Standards of practice and importance of practicing according to state regulations and statutes are examined. (OF, OSP) </P>

<P>PN 105 Introduction to Mental Health Nursing 1 credit </P>

<P>This course is designed to introduce the knowledge, skills, and attitudes essential to mental health nursing. Emphasis is placed on the patient-centered care of patients across the lifespan experiencing common cognitive, mental and behavioral disorders. The focus will be on adapting the nurse-patient relationship to meet the special concerns of the client who has a mental health disorder. Concepts of teamwork and collaboration, professionalism, safety, crisis intervention, evidence based practice, therapeutic communication, anger management, and coping skills are integrated throughout the course (OF, OSP) </P>

<P>PN 106 Maternal and Child Health Nursing 2 credits </P>

<P>A course designed to introduce the student to the knowledge and skills essential to providing safe and competent nursing care to child bearing women, newborns and children. For the obstetric client, focus is placed on basic care during the antepartum, intrapartum, and postpartum periods. Growth and development of a child from birth through adolescence will be taught along with common pediatric health concerns. (SP, F) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>PN to ADN Nursing </H3>

<P>Nursing courses are restricted to students accepted to the NCMC PN to ADN Nursing Program. </P>

<P>RN 200 Leadership in Nursing 2 credits </P>

<P>This course facilitates the transition of the student to the role of a professional nurse in the microsystem of a work unit. Emphasis is placed on contemporary issues and management concepts, as well as developing the skills of delegation, conflict management, and leadership. Legal and ethical issues are discussed with a focus on personal accountability and responsibility. Standards of practice and the significance of functioning according to state regulations and statutes are analyzed. Clinical experiences provide the student the opportunity to apply theoretical concepts while functioning in a leadership role. (SP, OSP) </P>

<P>RN 201 Adult Nursing I 6 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on the care of adult patients with acute/complex medical/surgical health problems. Emphasis is placed on helping patients and their families cope with alterations in body functions. Concepts of pharmacology, nutrition, health promotion and education, cultural sensitivity, informatics, quality improvement, leadership and professionalism will be integrated throughout the course. Teamwork and collaboration utilizing evidence based practice is emphasized. Clinical experiences provide the student an opportunity to apply theoretical concepts and implement safe care to clients and selected groups in a variety of settings. (F) </P>

<P>RN 202 Adult Nursing II 4 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on advanced concepts of nursing </P>

<P>care as they relate to adult patient’s multisystem </P>

<P>alterations in health. Emphasis is placed on implementing time management and organizational skills while managing the care of patients with multiple needs and collaborating with the interdisciplinary team. Complex clinical skills, as well as priority setting, clinical judgement, and tenets of legal and ethical practice, are integrate throughout the course. Clinical experiences provide the student an opportunity to apply theoretical concepts and implement safe care to patients and selected groups in a variety of settings. (SP, OSP) </P>

<P>RN 203 Pharmacology 2 credits </P>

<P>This course expands upon the knowledge and comprehension of the concepts of pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, medication interactions and potential adverse medication reactions. Emphasis is placed on nursing interventions and health teaching related to the safe administration of medications to patients across the lifespan. (F, OF) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>RN 204 PN to ADN Transition 1 credit </P>

<P>This course is designed to facilitate successful student transition from the practical nursing course to that of the associate nursing coursework. Students will enhance previous learning strategies in addition to identifying goals for a successful transition into the associate degree nursing program. These strategies will encourage students to use sound clinical judgment in nursing practice. Emphasis is placed on student understanding of role concepts essential for registered nursing practice (Nursing Process, Teamwork, Collaboration, Leadership and Professionalism). (F, OF) </P>

<P>RN 205 Mental Health Nursing 2 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on the care of patients across the lifespan experiencing cognitive, mental and behavioral disorders. Emphasis is placed on management of patients facing emotional and psychological stressors, as well as promoting and maintaining the mental health of individuals and families. Concepts of crisis intervention, therapeutic communication, anger management, and coping skills are integrated throughout the course. The community as a site for care and support services is addressed. Clinical experiences provide the student an opportunity to apply theoretical concepts and implement safe patient care to patients in selected mental health settings. (F, OF) </P>

<P>RN 206 Maternal and Child Health Nursing 4 credits </P>

<P>This course provides an integrative, family-centered approach to the care of mothers, newborns, and children. Emphasis is placed on normal and high-risk pregnancies, normal growth and development, family dynamics, common pediatric disorders and the promotion of healthy behaviors in patients. Clinical experiences provide the student an opportunity to apply theoretical concepts and implement safe patient care to mothers, newborns, and children in selected settings. (SP, OSP) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Political Science </H3>

<P>PL 105 Missouri Constitution 1 credit </P>

<P>A survey of the history and content of the Missouri Constitution, its similarities and differences with the federal constitution, and its relevance today. Not open to students with credit for HI 103, PL 216 or any other course that covered instruction in Missouri State Constitution. (CBA) </P>

<P>PL 202 Introduction to Comparative Politics 3 credits </P>

<P>Comparative politics is the study of global political and economic systems. This course covers topics ranging from comparative studies of different political systems, global development, conflict, and economics. Students will be introduced to a wide range of subjects from a variety of perspectives, providing a strong foundation for understanding the complexities of our global society. (OF, OSP) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR POSC 202 – INTRODUCTION TO COMPARATIVE POLITICS </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>PL 216 National Government 3 credits </P>

<P>A basic introductory course to acquaint the student with the workings of the national government and the political system which bolsters it. Emphasis is placed on governmental structure, using the historical approach to answer the questions as to why the United States system has developed in the manner it has. The Constitution is dealt with in detail as the source of governmental power. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. Civics credit (meets the Constitution requirement). PREREQUISITE: Appropriate placement score or successful completion of EN101W. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR POSC 101 – AMERICAN GOVERNMENT </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Psychology </H3>

<P>PY 121 General Psychology 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey course dealing with the basic facts and principles of human behavior, providing an understanding of why and how people think and act as they do, emphasizing the manner in which the environment influences people. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PSYC 100 – GENERAL PSYCHOLOGY </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>PY 214 Social Psychology 3 credits </P>

<P>This course can be applied to either the sociology or psychology requirement. The course considers individual behavior in relation to society and includes theoretical foundations, socialization, social cognition, group dynamics and leadership. PREREQUISITE: PY 121 or SO 107. (OF) </P>

<P>PY 219 Adult Development and Aging 2 credits </P>

<P>This course focuses on the physiological, cognitive, personality and psychosocial development of middle and late adulthood. Emphasis is placed on the problems and concerns of aging, such as, interpersonal relations, retirement, the economy, psychopathology, and death and dying. PREREQUISITE: PY 121. (DD) </P>

<P>PY 225 Child Psychology 3 credits </P>

<P>Psychological basis of child growth and development, with emphasis on the emotional, mental, physical and social needs of childhood including an analysis of the factors in the home, school and community which influence behavior and personality. PREREQUISITE: PY </P>

<P>121. (SP) </P>

<P>PY 226 Adolescent Psychology 3 credits </P>

<P>A course focused on physical, intellectual and emotional changes that occur during adolescence. Included is an examination of the unique problems and risks involved as the adolescent develops personal values, behavior patterns, sexuality and morality. PREREQUISITE: PY 121. (DD) </P>

<P>PY 230 Abnormal Psychology 3 credits </P>

<P>This is an advanced Psychology course that will explore the historical views and different viewpoints of abnormal behavior. It will cover the different diagnostic categories of the DSM-5 and the treatments offered for these psychological disorders. PREREQUISITE: PY 121. (OF) </P>

<P>PY 233 Human Growth &amp; Development 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of human development across the life span. The focus is on clearly-defined stages of life, each with its own unique problems, concerns and solutions. The history, research methods, theories, technology and terminology related to the study of human development are discussed. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. PREREQUISITE: PY 121. (F, OSP) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR PSYC 200 – LIFESPAN HUMAN DEVELOPMENT </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>PY 245 Advanced General Psychology 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is a survey of the field of scientific psychology, emphasizing the methods used in conducting research and in data analysis. The purpose is to give students a scholarly framework with which to view psychology as a biological and social science. Recommended for second year students. PREREQUISITE: PY 121. (DD) </P>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<H3>Religion </H3>

<P>RL 101 Introduction to Religion 3 credits </P>

<P>This course introduces the student to the richness and variety of religious expressions around the world. Further, the student will be introduced to the theology and practices of the religions studied. The student will have an opportunity to analyze and compare religious systems. The student will be prepared to better understand contemporary religious issues and conflicts. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR RELG 100 – WORLD RELIGION </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Social Science </H3>

<P>SO 107 General Sociology 3 credits </P>

<P>A survey course concerned with the study of human relationships in groups and of the structures and organizations that develop within human society. Emphasis is placed on various social phenomena and the theories which attempt to explain them. Social and Behavioral Sciences credit. (F, SP, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR SOCI 101 – GENERAL SOCIOLOGY </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<P>SO 201 Marriage and the Family 3 credits </P>

<P>This course is designed to represent an analysis of the institution of the family and to provide an opportunity for the student to objectively study such basic phenomena as courtship patterns, marriage forms and socialization techniques. (DD) </P>

<P>SO 210 Social Problems 3 credits </P>

<P>This course discusses social problems such as violence, gender inequality, education and environment. It examines how social structure and culture of society contribute to social problems and their consequences. This course develops an understanding of the social forces that contribute to these problems, which leads to designing strategies for action. PREREQUISITE: SO 107. (DD) </P>

<P>SO 230 People &amp; Cultures of the World 3 credits </P>

<P>A course to give an American look at the anthropological study of world cultures. Cultural metaphors will be used as a method for understanding the cultural mind-set of a nation, a cluster of nations, and even a continent to quickly understand what members of a culture consider important. General types of cultures such as authority ranking, equality matching, market pricing, cleft, and torn. Cultural characteristics including religion, politics, gender, language, food, and history of the countries will also be examined. (DD) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR ANTH 201 – CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Speech </H3>

<P>SP 150 Studies in Communication 1-3 credits </P>

<P>A special topics course in communication which may include interpersonal communication, nonverbal communication, advanced oral interpretation, theatre practice or forensics. The subtitle on the schedule of courses for a particular semester indicates specific content. Credit varies from one to three hours. The course may be repeated if the content changes. (DD) </P>

<P>SP 175 Speech Communications 3 credits </P>

<P>Learn how to better think and act as a public speaker by preparing the presenting speeches. Application of content and self-assessment are principle learning strategies in this introductory course. The message-creation process stresses thinking broadly and deeply about the subject. The delivery approach emphasizes interactive skills and attitudes. Oral Communications credit. (F, SP, SU, OF, OSP, OSU) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR COMM 110 – FUNDAMENTALS OF PUBLIC SPEAKING </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>SP 176 Oral Interpretation 3 credits </P>

<P>Study and oral reading of prose, drama and poetry. Performances for audiences beyond the classroom provide practical experience. Understanding literature and developing self-confidence are important aspects of the course. (DD) </P>

<P>SO 231 Experiencing Culture 1 credit </P>

<P>This course is designed to allow students to read about a variety of issues in another culture and then experience the culture by traveling to the selected country. The course will give students skills involving relating with cultures other than their own. PREREQUISITE or COREQUISITE: SO 230. (DD) </P>

<P>SO 250 Introduction to Social Work 4 credits </P>

<P>Introduction to Social Work provides students with an overview of professional social work practice including its history, philosophy, ethics, values, methods and fields of practice. Forty hours of volunteer experience required in an area human service agency. PREREQUISITES: PY121 or SO107 or instructor approval. (DD) </P>
</Sect>
</Sect>

<Sect>
<Sect>
<H3>Theatre </H3>

<P>TH 111 Introduction to Theatre 3 credits </P>

<P>A study of the interrelated roles contributing to the creation of a play: playwright, actor, director, designers and technicians. Examination of the history of theatre is a major component of the course. Humanities and Fine Arts credit. (SPO) </P>

<P>MOTR Equivalent: MOTR THEA 100A – THEATRE APPRECIATION </P>
<Figure>

<ImageData src=""/>
</Figure>

<P>TH 113 Beginning Acting 2 credits </P>

<P>Introduction to fundamentals necessary for the actor and an approach to creating a character. Improvisational exercises and short scenes enable students to experience the basics of the craft. (DD) </P>

<P>TH 201 Theatre Participation 1-3 credits </P>

<P>Exploration of one or more aspects of theatre (acting, directing, design, etc.) in a workshop environment. Participants may also satisfy requirements by working on a production. Hours are arranged; requires permission of the instructor. (DD) </P>
