<P>APS 3313 Portfolio Development 	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course focuses upon the preparation, development, and submission of an experiential learning portfolio for those students pursuing their Bachelor’s degree through the School of Distance Education, who desire credit for experiential learning. Credit granted may range from 3 to 31 hours contingent upon approval of the portfolio. </P>

<New_Style_Sheet>BIBLE</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>BIB 1133 Biblical Prayer as Ministry 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey of references and examples of prayer throughout the Scriptures. Biblical Prayer is viewed as Christian ministry. Practical interpretations of the concept are applied to the revealed purposes of God and to the unreached peoples of the world.</P>

<P>BIB 1223 The Church in Ministry and Mission	3 Hours</P>

<P>A biblical study of the mandate and extraordinary potential of the local church in its efforts to worship God, edify believers, and evangelize the entire world. The priority of both personal and corporate participation in God’s great redemptive plan as expressed in the Old and New Testament is stressed. Additionally, students will explore leadership and ministry gifts within the Church and the central role of the Holy Spirit in advancing the kingdom of God.</P>

<P>BIB 2133 Book of Acts 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the Book of Acts with special emphasis on distinctive themes in Lucan theology as it relates to Luke-Acts. Attention is given to the expansion of the early Church, the work of the Holy Spirit, and the many challenges faced by the rapidly growing New Testament Church. (Prerequisite: REL 1153)</P>

<P>BIB 2213 Bible Study 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Representative passages of Scripture from a variety of genre in both Old and New Testament will be analyzed and studied in order to learn basic Bible study skills. Special emphasis will be placed on the meaning of Scripture in its historical and literary context. The student will be introduced to the proper use of basic Bible study tools. </P>

<P>BIB 2233 Pentateuch 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of Genesis through Deuteronomy with an emphasis on the prominent themes, historical events and legal codes. Attention is given to the concept of covenant and its significance throughout the Bible. (Prerequisite: REL 1163)</P>

<P>BIB 2243 Prison Epistles 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An exegetical study of Ephesians, Philippians, Colossians, and Philemon emphasizing the message of each letter and its contribution to Pauline theology. (Prerequisite: REL 1153) </P>

<P>BIB 2263 Historical Books 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the history of Israel comprising the conquest, monarchy, captivity, and the restoration of Israel as portrayed in the Books of Joshua through Esther. (Prerequisite: REL 1163) </P>

<P>BIB 2273 Geography and Archaeology of the Ancient Near East	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the history and geography of the Ancient Near East accented by archaeological discoveries that give insight to the biblical world. (Prerequisite: REL 1153 and 1163)</P>

<P>BIB 2313 Biblical Languages and Tools	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a basic introduction to biblical Hebrew and Greek that introduces students to the alphabet, grammatical terminology, and basic features of each biblical language with an emphasis on equipping the student to use commentaries, lexica, Bible software, and other language resources. (Prerequisite: BIB 2213)</P>

<P>BIB 2323 General Epistles	3 Hours</P>

<P>An exegetical study of Hebrews, James, 1 and 2 Peter, and Jude giving attention to the genre, theology, and application of each book. (Prerequisite: REL 1153)</P>

<P>BIB 2333 Pastoral and Thessalonian Epistles	3 Hours</P>

<P>An exegetical study of 1 and 2 Thessalonians, 1 and 2 Timothy and Titus that examines Paul’s instruction and encouragement to his two associates in Ephesus and Crete and the church in Thessalonica. (Prerequisite: REL 1153)</P>

<P>BIB 3233 Biblical Principles of Worship	3 Hours
An examination of the concept of worship in light of the biblical narrative, and the resulting theological, philosophical, and practical implications for life and ministry in contemporary culture. </P>

<P>BIB 3313 Corinthian Correspondence	3 Hours</P>

<P>An exegetical study of Paul’s letters to the church at Corinth including an introduction to the historical contexts and archaeology of this influential city. The pneumatological sections receive special attention highlighting their contribution to Pauline pneumatology. (Prerequisite: BIB 2213 and REL 1153)</P>

<P>BIB 3343 Romans and Galatians 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An exegetical study of Romans and Galatians emphasizing Paul’s distinctive teaching of justification by grace through faith and sanctification by the Holy Spirit. (Prerequisites: BIB 2213 and REL 1153)</P>

<P>BIB 3373 Bible as Literature 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A course designed to develop an appreciation for the artistry and beauty of the literature of the Bible. Emphasis will be placed upon literary genres, such as heroic narrative, epic, tragedy, lyric, poetry, and pastoral romance. This approach complements historical and theological approaches to the study of the Scriptures. (Same as ENG 3373)</P>

<P>BIB 3413 Prophetic Literature	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the history and messages of the Old Testament prophets. The course includes the exegesis of selected passages from the Major and Minor prophets. (Prerequisites: BIB 2213, REL 1163)</P>

<P>BIB 3423 Poetical and Wisdom Literature	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the books of Job, Psalms, Proverbs, Ecclesiastes, Song of Solomon, and Lamentations highlighting the poetic and literary characteristics unique to each genre. The theological content of each book is studied providing specific applications for faith and conduct. (Prerequisites: BIB 2213 and REL 1163)</P>

<P>BIB 3433 Hebrews	3 Hours</P>

<P>An exegetical study of Hebrews accentuates the supremacy of Christ as the fulfillment of God’s redemptive plan. (Prerequisites: BIB 2213 and REL 1153)</P>

<P>BIB 3483 Hermeneutics	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the crucial importance of sound Bible interpretation for the ongoing process of teaching and preaching, including the history, science, principles, and practices of biblical interpretation. The classroom becomes a laboratory where the student, by using selected genre, is trained to discover the true meaning of the biblical passages by applying correct principles and using proper tools. (Prerequisite: BIB 2213)</P>

<P>BIB 4133 Seminar in the Old Testament	3 Hours</P>

<P>An advanced exegetical study of an Old Testament book or theological theme. This course may be repeated provided the topic matter is distinct.</P>

<P>BIB 4143 Seminar in the New Testament	3 Hours</P>

<P>An advanced exegetical study of a New Testament book or theological theme. This course may be repeated provided the topic matter is distinct.</P>

<P>BIB 4150 Senior Paper	0 Hours</P>

<P>The senior paper represents the culmination of the student’s biblical and theological training. The choice of a topic must be made in consultation with the Department of Bible and Theology and an advisor will be assigned to the student to guide during the writing process. The course must be taken during the first semester of the senior year. (This course is available only to Bible and Theology, Biblical Studies, and Theological Studies Majors.) </P>

<P>BIB 4151 Senior Paper	1 Hour</P>

<P>The senior paper represents the culmination of the student’s biblical and theological training. The choice of topic must be made in consultation with the Department of Bible and Theology and an advisor will be assigned to the student to guide during the writing process. The course must be taken during the first semester of the senior year. (This course is available only to Bible and Theology, Biblical Studies, and Theological Studies Majors.)(Same as THE 4151)(Replaced by BIB 4150)</P>

<P>BIB 4443 Synoptic Gospels 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the life, ministry, and teachings of Jesus as recorded by Matthew, Mark and Luke. The common and distinctive characteristics and theology of each gospel will be evaluated. An overview of each book will be presented giving attention to its structure and dominant themes. Principles for the effective interpretation of the gospels are considered. (Prerequisites: BIB 2213 and REL 1153)</P>

<P>BIB 4453 Johannine Literature 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An exegetical study of the Gospel and Epistles of John emphasizing central theological themes including John’s contribution to Christology. (Prerequisites: BIB 2213 and REL 1153)</P>

<P>BIB 4513 Apocalyptic Literature 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An exegetical study of Daniel and Revelation and other apocalyptic passages of Scripture. The characteristics of apocalyptic literature and the canons of interpretation that apply to this genre will be examined. (Prerequisites: BIB 2213, REL 1153)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>BIBLICAL LANGUAGES</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>GRK 3113 New Testament Greek I	3 Hours</P>

<P>A beginning course in Greek designed to prepare the student for elementary translation in the New Testament. The student will begin to build an essential vocabulary necessary for translation of the New Testament. (Prerequisite: ENG 1123 or High Entrance Exam)</P>

<P>GRK 3123 New Testament Greek II	3 Hours</P>

<P>A continuation of GRK 3113 that will continue to build knowledge and skill level for translation and exegesis of the New Testament. (Prerequisite: GRK 3113 or equivalent)</P>

<P>GRK 4113 Intermediate Greek I	3 Hours</P>

<P>An advanced study in biblical Greek. An inductive study of the various portions of the Greek New Testament to extend the student’s knowledge of grammar, syntax, vocabulary and translation skills. (Prerequisite: GRK 3123)</P>

<P>GRK 4123 Intermediate Greek II	3 Hours</P>

<P>A continuation of GRK 4113. An inductive study of the various genre of the Greek New Testament with emphasis on exegesis and textual criticism. (Prerequisite: GRK 4113)</P>

<P>HEB 3113 Biblical Hebrew I	3 Hours</P>

<P>A beginning course in Hebrew designed to prepare the student for elementary translation in the Old Testament. The student will begin to build an essential vocabulary necessary for translation of the Old Testament. (Prerequisite: ENG 1123 or High Entrance Exam)</P>

<P>HEB 3123 Biblical Hebrew II	3 Hours</P>

<P>A continuation of HEB 3113 that will continue to build knowledge and skill level for translation and exegesis of the Old Testament. (Prerequisite: HEB 3113)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>BUSINESS</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>ACC 2213 Principles of Financial Accounting 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Accounting principles and procedures essential to the preparation of financial statements are developed with emphasis on their form, relationship, and presentation. Introduction to accounting principles for sole proprietorships, partnerships, and corporations. Use of accounting systems and application of valuation principles to assets, liabilities, equity, revenues, and expenses.</P>

<P>ACC 3000/4000 Special Topics 1	3 Hours </P>

<P>Various topics in Accounting are considered. They will vary depending upon recent developments in the field and upon the research interests of the instructor. The topics to be included are announced at the time of the course offering.</P>

<P>ACC 3343 Intermediate Accounting I 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A systematic study of intermediate accounting theory and practice. The development of accounting theory and processes are reviewed and financial statement relationships are studied. A methodical in-depth examination of all of the major balance sheet classification and account groupings follows. This course includes coverage of the official pronouncements of the FASB and other preceding AICPA bodies. (Prerequisite: ACC 2213)</P>

<P>ACC 3353 Intermediate Accounting II 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A continuation of the study of intermediate accounting theory with a methodical examination of the major balance sheet classifications and account groupings. The course concludes with specialized topics of relevant interest to the intermediate student. These topics include: income taxes, inflation and its impact on financial statements, accounting changes, statement of changes in financial position and analysis of financial statements. (Prerequisites: ACC 2213, ACC 3343)</P>

<P>ACC 4433 Managerial Cost Accounting 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An analysis of basic cost relationships which include standard costing techniques, variance analysis, CVP analysis and the design of cost systems. Inventory planning and control techniques are studied. The income effects of alternative product costing methods are compared. A timely and relevant course for both the accountant who records and reports costs and the manager who receives and analyzes this information. (Prerequisite: ACC 2213) </P>

<P>ACC 4443 Income Tax Accounting 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of personal income tax rules and regulations together with their application to specific taxpayer situations. A brief comparison of some basic differences between personal and corporate income tax regulations is also presented. Tax reference services will be introduced in the course, and students will be required to demonstrate some proficiency in their use. (Prerequisite: ACC 2213) </P>

<P>ACC 4453 Auditing 	3 Hours </P>

<P>The course is designed to acquaint the student with the theoretical knowledge to successfully perform the attest function. Problems and case studies are used to grant the student practical exposure to the process since actual records are not available. (Prerequisite: ACC 2213)</P>

<P>ACC 4483 Advanced Accounting 	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course completes the study of financial accounting theory. A variety of advanced topics are covered in depth. These topics include: business combinations, consolidated financial statements, partnerships accounting, not-for-profit accounting, fiduciary accounting and advanced financial statement presentation. (Prerequisite: ACC 3353)</P>

<P>ACC 4591 Accounting Internship	1 Hour</P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing accounting practices in any of several fields, such as financial analysis, auditing, taxation processes, accounts receivable/payable, cost accounting, business finance, etc. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of courses in the accounting specialization, permission of instructor and Department Chair)</P>

<P>ACC 4593 Accounting Internship	3 Hours</P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing accounting practices in any of several fields, such as financial analysis, auditing, taxation processes, accounts receivable/payable, cost accounting, business finance, etc. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of courses in the accounting specialization, permission of instructor and Department Chair) (Replaced by ACC 4591)</P>

<P>ACC 4910 Accounting Practicum	0 Hours
Beginning with the first Professional Development course, students will be enrolled in a co-requisite Practicum course every semester until they successfully complete either an approved 120-hour internship or a Capstone project. Students must successfully complete the course prior to graduation. (Prerequisite: Enrollment in Professional Development courses)</P>

<P>BSM 2113 Introduction to Sport Management	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introductory course emphasizing basic management principles as they relate to the business of sports. Students are introduced to sports marketing, sports law, sports supervision, sports media, sports ethics, and recreational sports management. An overview is provided with regard to career opportunities in this field.</P>

<P>BSM 3213 Sport Facility and Event Management 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will examine current industry practices in the planning, funding, operations, and supervision of facilities. The course will also examine practical aspects of event management such as planning, sponsorship, budgeting, and evaluation. (Prerequisite: BSM 2113 or concurrent enrollment)</P>

<P>BSM 3223 Sport Governance, Leadership and Administration	                      3 Hours</P>

<P>This course serves as an introduction and examination of organizations that govern sport at all levels of sport structure, organizational leadership roles and management techniques, and operations practices for sport organizations. Focus will be directed towards leadership principles and specific competencies required by all sport managers. (Prerequisite: BSM 2113 or concurrent enrollment)</P>

<P>BSM 3253 Sport Marketing and Promotion	3 Hours</P>

<P>Study of the marketing function of the firm and the impact of consumer buying behavior. Marketing of sports, teams, athletes, sport marketing planning, market segmentation, sponsorship, and promotions management are emphasized. (Prerequisite: BSM 2113 or concurrent enrollment)</P>

<P>BSM 4133 Legal Aspects of Sport   	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course provides an extensive overview of legal principles in collegiate, high school, and amateur athletics. Includes introduction to the different fields of law and practical legal issues faced by sport managers. (Prerequisite: BSM 2113 or concurrent enrollment)</P>

<P>BSM 4911 Sport Management Internship I    	1 Hour</P>

<P>A 120 hour supervised work experience in sports management taking place on the college campus working with the Athletic Department, Student Activities Director, and/or the Intramural Department. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of courses in the Business core curriculum, permission of instructor and Department Chair)</P>

<P>BSM 4921 Sport Management Internship II    	1 Hour</P>

<P>A 120 hour supervised work experience in sports management with an approved organization, school, business, or industry within the community. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of courses in the Sport Management program, BSM 4911, permission of instructor and Department Chair)</P>

<P>BUS 1123 Survey of Economics	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course surveys basic microeconomic and macroeconomic principles including market structures, supply and demand, competition, government policy making, interest rates, and the banking system. Current economic problems are identified and analyzed in relationship to the basic economic principles explored.</P>

<P>BUS 2133 Technology Application Certifications	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course will prepare students for marketplace ministry through the development of job competencies that will be attained through certification in various technology applications. These certifications will include a variety of applications such as Microsoft Excel, Microsoft Office, Microsoft Word, and others. Course content may vary from semester to semester as industry standards and certification opportunities become available.  (Same as MGT 2133)</P>

<P>BUS 2253 Business Law I	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the U.S. legal system and its application and impact upon business/managerial decision-making as well as the typical legal issues encountered in the marketplace today. The course addresses the U.S. legal system/legal procedure, contracts, Uniform Commercial Code (Article 2), domestic and international sales and lease transactions, secured transactions, agency, and ethics.</P>

<P>BUS 3123 Project Management	3 Hours</P>

<P>Companies continuously implement more efficient processes and launch new products and services. The successful management of these projects is critical for optimal business operations and growth. In this course, students will learn how to link projects to strategic goals, build cooperation among cross-functional teams, and manage resources within multi-project environments. Topics include project selection, leadership for project managers, scope management, team building and conflict resolution, cost estimation and budgeting, and project scheduling. In addition, student learning is aligned with the Project Management Body of Knowledge (PMBoK) throughout the course, and students will complete a team-based project to provide practical experience. (Prerequisite: MGT 2383)(Same as MGT 3123)</P>

<P>BUS 3133 Global Team Management	3 Hours</P>

<P>Organizations have expanded globally to remain competitive and to expand their product and service offerings. To facilitate world-wide expansion, companies utilize team leaders to facilitate virtual, cross-functional, and multi-national teams of experts. These global team leaders must overcome challenges like cultural and linguistic differences, the absence of face-to-face communications, and barriers to technological availability and usage to ensure that the organization’s competitive and expansion goals are met. In this course, students will learn how to effectively lead virtual teams by overcoming temporal, spatial, and cultural challenges. Topics include the stages of team development, team facilitation, knowledge management, eCommunications, lateral leadership, and transformational leadership. In addition, students will evaluate real-world case-studies and will participate in virtual teams to gain real experience as global team members and global team leaders. (Prerequisite: MGT 2383)</P>

<P>BUS 3413 Statistics	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of basic statistical methods of distributions, central tendency, variability, correlation, sampling techniques, and hypothesis testing. (Prerequisite: Successful completion of MTH 1123. Same as MTH 3413)</P>

<P>BUS 4113 Business Ethics 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study contemporary business issues and dilemmas involving personal and corporate ethical practices, values, and corporate social responsibility in both the domestic and global marketplace using texts and case studies. (Prerequisite: Junior or senior class standing in any major/specialization.)</P>

<P>BUS 4123 Quality Improvement and  Management	3 Hours</P>

<P>Defective products and non-value adding activities are preventable expenses, and they reduce company profits. To become a competitive entity within our global business environment, companies can reduce their inefficiencies by embedding continuous, quality improvement and management techniques within the organizational culture. In this course, students will learn how to analyze processes, measurably solve problems, and implement sustainable solutions that reduce defects and improve quality within products and services. Topics include global competitiveness, change leadership, team management, conflict resolution, decision management, and Lean Six Sigma. Students will also utilize quality improvement tools like voice of the customer (VOC), root cause analysis, and affinity diagrams to gain real-world experience with quality improvement. (Prerequisite: MGT 2383)</P>

<P>BUS 4443 Business Finance 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of financing and investment decisions of the financial manager that maximize shareholder wealth. Topics include risk and return, interest and time value calculations, financial statement analysis, capital budgeting, long-term financing, and working capital management. (Prerequisite: ACC 2213, FIN 2113) </P>

<P>BUS 4453 International Business 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An introduction to essentials of international business. Includes topics covering the nature of international business, international organizations and monetary systems, foreign environments, and special management and marketing considerations. (Prerequisite: MGT 2313)</P>

<P>BUS 4473 Strategy and Policy in Business 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Problem analysis and strategic management of today’s businesses. The integration of knowledge and application of theories across functional areas is stressed. Case approach will develop skills of problem identification, analysis of alternatives, decision making, and proposal presentation. (Prerequisites: ACC 2213 and MGT 2313)</P>

<P>BUS 4591 Business Administration Internship	1 Hour</P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing management practices in any of several fields, such as managerial decision making, financial analysis, human resources management, labor management, supply chain management, operations management, organizational change management, etc. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisite:  12 hours of courses in the business administration specialization, permission of instructor and Department Chair)</P>

<P>BUS 4593 Business Administration Internship	3 Hours</P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing management practices in any of several fields, such as managerial decision making, financial analysis, human resources management, labor management, supply chain management, operations management, organizational change management, etc. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisite:  12 hours of courses in the business administration specialization, permission of instructor and Department Chair)(Replaced by BUS 4591)</P>

<P>FIN 2113 Principles of Finance	3 Hours
This course is designed to introduce students from all business disciplines to finance and prepare them for more in depth study in finance. The objective of this course is to provide the student with very basic analytical tools necessary to make value-enhancing financial decisions. Topics covered in the course include the time value of money, risk-return trade-off, valuation of financial assets and real assets, and capital structure decisions. At the end of this course, students are expected to have a good understanding of the basic techniques needed for making sound financial decisions. </P>

<P>HRM 3113 Human Resource Management 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of philosophies and policies of the personnel management system: planning and staffing; training and development; labor relations; understanding and managing people; financial compensation; assessment. (Prerequisite: MGT 2313)</P>

<P>HRM 3123 Conflict Resolution for Business Professionals </P>

<P>	3 Hours </P>

<P>Students will demonstrate conflict resolution, mediation, and arbitration competencies by developing exceptional listening and communication skills, distinguishing between positive and negative conflicts in the workplace, interpreting body language, and utilizing conflict resolution best practices to reduce and/or eliminate negative conflict in the workplace. Upon successful completion of the course, students will receive an industry-recognized Crucial Conversations certification. </P>

<P>HRM 4113 Compensation Management 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Wage and salary administration in public and private organizations; determinants of general wage and salary levels and structures; total compensation systems, interrelationship among employee performance, intrinsic and extrinsic rewards, perceived equitable payments, employee satisfaction. (Prerequisite: HRM 3113)</P>

<P>HRM 4123 Employment Law 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the laws relating to employment. Includes defining the employer-employee relationship; regulation of discriminatory practices in employment (Title VII, the 1964 Civil Rights Act, and other statutes); regulation of the employment environment; and testing and evaluation of employee job performance. (Prerequisite: HRM 3113)</P>

<P>HRM 4133 Human Resource Development 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Practical and theoretical approaches to training and development of employees in an organization. Topics include organization, role and scope, training and development functions, philosophies, strategies, need analysis, development of program content, methods, materials and techniques, and evaluation and control of the training and development function. (Prerequisite: HRM 3113)</P>

<P>HRM 4591 Human Resource Management Internship	1 Hour </P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing Human Resource Management skills. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of HRM courses, permission of instructor and Department Chair.)</P>

<P>HRM 4593 Human Resource Management Internship	3 Hours </P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing Human Resource Management skills. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of HRM courses, permission of instructor and Department Chair.)(Replaced by HRM 4591)</P>

<P>HRM 4910 Human Resource Management Practicum	0 Hours
Beginning with the first Professional Development course, students will be enrolled in a co-requisite Practicum course every semester until they successfully complete either an approved 120-hour internship or a Capstone project. Students must successfully complete the course prior to graduation. (Prerequisite: Enrollment in Professional Development courses) </P>

<P>MGT 2133 Technology Application Certifications	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course will prepare students for marketplace ministry through the development of job competencies that will be attained through certification in various technology applications. These certifications will include a variety of applications such as Microsoft Excel, Microsoft Office, Microsoft Word, and others. Course content may vary from semester to semester as industry standards and certification opportunities become available. (Same as BUS 2133)</P>

<P>MGT 2313 Principles of Management 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Study of historical and contemporary management theory, models, and practices. Includes principles of planning, organizing, staffing, leadership, and control. Introduction to decision-making processes, styles, and situations. Emphasis on development of interpersonal managerial skills through student interaction and group activities.</P>

<P>MGT 2383 Management Communications 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Study and practice in writing a variety of business correspondence, foundations and practice of the elements of visual and verbal business communication. (Same as COM 2383.)</P>

<P>MGT 3000/4000 Special Topics I	3 Hours </P>

<P>Various topics in Management are considered. They will vary depending upon recent developments in the field and upon the research interests of the instructor. The topics to be included are announced at the time of the course offering.</P>

<P>MGT 3113 Nonprofit Management	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course deepens student knowledge of nonprofits by examining the theoretical and practical aspects of the effective leadership and management of nonprofit organizations. The course includes the coveted topics of leadership, governing boards, accountability, partnerships, volunteerism, and fundraising for nonprofit organizations that operate in our global world. Video-based and real-world case studies from revered nonprofit leaders and organizations, lectures, and scholarly materials are utilized to prepare students to successfully lead, manage, and overcome key issues and sustainability challenges that plague nonprofit organizations.</P>

<P>MGT 3123 Project Management	3 Hours</P>

<P>Companies continuously implement more efficient processes and launch new products and services. The successful management of these projects is critical for optimal business operations and growth. In this course, students will learn how to link projects to strategic goals, build cooperation among cross-functional teams, and manage resources within multi-project environments. Topics include project selection, leadership for project managers, scope management, team building and conflict resolution, cost estimation and budgeting, and project scheduling. In addition, student learning is aligned with the Project Management Body of Knowledge (PMBoK) throughout the course, and students will complete a team-based project to provide practical experience. (Prerequisite: MGT 2383)(Same as BUS 3123)</P>

<P>MGT 4113 Organizational Behavior	3 Hours</P>

<P>Analysis of organization in its various forms and the influence of environmental forces. Emphasis is placed on theoretical concepts, structural design and research findings about organizational relationships and effective management. (Prerequisite: MGT 2313)</P>

<P>MGT 4443 Entrepreneurship and Venture Management             		3 Hours </P>

<P>Fundamentals of identifying the need for and organizing a small business. The role and characteristics of the entrepreneur and problems of venture initiation are studied: new venture creation and its management through the first two or three years of operation. (Prerequisite: MGT 2313)</P>

<P>MGT 4453 Operations Management 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Analysis of the ongoing operations of established businesses. Students will be introduced to useful problem-solving techniques to deal with complex business problems. Topics include design and improvement of production processes, work measurement and standards, quality control, facilities layout, transportation problems, budgetary and cost control, inventory management, and PERT and critical path methods. (Prerequisite: MGT 2313)</P>

<P>MGT 4591 Management Internship	1 Hour</P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing management practices in any of several fields, such as managerial decision making, financial analysis, human resources management, labor management, supply chain management, operations management, organizational change management, etc. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of courses in the management specialization, permission of instructor and Department Chair)</P>

<P>MGT 4593 Management Internship	3 Hours</P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing management practices in any of several fields, such as managerial decision making, financial analysis, human resources management, labor management, supply chain management, operations management, organizational change management, etc. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of courses in the management specialization, permission of instructor and Department Chair)(Replaced by MGT 4591)</P>

<P>MGT 4910 Management Practicum	0 Hours
Beginning with the first Professional Development course, students will be enrolled in a co-requisite Practicum course every semester until they successfully complete either an approved 120-hour internship or a Capstone project. Students must successfully complete the course prior to graduation. (Prerequisite: Enrollment in Professional Development courses)</P>

<P>MIS 2113 Information Systems Theory and Practice	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course equips students with a biblical worldview and skills necessary to enable them to deal with the many information systems issues that confront every person who lives in this modern information age. The course will give the student a basic foundation of Information Technology/Information Systems (IT/IS) history, components and application in the global environments of today.</P>

<P>MIS 3113 Ethical Side of Information Technology	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination and analysis of the tremendous impact of technology on individuals, organizations and global societies, focusing on the ethical issues in the use of information technology in the modern business world, as well as legal and social issues. Ethics for IT professionals and IT users will be considered. Additionally, the class will examine the human dimensions of technology and the impact that technology and globalization is having on individuals and the workplace and the implications this has for managing and leading organizations. (Prerequisite: MGT 2313 or MIS 2113)</P>

<P>MIS 3133 Telecommunications and Networking in Business</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of the issues involved in the use, construction, and management of local and global data communication networks in a business environment. Topics include basic terminology, networking fundamentals, ethics, team collaboration, organizational communication, and the use of the Internet and Intranet clients, servers, and languages to support electronic commerce. An overview of telecommunications legal issues, security and network management issues will be emphasized. (Prerequisite: MGT 2313 or MIS 2113)</P>

<P>MIS 4113 Information Systems Analysis and Design	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination and analysis of an existing information system and the modification of that system or the design of a new system. The various tools, techniques, and models used by systems analysts are explored. Emphasis is on successful IS development and the role of the IS professional to effectively interact and communicate with global management, the IS department, clients, users and peers both verbally and in writing. (Prerequisite: MIS 2113)</P>

<P>MIS 4123 Information Systems for Management	3 Hours</P>

<P>A case-oriented course providing an overview of information technology and information systems topics from an organizational and managerial perspective. Topics include current information technology (IT) types and trends, such as the Internet and its organizational impact; the relationship of technology to organizational strategy, structure, controls, resources, and security; the ethical and social impacts of information systems, such as privacy, intellectual property rights, accountability and quality of life. Emphasis will be placed on the user’s role in developing information systems, ethical and management challenges and the uses of IT to create competitive advantages for an organization and for decision-making. (Prerequisite: MIS 2113)</P>

<P>MIS 4133 Information Technology Security and Forensics</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>The first part of this course emphasizes the IT professional’s need to understand, apply, and manage information assurance and security “best practices” in computing, communication, and organizational systems. The importance for the IT professional to educate users to be sufficiently security aware is stressed in the course. The second part concentrates on the theory of IT investigative forensics. The course will cover such topics as how to identify, develop, and implement security policies and procedures for an information system and its physical environment (i.e. network interface), IT security management, risk assessment, legal issues, crime investigation, and financial considerations. This course covers proactive practice including Business Continuity Planning (BCP) and disaster recovery planning in order to maintain information integrity. (Prerequisites: MIS 2113, MIS 3113)</P>

<P>MIS 4143 Current Information Technology</P>

<P>     Trends and Emerging Technologies	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course identifies and evaluates significant current trends, research, emerging technologies and events in the global environment of information technology and information systems. The course will address the constantly changing nature of information technology and its implementation in business and industry and emphasize the need for continued lifelong learning. Ethics, strategic use of technologies, and case studies of successful implementation of new technologies will be discussed. (Prerequisite: MIS 2113)</P>

<P>MIS 4593 Management Information Systems Internship
	3 Hours</P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing MIS practices in any of several fields, such as information systems management or information technology systems position in any industry, database mining for any business purpose, website or network design or implementation/administration, etc. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of courses in the MIS specialization, permission of instructor and Department Chair)</P>

<P>MKT 2323 Principles of Marketing 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Study of the marketing function of the firm and the impact of consumer buying behavior. This course examines the variables of the marketing mix; product planning, pricing, physical distribution, channels of distribution, advertising, personal selling, and sales promotion. Investigates the economic, social, ethical, and political influences on the marketing environment. </P>

<P>MKT 3000/4000 Special Topics I	3 Hours </P>

<P>Various topics in Marketing are considered. They will vary depending upon recent developments in the field and upon the research interests of the instructor. The topics to be included are announced at the time of the course offering. </P>

<P>MKT 3223 Consumer Behavior 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the buying habits and preferences of consumers, models for explaining and predicting consumer and marketing behavior and consumer movements and attitudes with implications for marketing management policies and the business economy. (Prerequisite: MKT 2323) </P>

<P>MKT 3233 Business Marketing 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An overview of business marketing including: derived demand, vendor analysis, the multiple buying unit, value analysis, competitive bidding, industrial design, key accounts, and trade shows. (Prerequisites: MKT 2323)</P>

<P>MKT 4123 Marketing Research	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is an introduction to the marketing research process enabling business analysis and decision making on behalf of a company or client. Topics include the creation and execution of a research project, an exploration of measurement instruments and survey design, analysis and reporting, as well as communicating research results at the leadership level. Additionally, ethical and organizational challenge related to applied research will be explored. (Prerequisites: BUS/MTH 3413, MKT 2323) </P>

<P>MKT 4313 Advertising and Promotion	3 Hours
A study of the marketing promotional mix while gaining skills necessary to support the marketing with visual content. Topics include blogging, typography, color schemes, photography, video and editing skills for content creation. Additional focus will encompass strategies for advertising, sales promotion, personal selling, and public relations. Ethics and truth in advertising will be emphasized. (Prerequisite: MKT 2323)</P>

<P>MKT 4353 Digital Marketing and Sales Strategies	3 Hours
This course provides a practical understanding of the internet marketplace focusing on applications within business, ministry, and missions, while also equipping the students with the skills needed to perform vital daily functions. Topics include internet marketing strategies, search engine optimization, creation and optimization of a product website/webpage, internet analytics, selling and telling in social media and mobile marketing. Additionally, ethical and organizational challenges related to marketing online will be explored.</P>

<P>MKT 4591 Marketing Internship	1 Hour</P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing marketing practices in any of several fields, such as account marketing management, advertising and promotion in media, event promotion, marketing research, database mining for marketing purposes, etc. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of courses in the marketing specialization, permission of instructor and Department Chair)</P>

<P/>

<P>MKT 4593 Marketing Internship	3 Hours</P>

<P>Internship experience in an organization emphasizing marketing practices in any of several fields, such as account marketing management, advertising and promotion in media, event promotion, marketing research, database mining for marketing purposes, etc. 120 hours are required for this internship. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of courses in the marketing specialization, permission of instructor and Department Chair)(Replaced by MKT 4591)</P>

<P>MKT 4893 Marketing Management	3 Hours
This course builds upon material in Principles of Marketing but is more applied in nature and covers the four P’s in greater depth. A study of the process of analyzing marketing opportunities. (Prerequisite: MKT 2323)</P>

<P>MKT 4910 Marketing Practicum	0 Hours</P>

<P>Beginning with the first Professional Development course, students will be enrolled in a co-requisite Practicum course every semester until they successfully complete either an approved 120-hour internship or a Capstone project. Students must successfully complete the course prior to graduation. (Prerequisite: Enrollment in Professional Development courses)</P>

<P/>

<New_Style_Sheet>CHILDREN AND FAMILY MINISTRIES </New_Style_Sheet>

<P>CFM 2113 Leadership of Children and Family Ministry	</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>An overview study of the various aspects of Children and Family Ministries. This course will provide the foundational understanding of the biblical perspective of children’s ministries. It will also address the role of the children’s minister in relation to parents, families, the pastor and other church staff in leadership positions.</P>

<P>CFM 2133 Creative Methods for Communicating to Children</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>Instruction and practice in a wide variety of creative methods to be used in teaching and preaching to children. Special emphasis will be given to developing skills and presentations. This lab-like course will prepare students to increase their ability to communicate effectively to children. (Replaced by CFM 3123)</P>

<P>CFM 2143 Perspectives of Children and Family Ministries</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>An overview study of the various perspectives of Children and Family Ministries. This course will provide the foundational understanding of the biblical perspective of ministering to children and families. Attention will also be given to the historical understandings of childhood and the development of ministry to children.</P>

<P>CFM 2153 Marriage and Family Relationships 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the historical and comparative importance of the family, the effect and impact of modern industrial society and </P>

<P>social change upon the family, and family integration and disintegration. </P>

<P>CFM 3113 Bridging Between Children and Youth	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of principles and methods for effectively helping individuals transition from childhood to adolescence within church ministries. Emphasis will be placed upon cooperative efforts between children’s and youth pastors to facilitate successful transition. (Same as YSM 3113)</P>

<P>CFM 3123 Creative Methods for Communicating to Children</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>Instruction and practice in a wide variety of creative methods to be used in teaching and preaching to children. Special emphasis will be given to developing skills and presentations. This lab-like course will prepare students to increase their ability to communicate effectively to children.</P>

<P>CFM 3133 Spiritual Formation of Children	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the discipleship of children in keeping with their varied developmental needs and characteristics. Emphasis is given to training children, managing behavior, developing curriculum, and creating learning experiences that will effectively guide them in a growing relationship with Jesus Christ.</P>

<P>CFM 3143 Issues in Childhood and Family Life	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will involve the exploration of challenging issues in the lives of children. Students will learn to administer care and advocacy to and for children affected by a variety of societal issues and special needs.</P>

<P>CFM 3153 The Hospitalized Child	3 Hours</P>

<P>Overview of the role of the child life specialist in working with children and their families in healthcare settings, with emphasis on both theory and evidence-based practice.</P>

<P>CFM 4113 Contemporary Issues in Children and Families</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will involve the exploration of challenging issues in the lives of children. Students will learn to administer pastoral care and advocacy to and for children affected by a variety of societal issues and special needs. (Replaced by CFM 3143)</P>

<P>CFM 4123 Reaching Children in Unique Contexts	       3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will involve students in understanding outreach to children in one or more unique contexts. Each student will also gain first-hand experience in reaching children in unique contexts agreed upon by the student and the program director. Such contexts may include camping programs, community organizations, urban settings, foreign countries, or other unique settings for reaching children. Students must be in either the junior or senior year.</P>

<P>CFM 4133 Leading Children and Family Ministries	     3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will address the role of the children’s pastor or director of children and family ministries. Attention will be given to the administrative responsibilities of a director, recruitment and development of volunteers, support of parents, investment in families, and cooperation with the pastor and church staff. Working in churches of various sizes and cooperating with district and national ministries will be included.</P>

<P>CFM 4143 Family Life and Parenting	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will involve students in understanding the principles for creating and directing family ministries that include: help and resources for parents to disciple their children; opportunities for family members to minister together; and intergenerational efforts to facilitate community.</P>

<P>CFM 4183 Children and Family Practicum	3 Hours</P>

<P>Students will complete 120 hours in an off-campus setting in which they will obtain experiential learning in the field.</P>

<P>CFM 4999 Child Life Clinical Internship	9 Hours</P>

<P>Students will complete a minimum of 480 hours of child life clinical experience in a healthcare setting, under the direct supervision of a Certified Child Life Specialist.</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>CHRISTIAN EDUCATION </New_Style_Sheet>

<P>CED 4413 Adult Ministries 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the characteristics of the adult at various life stages, and developing trends in the Church’s work with adults. An investigation is made of methods which can be used effectively in reaching, teaching, and retaining adults in the local church with special emphasis upon principles which guide in structuring viable adult ministries.</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>CHURCH MINISTRIES</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>CMN 2213 Foundations of Church Ministries 	    3 Hours </P>

<P>An overview  of the various representative ministries, structure and functions of the local church. It also addresses the polity and policies of the Assemblies of God. Special attention is given to the personal, interpersonal, family and professional dimensions of ministry. </P>

<P>CMN 2313 Pastoral Counseling 	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide basic counseling training in those areas of counseling that are common among vocational ministries. The course will include Marriage and Family, Grief, Death and Dying, Crisis Intervention, and biblical strategies for solving problems of life. </P>

<P>CMN 3113 Ministry of Teaching	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the principles for effectively teaching Scripture to a variety of developmental and interest groups within the Church. The preparation of unit and lesson plans, the writing of objectives, selection of appropriate methodologies, effective presentation, and management of a quality learning experience will be discussed. Special emphasis will be given to an analysis of the teaching ministry of Jesus and the ancient Church. (Prerequisite: BIB 2213)</P>

<P>CMN 3123 Small Groups Ministry	3 Hours</P>

<P>Prepares the student to serve and equip the church in design, curriculum selection, implementation and evaluation of small group ministry.  Consideration is given to the training dimension for leader development as well as evangelistic intent. Emphasis will be on the biblical basis, effective models, and group dynamics of effective assimilation strategies within the local church and emerging ministry settings.</P>

<P>CMN 3163 Leadership in Ministry	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of the theory and practice of leadership principles particularly in relationship to ministry in the local church and para-church ministries. Leadership principles are examined from multiple fields of leadership practice (business, church, education, sociology, philosophy, etc.) in an attempt to expose students to best practices that can be applied to their current and future roles as Christian leaders in the church and their community. Among the topics that are covered are self-assessment techniques, personality traits, parliamentary procedures, recruitment, motivation, retention principles, goal setting, vision development, and time management.</P>

<P>CMN 3173 The Church and Media	3 Hours</P>

<course_listings>The exploration of the challenges facing the twenty-first century Church in regard to reaching a media saturated generation and utilizing media to accomplish the goals of the Church. The course will give the student an overview of the various kinds of media useful to the Church including video, print, computers and multimedia, audio, lighting, drama, television, and radio broadcasting.</course_listings>

<P>CMN 3183 Church Resource Management	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is an introduction to church resource administration. The administration of physical, financial, and human resources will be considered. This course also includes church liability management, taxation, insurance, and safety. The integration of technology into the administrative mission of the church will also be addressed.</P>

<P>CMN 3333 Biblical Preaching 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A basic course in the art and science of biblical sermon construction methodology. Special emphasis is given to the process of constructing sermons which are based on the meaning of the original author(s) of the Scripture(s) used for the sermon and which address contemporary human needs. (Prerequisites: BIB 2213, BIB 3483, COM 1143) </P>

<P>CMN 4123 Entrepreneurial Leadership	3 Hours</P>

<P>In this course students will learn the principles that make start-up businesses successful, the attitude of a person who is able to build a church or a company, as well as strategies for marketing the church in a manner that is appealing to the community and honoring to God.</P>

<P>CMN 4143 Leadership for Spiritual Formation	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the development and administration of all the discipleship ministries of the local church. Leadership principles, recruitment and training of workers, staff relationships, planning, leading, organization and supervision are all considered with a view toward spiritual formation of God’s people. Special attention is given to the discipleship ministries of the Assemblies of God.</P>

<P>CMN 4483 Church Ministries Practicum 	3 Hours </P>

<P>The student is assigned to a qualified mentor, and actively participates in a supervised ministry program. Emphasis in training is placed on the prospective graduate’s specialization</P>

<P>LDR 1113 Introduction to Leadership Internships	3 Hours</P>

<P>The student will be exposed to the various ministries of the local church, explore the expectations of interns in the local church setting, discover the policies and practices of their local church and participate in various ministries as assigned. Students will learn basic leadership principles through instruction, case studies and reading. Students will be expected to participate in local church ministry throughout the semester. An emphasis will be placed on finding a healthy blend of personal, spiritual, and ministerial responsibilities. </P>

<P>LDR 2133 Leadership Internship I	3 Hours</P>

<P>Leadership Internship I is designed to build on the principles learned through the Introduction to Leadership Internships through additional reading and practical experience under the supervision of a qualified supervisor. Emphasis will be placed on understanding the importance of finding one’s place in ministry and completing ministry hours in one or more departments of the church. (Prerequisite: LDR 1113) </P>

<P>LDR 3133 Leadership Internship II	3 Hours</P>

<P>Leadership Internship II is designed to help the student understand the importance of vision and mission in the success of an organization through reading, observation, and interviewing leaders in a local church setting. The student will participate in developing ministries that are in alignment with the mission of the church under the supervision of a qualified supervisor. The student will complete ministry hours in one or more departments of the church. (Prerequisites: LDR 1113, LDR 2133)</P>

<P>LDR 3193 Leadership Internship Elective	3 Hours</P>

<P>Leadership Internship Elective is designed to allow students to take internships in addition to those required in the Church Leadership program. The student will gain experience in the local church under the supervision of a qualified leader in the church. In addition, the student will gain leadership skills and insights through reading, observation, and interviewing leaders in a local church setting. The student will complete ministry hours in one or more departments of the church. (Prerequisites: LDR 1113, LDR 2133, LDR 3133) </P>

<P>LDR 4913 Leadership Protégé	3 Hours</P>

<P>Leadership Protégé is designed to permit students nearing the completion of the Church Leadership program to gain practical experience leading ministry efforts in the local church or parachurch agency. The student will be expected to lead a group of volunteers in the accomplishment of significant tasks in keeping with the vision and mission of the organization. The student will be directly responsible to a member of the executive leadership of the organization. Only students who have been highly successful in previous internship courses will be permitted to participate in this course. (Prerequisites: LDR 1113, LDR 2133, LDR 3133)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>
CHURCH PLANTING AND REVITALIZATION </New_Style_Sheet>

<P>CPR 3133 Church Health and Revitalization	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course addresses the needs of existing churches in 21st century American settings. The student will be taught evaluation skills designed to assess the health of existing churches. Special emphasis will be given to congregations that are either plateaued or declining. Strategies will be presented designed to lead such churches to renewed health and subsequent growth. Attention will be given to the needs of congregations that are currently growing but will face potential plateauing and decline if they do not take necessary steps that will enhance the likelihood of continued growth. A student internship is included in this course.</P>

<P>CPR 3313 Understanding and Reaching the Community</P>

<P>	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course will familiarize the student with community analysis and assessment techniques. The student will be taught to develop churches and ministries based on a composite profile of the ministry focus group to be reached. The course will explore a variety of models and methods for developing ministries that impact people, communities, and cities with the gospel to win converts, make disciples, and build up the church. Emphasis will be placed on the discovery of evangelism forms that would effectively reach the people in the neighborhood and community context in which a church is located.</P>

<P>*CPR 4113 Mentoring and Mobilizing Ministry Leaders 			3 Hours</P>

<P>(*This course is offered in non-traditional format only.)</P>

<P>This course introduces the student to principles of leadership made applicable to the church planting and revitalization context. The student will be taught how to transmit this information to potential local church leaders through the process of mentoring. The topic of mentoring is well-developed and clarifying instruction is given regarding a final essential component--the importance of worker mobilization in the church planting and revitalization context. A student internship is included in this course.</P>

<P>*CPR 4613 Church Planting	3 Hours</P>

<P>(*This course is offered in non-traditional format only.) </P>

<P>Students will be exposed to various stages of the church planting process. Foundational concepts will include the development of a philosophy of ministry, launching of public worship services, assimilation of people, and the importance of becoming a reproducing congregation. Advanced concepts will include the process for obtaining church incorporation, the financing of property, and the importance of adequate facilities. A student internship is included in this course.</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>COMMUNICATION ARTS</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>COM 1143 Fundamentals of Speech Communication 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An introductory speech course designed to develop individual </P>

<P/>

<P>speaking skills. Study in preparing, organizing, and delivering the basic types of speeches is included. </P>

<P>COM 2113 Web Design	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introductory study of web design with a focus on using different media with web sites. Includes integration of digital photography, video and text, and different application of the Internet resources for publication and public relations.</P>

<P>COM 2123 Computer Applications and Graphics in Mass Media	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study in using hardware and software technology for print publications and computer-mediated communication in news media, public relations and advertising. Experience with desktop publishing, databases, scanning, and web applications. Also attention will be given to graphic design and animation for web communication and other types of computer media. </P>

<P>COM 2133 Print and Broadcast Journalism	3 Hours</P>

<P>Students will explore methods of news, features and sports journalism with opportunities for practical application to real media outlets such as the University’s website, SAGU.TV, and area publications. Writing and editing for both the eye and ear will be studied and put into practical application. Special emphasis will be given to mastering the inverted pyramid formula, quote attributions, correct AP style, grammar and punctuation, and distinctive creativity. This course requires a technology fee. (Prerequisite: MED 2153 to be taken concurrently)</P>

<P>COM 2143 Scriptwriting for Theatre and Film	3 Hours</P>

<P>The exploration of the basic principles required to develop and write scripts for theatre and film production. Topics of study and application include: story treatments, research, source interviews, early script drafts, and final script submissions. (Same as WRT 2143)</P>

<P>COM 2213 Mass Communication in Society	3 Hours</P>

<P>Principles of mass communication including historical, economic, social, ethical and legal factors influencing the operation and content of the mass media. Impact of new technology in changing the media. A survey of mass communication areas (newspapers, magazines, advertising, public relations, television, wire services, Internet and networks), and careers they offer.</P>

<P>COM 2223 Fundamentals of Visual Communication	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is designed to provide students a foundational knowledge of graphic creation and its design concepts. Learning topics include: color theory/models, image-compositing, raster vs. vector graphics, photo manipulations, illustrations, 3D imaging, and font/typesets. Students will apply skills learned for project output to print, web, apps, and animated video. Course software: Photoshop, illustrator, and In-Design (Adobe Creative Cloud applications). (Prerequisite: MED 2123)</P>

<P>COM 2383 Management Communications 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Study and practice in writing a variety of business correspondence, foundations and practice of the elements of visual and verbal business communication. (Same as MGT 2383)</P>

<P/>

<P>COM 3113 The Church and Media	3 Hours</P>

<P>The exploration of the challenges facing the twenty-first century Church in regard to reaching a media saturated generation and utilizing media to accomplish the goals of the Church. The course will give the student an overview of the various kinds of media useful to the Church including video, print, computers and multimedia, audio, lighting, drama, television, and radio broadcasting. (Replaced by CMN 3173)</P>

<P>COM 3143 Entertainment-Education	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course focuses on entertainment-education initiatives used worldwide for social change. Topics presented and analyzed will help discover how media can be implemented to both entertain and educate in order to increase audience members’ knowledge about educational issues, to create favorable attitudes, shift social norms, or change overt behavior. (The course does not address pedagogical concepts and cannot be used as a substitute for any requirements that are part of SAGU’s Education degree programs.)</P>

<P>COM 3513 Rhetorical Studies in Film I	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of films using a rhetorical analysis framework, with an overview of objective, mimetic, pragmatic, and expressive theories applied to the film, the writer, and the culture. Various genres of film will be examined, such as comedy, drama, mystery, science fiction, musical, and animation. (Same as ENG 3513)</P>

<P>COM 3523 Rhetorical Studies in Film II	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course focuses on the viability of film as an effective tool to communicate biblical and Christian values, those of the Church, for all of culture. Films pertaining to evangelism and discipleship, marriage and family, eschatology, missiology, and other doctrinal truths of the Bible will be analyzed rhetorically for their thematic, artistic, social, and cinematic effectiveness. (Same as ENG 3523)</P>

<P>COM 4113 Communication Theory	3 Hours</P>

<P>Survey of classical and contemporary theories of communication. This course will consider the theory and practice of interpersonal communication, influence, group and organizational communication, public rhetoric, and cultural communication. The course will include discussion and application of the impact of these theories in everyday life. </P>

<P>COM 4123 Communication History	3 Hours</P>

<P>A historical and interdisciplinary analysis of the development of communication art concepts and practices from the classical rhetorical tradition to the present.</P>

<P>COM 4133 Mass Communication Research Methods	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of quantitative and qualitative methods used to study audiences, contents and effects of mass media, especially focusing on advertising and public relations communication and utilizing social science research skills and statistical analysis. Approaches include content analysis, survey research, focus groups and other experimental studies.</P>

<P>COM 4153 Communication Ethics	3 Hours</P>

<P>Examines ethical issues raised by contemporary mass media practices, especially those related to news, advertising, and public relations. Students will learn to recognize and analyze problem situations in terms of a framework of ethical principles in a societal context. The course also considers the role of media in light of a Christian worldview.</P>

<P>COM 4480 Communication Arts Internship	0 Hours</P>

<P>Students arrange for either short-term employment or a not-for-hire position that relates to their major with a cooperating business, church or institution. 120 hours of tasks specifically related to students’ academic and career interests are required, and are documented via a journal submitted weekly to the supervising faculty member. Additional assignments that reflect on the work experience are also required. Offered on a Pass (P)-No Pass (N) basis only. This course is required for graduation, but is a zero-credit course. (Prerequisite: approval of the Communication Arts Department Chair)</P>

<P>COM 4483 Communication Internship	3 Hours</P>

<P>Students arrange for either short-term employment or a not-for-hire position that relates to their major with a cooperating business, church or institution. 120 hours of tasks specifically related to students’ academic and career interests are required, and are documented via a journal submitted weekly to the supervising faculty member. Additional assignments that reflect on the work experience are also required. Offered on a CR/NC basis only. (Prerequisite: approval of the Communication Arts Department Chair)</P>

<P>COM 4916 New Media Internship	6 Hours</P>

<P>Students will receive training in and be given opportunity for practical application of new media design and development at a cooperating business located within SAGU proximity that develops new media product. New media includes, among other things, computer animation, motion graphics and mobile applications, and integrates inventive computer-based creative content with conventional forms of video and audio production. Internship activities will be structured specifically around the learning and application of motion graphics for video and film, Adobe Flash animation, Flash mobile development, and Unity mobile development, in a real-world, production environment, working alongside industry professionals. (Prerequisite: approval of the instructor and practicum sponsor [company].)

COM 4923 Advanced Topics in Communication Arts	3 Hours
This course provides a custom-designed academic experience for students that have interest in exploring one or more aspects of communication arts that, due to the timing of course offerings, are not available for scheduling prior to an expected graduation date. (Prerequisite: Department approval)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>COUNSELING </New_Style_Sheet>

<P>COU 2113 Counseling Families Through the Life Cycle</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the stages of family development and the typical counseling issues which flow from those transitions. Emphasis is on family life cycle and transitions including the independent adult, marital dyad, the infant/preschool/grade school family, parenting teens, launching teens, retirement and death of spouse. The issues of divorce and re-marriage </P>

<P>counseling will also be examined. (Prerequisite: CMN 2313 or COU 2283)</P>

<P>COU 2123 Introduction to Counseling	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is an introduction counseling, emphasizing individual, groups, and families. Basic counseling skills will be taught. It introduces students to interviewing and intervention strategies. Students will learn assessment, evaluation, and planning.</P>

<P>COU 2213 Counseling Children and Adolescents 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course presents assessment, diagnosis, and remedial therapeutic techniques unique to the practice of counseling children and adolescents and presenting parents with tools to utilize in facilitating growth in their children. (Prerequisite: CMN 2313 or COU 2283)(Same as SWK 2213)</P>

<P>COU 2223 Addictive Behavior and Recovery 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will explore assessment and treatment of various addictions including substance abuse (drug and alcohol), sexual addictions (pornography), self mutilation, and other compulsive addictive behavior, and will focus on strategies for recovery. (Same as SWK 2223)</P>

<P>COU 2513 Counseling Methods in Chemical Dependency and Other Addictions 	3 Hours</P>

<P>A course in counseling methods and techniques with the substance abusing and/or addictive client. Individual, family and group processes and interventions are explored in rehabilitation and recovery programs such as criminal justice agencies, therapeutic communities, and various faith-based community addictions services. Current models of prevention and intervention are studied as well as the 12-step recovery approach. One area of focus includes the special skills and techniques utilized with the Alcohol and Other Drug (AOD) client, incorporating the 12 core functions of an addiction counselor. i.e., screening, intake, assessment, treatment planning, case management, counseling, crisis intervention, client education, referral, report and record keeping, and consultation. (Same as PSY 2513)</P>

<P>COU 2523 Professional, Ethical and Special Issues for the Addictions Professional 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course includes a systematic review of the competencies and knowledge areas required in preparation for licensure as a chemical dependency counselor in Texas. However, there should be significant overlap with those seeking licensure in other states. The competence, role and function of the addiction counselor are reviewed in relation to such issues as stress, burn-out, resilience, dealing with denial and resistance, client defense mechanisms, confidentiality, scope of practice and type of clientele. Ethical guidelines and dilemmas are explored along with such special issues as criminal behavior and the criminal justice system, cultural norms and influences, family-of-origin dynamics, alcohol family roles, codependency, domestic violence, child abuse, HIV-AIDS awareness, women’s issues, and Judeo-Christian perspectives on addictive behavior. (Same as PSY 2523)</P>

<P>COU 2533 Pharmacology of Addiction	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course examines the psychological, physiological, and sociological effects of mood altering substances and behaviors and their implications for the addiction process, including signs and symptoms of addictive behavior and phases of relapse. There is an emphasis on pharmacological effects of tolerance, dependency/withdrawal, cross addiction, and drug interaction. HIV, AIDS, STDS, and addiction related pathology are also covered. (Same as PSY 2533)</P>

<P>COU 3111 Practicum in Substance Abuse Counseling I</P>

<P>	1 Hour</P>

<P>This course focuses on practical, general workplace training supported by an individualized learning plan developed by the employer, University, and student. This course fulfills 100 of the required 300 hours practicum for LCDC. (Prerequisite: COU 2123, COU 2223, COU 2513, COU 2523, COU 2533, PSY 3443) (Same as PSY 3111)</P>

<P>COU 3113 Theories of Marriage and Family Counseling 			3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the theoretical foundations of family systems and the major theories and models in family systems. Emphasis is on psychodynamic, cognitive/behavioral, systems, experiential, transgenerational, structural, and strategic models of family therapy. </P>

<P>COU 3121 Practicum in Substance Abuse Counseling II</P>

<P>	1 Hour</P>

<P>This course focuses on practical, general workplace training supported by an individualized learning plan developed by the employer, University, and student. This course fulfills 100 of the required 300 hours practicum for LCDC. (Prerequisite: COU 2123, COU 2223, COU 2513, COU 2523, COU 2533, PSY 3443) (Same as PSY 3121)</P>

<P>COU 3123 Advanced Methods and Techniques in Counseling</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course presents counseling methods with individuals, groups, and organizations. It includes collecting, assessing data, as well as planning, implementing, and evaluating interventions. Major schools of counseling and psychotherapy will provide students with a practical orientation to the field. (Prerequisite: COU 2123)</P>

<P>COU 3131 Practicum in Substance Abuse Counseling III</P>

<P>	1 Hour</P>

<P>This course focuses on practical, general workplace training supported by an individualized learning plan developed by the employer, University, and student. This course fulfills 100 of the required 300 hours practicum for LCDC. (Prerequisite: COU 2123, COU 2223, COU 2513, COU 2523, COU 2533, PSY 3443) (Same as PSY 3131)</P>

<P>COU 3213 Counseling Adult Populations 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a study of counseling adults. Students explore adult developmental issues and adult adjustment to physical, social, and psychological changes. Techniques for counseling adults are introduced. This course also includes a study of counseling issues relating to grief, death, and dying. </P>

<P>COU 3443 Crisis Intervention and Management	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a study of crisis intervention and management with a Christian perspective. This course reviews theoretical models of crisis development in a variety of settings. Students will develop an understanding of intervention and management techniques demonstrating a competency in crisis intervention skills. Special emphasis is given to suicide, family crisis, and major catastrophes. (Same as PSY 3443, SWK 3443)</P>

<P>COU 4313 Behavioral Science Research 	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the various research methods in the behavioral sciences. Emphasis is on the techniques used as well as the process and ethics of research. Topics investigated include: sampling, hypothesis development and testing, and research design. (Prerequisite: PSY 2413. Same as PSY 4313, SWK 4313)</P>

<P>COU 4413 Methods and Techniques in Marriage and Family Counseling  	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the use of particular techniques for working with marriages and families in counseling. Theory and practice will be integrated to identify when and how to use techniques with couples and families in the counseling setting. Role play and practice will be an integral part of this course. (Prerequisite: CMN 2313 or COU 2283. Same as SWK 4413)</P>

<P>COU 4513 Special Issues in the Behavioral Sciences 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course focuses on research, defense and logical argumentation of special and controversial issues in the behavioral sciences from a Christian perspective. Students will apply theoretical, biblical and research-based studies to these discussions. Strategies for researching background information and behavioral science studies as well as appropriate participation in the discussions and debates will be emphasized. (Same as PSY 4513) (Replaced by COU 4523)</P>

<P>COU 4523 Advanced General Counseling	3 Hours</P>

<P>This is a capstone course designed for upper level senior advanced undergraduate students in counseling to review, explore special issues in counseling, and prepare and assist in developing a more in-depth orientation to main domains of counseling from which they have studied in their counseling curriculum. It also helps to expand their knowledge of counseling as preparation for graduate school. Further, a Major Studies Examination in Counseling is provided over multiple domains in the discipline. Through the integration of knowledge in psychological science with a Christian worldview, the student is required to complete a senior level research project under the supervision of a major professor in counseling. In this regard the counseling major is challenged to further develop their critical thinking, research knowledge and skill. (Prerequisites: COU 3213, COU 3273, COU 3443, COU 4313, COU 4413)</P>

<P>COU 4583 Field Practicum 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course requires the student to complete 120 hours in an off-campus setting allowing him or her the opportunity for experiential learning. Students will complete assignments designed to demonstrate knowledge, competency of the profession, and the ability to complete guided field research. </P>

<P>COU 4593 Counseling Ministries Practicum	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course requires the student to complete 120 hours in an off-campus setting allowing the opportunity for experiential learning. Students will complete assignments designed to demonstrate knowledge, competency of the profession, and the ability to complete guided field research. Students will demonstrate the ability to minister to the needs of the mentally ill and function as mental health care givers in church related settings. Field research may include but is not limited to direct observation of mental health disorders and/or the visitation of approved mental health facilities.</P>

<P>COU 4993 Special Topics	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will focus on a specific topic including those which demand further intensive study as well as contemporary issues. In this regard, this course allows for recent developments and latest issues in the field related to a specific topic as well as the possible research interests of the professor. This course is intended to provide the student the opportunity to enhance their knowledge of a selected topic by examination of salient, current critical issues. This course may be taken as a general elective and may be repeated for another topic. (Prerequisites: Permission to take this subject has to be approved by the program coordinator or department chair.)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>CRIMINAL JUSTICE  </New_Style_Sheet>

<P>CJU 1113 Introduction to Criminal Justice   	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introductory course in criminal justice.  The history and philosophy of criminal justice in a democratic society is reviewed along with an analysis of the structure and function of criminal justice systems in the United States. Aspects of law and the courts, justice, criminal procedures, adjudication and law enforcement are explored.</P>

<P>CJU 1123 Ethics in Criminal Justice   	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of ethical concepts and issues in criminal justice. Standards, professional conduct and responsibilities of the criminal justice practitioner are examined in accordance with current ethical practices and issues in the field. Problems confronting law enforcement, the courts and correctional systems are addressed from an academic, professional and Christian worldview perspective. (Prerequisite: CJU 1113)</P>

<P>CJU 2113 Analysis of Police Operations  	 3 Hours</P>

<P>This course examines the administrative structure, management practices and operational processes of law enforcement agencies and personnel.  Police and security issues such as recruiting, patrol techniques, criminal investigation including interviewing, search and seizure, and arrest procedures are examined.</P>

<P>CJU 2123 Criminal Investigation	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the theory, history and methods of obtaining and reporting information from the crime scene, victims, witnesses and suspects. Processes of scientific crime detection, case management and documentation in criminal investigation are reviewed. Components of this course also include a focus on methods used with certain types of major and minor crimes including homicides, assaults, sex offenses, property crimes and others.</P>

<P>CJU 3113 Constitutional Law   	3 Hours</P>

<P>An analysis of the United States Constitution.  An exploration of the historical foundation and context of the constitution as well as state and federal relationships is conducted.  Key United </P>

<P>States Supreme Court decisions are reviewed in relation to their impact on American society. </P>

<P>CJU 3123 Theories of Criminology   	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of basic concepts and theories of criminal behavior as well as all the major types of crimes.  Basic methods and programs of prevention, control and treatment in relation to criminal justice agencies are reviewed.</P>

<P>CJU 3133 Delinquent Behavior and Rehabilitation 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a study of the nature, extent, causation, prevention and rehabilitation processes of juvenile delinquency.  Case management as well as procedures and operation of juvenile justice systems are also included. (Same as SWK 3133)</P>

<P>CJU 3143 Criminal Justice Administration   	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of administrative processes in various criminal justice agencies including law enforcement is provided.  Management principles, theories and practices are examined in the context of criminal justice administration. (Prerequisite: CJU 1113)</P>

<P>CJU 3153 Criminal Justice, Psychology and the Law 	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study that examines the interface between criminal justice, psychology and the law. Legal, ethical and investigative issues are examined in relation to civil rights, child welfare, mental health and criminal behavior.  The role of specialists including polygraph examiners, investigators and forensic psychologists is reviewed.</P>

<P>CJU 3163 Advanced Criminal Investigation  	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a continuation of CJU 2123. The course includes advanced crime scene technology and criminalistic applications under simulated field conditions. The students will conduct experiments individually and in groups in fingerprint identification and categorization, development processes, crime scene photography, fiber analysis, soil analysis, tool marks, Locard’s exchange principle, blood stain, spatter analysis, serology, tire impressions, questioned document analysis, ballistic evidence, microscopic analysis, report writing, physical evidence submission procedures, crime scene measurement and crime scene sketch-rough and finished. The course culminates in small groups utilizing the techniques learned to process a simulated homicide just as if they were a crime scene investigator-criminalist. (Prerequisites: CJU 1113, CJU 2123)</P>

<P>CJU 4113 Correctional Psychology   	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of correctional policies, procedures and approaches with regard to the management and treatment of the correctional client is explored.  An analysis of selected offender types as well as approaches in treatment and current intervention trends is provided.</P>

<P>CJU 4123 Advanced Penology   	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the history and evaluation of the correctional process with emphasis on American correctional facilities and prisons.  Also, an evaluation of community based programs is included. (Prerequisite: CJU 1113)</P>

<P>CJU 4133 Security Management   	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of security processes and management.  This course examines major processes in security including business, institutional and community areas.  Administrative principles and practices are surveyed in relation to criminal behavior including terrorism. (Prerequisite: CJU 1113)</P>

<P>CJU 4583 Field Practicum in Criminal Justice   	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course requires students to complete 120 hours of supervision in a criminal justice setting allowing the student the opportunity to gain practical knowledge, skill and experience in criminal justice. Enrollment in practicum must be approved by the CJ academic advisor or department chair. (May be repeated once as elective in another area of criminal justice.).</P>

<P>CJU 4993 Special Topics   	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will focus on a specific topic including those which demand further intensive study as well as contemporary issues. In this regard, this course allows for recent developments and latest issues in the field related to a specific topic as well as the possible research interests of the professor. This course is intended to provide the student the opportunity to enhance their knowledge of a selected topic by examination of salient, current critical issues. This course may be taken as a general elective and may be repeated for another topic. (Prerequisites: Permission to take this subject has to be approved by the program coordinator or department chair.)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>DRAMA</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>DRA 1131 Drama Group I	1 Hour</P>

<P>A small select group from all departments for extensive drama ministry in camps, churches, and conventions throughout the southwest region, with a major emphasis on promotion of SAGU. (Admission by audition.)</P>

<P>DRA 1141 Music/Drama Workshop	1 Hour</P>

<P>For students desiring credit as a result of participation in musical theatre productions. (Admission by audition.)</P>

<P>DRA 2123 Fundamentals and Theories of Acting	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course includes a review of the prominent theories of acting, beginning with those of Constantine Stanislavski. Attention is given to Stanislavski’s theoretical perspectives. Includes  beginning level study of scene work, monologues, script analysis, and techniques of character development.</P>

<P>DRA 2211 Play Production	1 Hour</P>

<P>Experience in the practical aspects of play production as an actor and/or a technician. Participation in dramatic productions including a thorough study of the play, the development of characters in rehearsal and performance of the role, set design and construction, costuming, lighting, sound and makeup.</P>

<P/>

<P>DRA 2223 The Art of Storytelling	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the fundamentals of storytelling. In this course, emphasis is placed on relaxation, audience engagement, timing, material selection and application. Students will apply the principles of storytelling to the interpretation and recreation of a variety of story genres from fairy tales to biblical narratives. The art of storytelling is highly dependent on in-class participation.</P>

<P>DRA 2233 Stage Makeup	3 Hours</P>

<P>Design and execution of makeup for the purpose of developing believable characters for the stage. This course will include discussion and demonstration of basic stage makeup principles and practical experience of makeup application. The following types of makeup application will be demonstrated, studied and executed in class: corrective, old age, fantasy, wounds/scars, and animal. A makeup morgue will also be required..</P>

<P>DRA 2333 Theatrical Movement	3 Hours</P>

<P>Introduction to the fundamentals of movement for the stage. Students will become familiar with the theories of Laban and others. The course will include a practical method for approaching problems and movement in a scene, helping actors to become more versatile through the principles of posture, alignment, breathing and centering.</P>

<P>DRA 3111 Drama Seminar    	1 Hour</P>

<P>The seminar shall bring to the campus eminent persons with experience in different phases of drama.  They shall function as resource persons whose experience and insights provide exposure for prospective drama majors.  (Maximum of three DRA 3111 seminars may be counted toward graduation)</P>

<P>DRA 3123 History of Drama   	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of the historical development of theatrical traditions from  pre-Grecian times to the present. Topics cover theory of dramatic criticism, physical staging, analysis of drama conventions, and the cultural and social vantage point of drama. Selected dramatic works from the various dramatic periods are read and analyzed.</P>

<P>DRA 3133 Directing for Theatre   	3 Hours</P>

<P>Principles and theories of stage movement, blocking, casting, rehearsals and performance will be covered. Laboratory training will be provided in techniques of conducting rehearsals and directing the work of actors and other production personnel including character development and play production.  The fundamentals of play directing are covered emphasizing research techniques, promptbook formatting, and historical investigation of directorial theories.  There is special emphasis on the function of the director as interpreter, organizer, and teacher.  Students required to direct scenes for class production.  (Prerequisites:  Approval of the instructor.)</P>

<P>DRA 3153 Advanced Theories of Acting I	3 Hours</P>

<P>Students will develop the ability to act from a truthful point of view by focusing on the scene partner and physical activities in the present moment. Through the use of repetition exercises, students will develop listening and intuitive skills which will culminate in scene work. (Prerequisite: Permission of the Instructor)</P>

<P>DRA 3163 Advanced Theories of Acting II	3 Hours</P>

<P>Students will learn the skills of emotional preparation in order to begin to create characters with specific, given circumstances. Through script analysis and a thorough reading of the text, students will develop scenes to be performed in class. (Prerequisite: DRA 3153)</P>

<P>DRA 3211 Drama Group II	1 Hour</P>

<P>A select group from all departments for extensive drama training for play productions, Southwestern Live!, drama ministry and other outlets for the communication arts productions with an emphasis on performance and promotion of SAGU. (Admission by audition.)</P>

<P>DRA 3343 Voice and Diction	3 Hours</P>

<P>Introduction to the fundamentals of vocal production for the stage. Emphasis on relaxation, breathing techniques, the creation of vocal sound, the interconnection of voice and body, and the use of acceptable grammar and pronunciation in formal presentations will be discussed. (Prerequisite: Permission of Instructor)</P>

<P>DRA 3353 Script Analysis	3 Hours</P>

<P>An investigation of dramatic structure from the points of view of the director, actor and designer in order to facilitate the dramatic process. Emphasis will be placed on the various practical applications of script analysis. Course incorporates elements of dramatic theory and their relevance to script analysis. This course may focus on specific time periods and genres. (Prerequisite: Permission of Instructor)</P>

<P>DRA 4113 Play Production II	3 Hours</P>

<P>Advanced practical aspects of play production as a technician. Participation in dramatic productions including set design and construction, costuming, lighting sound, makeup and a thorough study of the play, development of characters, performance of a role, or working with actors as a student director. (Prerequisite: Permission of the instructor)</P>

<P>DRA 4123 Theatrical Design	3 Hours</P>

<P>The history, theory, and basic concepts of design methods with application for the stage. Aesthetic skills of color, line, texture, and form, and the interactions of these elements. Mechanics and techniques of illustration and rendering of design ideas. Students will explore scenic costume, and lighting design. (Prerequisite: Permission of Instructor)</P>

<P>DRA 4133 Dramaturgy	3 Hours</P>

<P>Study of dramaturgy - its tasks, its techniques, and its function in the contemporary theatre. Students gain an understanding of the historical emergence of dramaturgy as a distinct discipline within the western theatre. Exploration of how the practice can best be taught. This class will include production-oriented research, text analysis, collaboration techniques, and season development. (Prerequisite: Permission of Instructor)</P>

<P>DRA 4143 Advanced Theories of Acting III	3 Hours</P>

<P>Principles of Shakespearean verse and prose for actors and directors. This class will include text analysis of sonnets and plays for solo performance and scene work. (Prerequisite: Permission of the Instructor)</P>

<P>DRA 4423 Drama as Ministry 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of how to use the dramatic arts as a ministry tool in teaching biblical principles. This course includes a study of the theological background and history of church drama ministry and contemporary Christian plays. Emphasis will be on how to formulate ideas and materials for writing short sketches and plays for the ministry. The actual writing of scripts and the performance of those scripts will be part of the class.</P>

<P/>

<P/>

<New_Style_Sheet>EDUCATION</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>Admission to the Education program must be attained before a student can take 4000 level EDU courses.</P>

<P>ECE 1113 Foundations of Early Childhood Education	3 Hours </P>

<P>A foundational course in early education based on child development principles. Early childhood curriculum, classroom environment, organization, relationships, and management principles are explored as well as the implementation and use of various technologies, methodologies, and materials. Also included are the foundational components of Christian child care including health and safety, physical and intellectual development, social and emotional development, relationships with families, child care operations, professionalism, biblical integration, and assessment through observation and recording behavior. Requirement for ACSI Early Childhood Teacher Certification. </P>

<P>EDP 3143 Teaching Social Studies in Elementary	3 Hours</P>

<P>A development of the understanding of content and appropriate pedagogy for social studies in the elementary classroom including history, Texas history, geography, economics, government, citizenship, and culture. State social studies standards and curriculum guidelines and appropriate technology is incorporated.</P>

<P>EDP 3413 Instructional Technology	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is designed to enable educators to use technology to enhance instruction within and across the content areas. Emphasis is placed on the utilization and evaluation of technologies and their appropriateness for the curriculum. National and state technology standards and curriculum guidelines will be incorporated.</P>

<P/>

<P>EDP 3423 Classroom Management	3 Hours</P>

<P>Examine research-based methods and strategies to create positive learning environments in culturally diverse classroom settings. Emphasis will be given to the organization and management of the learner centered classroom. Strategies that engage and motivate learners to improve instruction and minimize disruptive behaviors will be explored. State standards will be incorporated.</P>

<P/>

<P>EDP 3433 Classroom Instruction and Assessment for English Language Learners	3 Hours</P>

<P>Explore strategies and methods for teaching English as second language in elementary and secondary schools. Develop instructional strategies to promote ESL students’ language and literacy development. Emphasis will be given to curriculum design, resources, instructional methods, content area instruction, and language assessment necessary to meet the diverse needs of ESL students in the K-12 setting. State standards and curriculum guidelines will be incorporated.</P>

<P>EDP 4111 Educator Assessment	1 Hour</P>

<P>An emphasis on test taking strategies in preparation for professional educator examinations. (Prerequisites:  EDU 2253, PSY 2323, PSY 3353)</P>

<P>EDP 4123 Teaching Science in Elementary	3 Hours</P>

<P>A development of the understanding of content and appropriate pedagogy for physical, earth, life and space science in the elementary classroom.  The course covers the use of manipulative, lesson plans and cooperative groups.  State science standards, curriculum guidelines, and appropriate technology are incorporated.</P>

<P>EDP 4143 Teaching Math in Elementary	3 Hours</P>

<P>A focus on teaching mathematical concepts in the elementary school.  This course includes number theory, rational numbers, geometric ideas, measurement attributes, probability and related technology.  Lesson plans and assessment are also incorporated. (Replaced by EDP 4153)</P>

<P>EDP 4153 Elementary Math Concepts	3 Hours</P>

<P>A focus on teaching mathematical concepts in the elementary school.  This course includes number theory, rational numbers, geometric ideas, measurement attributes, probability and related technology.  Lesson plans and assessment are also incorporated.</P>

<P>EDP 4163 Methods in Teaching Elementary Math	3 Hours</P>

<P>A research-based study of the best practices for teaching mathematics in the EC-6 classroom. Emphasis will be given to the organization, curriculum design, resources, instructional methods, strategies, and assessments in the learner-centered math class. State standards and curriculum guidelines will be incorporated.</P>

<P>EDP 4613 Teaching Elementary Physical Education	3 Hours</P>

<P>A field-based course characterized by observations of various elementary physical education classes with an in-class emphasis on the design and implementation of instructional strategies. This course emphasizes necessary teacher competencies in physical education with an emphasis on cultural diversity. It includes the studies in movement, health-related physical fitness, and the physical education program. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of physical education)</P>

<P>EDP 4623 Teaching Secondary Physical Education	3 Hours</P>

<P>A field-based course characterized by observations of various middle and secondary physical education classes with an in-class emphasis on the design and implementation of instructional strategies. This course emphasizes necessary teacher competencies in physical education with an emphasis on cultural diversity. It includes the studies in movement, health-related physical fitness, and the physical education program. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of physical education)</P>

<P>EDU 2253 Foundations of Education	3 Hours </P>

<P>A historical survey of philosophical concepts and competencies related to the field of education. This course focuses on pedagogy and professional responsibilities which ensure that the teacher designs instruction appropriate for all students, utilizes effective classroom management strategies to create a classroom environment of respect and rapport, and promotes student learning by providing responsive instruction. Legal and ethical requirements are also emphasized. Includes field experience and related technology.</P>

<P/>

<P>EDU 4173 Curriculum Development and Assessment I </P>

<P>	3 Hours </P>

<P>An examination of pedagogy and effective teaching strategies.  This course examines attributes and characteristics of effective teachers, teaching diverse populations, motivation of student learners, as well as implementation of state fine arts standards and curriculum guidelines. Includes field experience and related technology. (Prerequisite: Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program.)</P>

<P>EDU 4183 Curriculum Development and Assessment II </P>

<P>	3 Hours </P>

<P>An in-depth study of pedagogy and effective teaching strategies.  This course examines lesson planning, instructional alternatives, cooperative learning, classroom management and assessment, as well as implementation of state health and physical education standards and curriculum guidelines. Includes field experience and related technology. (Prerequisite: Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program.)</P>

<P>EDU 4243 Teaching Social Studies	3 Hours</P>

<P>An emphasis on the instructional strategies for teaching the most important types of social studies. This course emphasizes necessary teacher competencies and the organization and various methods used for different grade levels and achievement levels of middle and secondary school students with an emphasis on cultural diversity. It includes the use of instructional media, measurement, evaluation, technology and lesson planning. Extensive field experiences are included. (Prerequisites: 12 hours of History, Government, or Geography; Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program.)</P>

<P>EDU 4253 Special Issues and Populations 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An examination of current issues for early childhood through grade 12. It will include studies in developmentally appropriate classroom management, learning strategies, multicultural issues, inclusion, and identification and characteristics of special populations with an emphasis on pedagogy and professional responsibilities. This course will include field experience in schools representing cultural diversity, and employ related technology. (Prerequisites: Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program.)(Replaced by EDU 4563)</P>

<P>EDU 4263 Teaching English Language Arts 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A field-based course characterized by observations of various middle and secondary English Language Arts classrooms with an in-class emphasis on the design and implementation of instructional strategies and technology for teaching the language arts curriculum for reading, grammar, composition, listening/speaking, viewing/representing, and literature to culturally diverse middle and secondary school students. (Prerequisites: 18 hours of English; Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program.)</P>

<P>EDU 4273 Advanced Strategies for Teaching	3 Hours </P>

<P>Advanced strategies of teaching will be explored including the use of technology. Extensive field experiences are included. (Prerequisite: Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program.)</P>

<P/>

<P/>

<P>EDU 4293 Curriculum and Instruction in Elementary Music</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a comprehensive study of musical elements, structures, forms, genres, and literature in elementary music related to the stages of child development. Teacher competencies, lesson planning, materials, teaching strategies, the TEA music framework and TEKS for teaching elementary music are explored. Field experience and related technologies are included. (Prerequisite: Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program.)</P>

<P>EDU 4313 Curriculum and Instruction in Secondary Music</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course examines teaching approaches common to choral and instrumental music instruction in secondary schools. Aspects of adolescent psychology, rehearsal management, recruitment procedures, selection of suitable music literature, concert programming, performance preparation, fundraising, and adjudicated events are integrated. Field experience and related technologies are included. (Prerequisite: Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program.)</P>

<P>EDU 4353 Teaching Theatre Arts	3 Hours</P>

<P>A field-based course characterized by observations of various theatre classrooms with an in-class emphasis on the design and implementation of instructional strategies and technology for teaching the creating, utilizing, and/or performing dramatic material, producing and directing theatrical productions, design and technical theatre from different cultures and historical periods, and demonstrates the interrelationship between theatre and other disciplines. (Prerequisite: 18 hours of Drama; must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program.)</P>

<P>EDU 4363 Teaching Mathematics 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A field-based course characterized by observations of various mathematics classrooms with an in-class emphasis on the design and implementation of instructional strategies and technology for teaching Number Theory, Abstract Algebra, Modern Geometry, Linear Algebra, Statistics and Probability, and Calculus. (Prerequisite: 18 hours of Mathematics; must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education program.)</P>

<P>EDU 4479 Student Teaching All Level	9 Hours</P>

<P>Student teaching in EC-12 classrooms at schools approved or recognized by the Texas Education Agency. Students must apply to student teaching by an assigned date. (Prerequisite: EDP 4111; Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program and approved for Student Teaching.)</P>

<P>EDU 4489 Student Teaching Middle/Secondary	9 Hours</P>

<P>Student teaching in a grade 4-8 or 8-12 classroom at a school approved or recognized by the Texas Education Agency. Students must apply to student teaching by an assigned date. (Prerequisites: EDP 4111; Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program and approved for Student Teaching.) </P>

<P>EDU 4499 Student Teaching Elementary	9 Hours</P>

<P>Student teaching in elementary classroom at a school approved or recognized by the Texas Education Agency. Students must apply to student teaching by an assigned date. (Prerequisite: EDP 4111; Must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education Program and approved for Student Teaching.)</P>

<P>EDU 4563/EDU 5563 Special Issues and Populations 	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of current issues pertaining to special education populations for early childhood through grade 12. Educating students with various cognitive, social, emotional, and physical limitations in inclusive settings will be emphasized. Students will examine special education law and discuss the expectations and responsibilities of the general education teacher. Field experience included. (Prerequisite: Undergraduate students must be formally admitted to the Teacher Education program)</P>

<P/>

<New_Style_Sheet>ENGLISH</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>ENG 0013 Developmental Composition 	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to those aspects of reading and composition necessary for college work including the study of the fundamentals of grammar. All students reflecting verbal deficits in their ACT or SAT test scores are required to enroll in this course. This course does not fulfill the requirement for English in the core curriculum. Students enrolled in this course must earn at least a C (70%) to progress to ENG 1113.</P>

<P>ENG 0111 Composition Lab 	1 Hours</P>

<P>Composition Lab provides additional support in college-level reading and writing for students whose admissions scores suggest a need, and for students moving from Integrated Reading and Writing to Composition I. Students who are required to enroll in Composition Lab will do so concurrently with Composition I. This course does not fulfill the requirement for English in the core curriculum.</P>

<P>ENG 0113 Integrated Reading and Writing 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course focuses on college readiness in reading and writing. Students whose admissions scores in reading and writing do not reflect college readiness are required to enroll in this course. This course does not fulfill the requirement for English in the core curriculum.</P>

<P>ENG 1113 Composition and Rhetoric I 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A review of the principles of English grammar. Various rhetorical genres of composition are studied and practiced. Parallel readings of professional and student writers are required. Vocabulary development is required. </P>

<P>ENG 1123 Composition and Rhetoric II 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A continuation of ENG 1113. The research paper is discussed and composed. The rhetorical modes of argumentation and critical analysis are studied and practiced. Parallel readings of professional and student writers are required. (Prerequisite: ENG 1113 or equivalent)</P>

<P>ENG 2233 American Literature I 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey of representative works from the foundational Colonial Period through the Civil War in the mid-nineteenth century. Imaginative artistic works will be studied along with political and theological masterpieces in relation to the historical and cultural context of that time frame. (Prerequisite: ENG 1123)</P>

<P/>

<P>ENG 2243 American Literature II 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A continuation of ENG 2233. Emphasis is placed on prose and poetry of the latter 19th century through the 20th century, with representative works from diverse cultures. (Prerequisite: ENG 1123)</P>

<P>ENG 2273 Introduction to Literature 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey course of the major genres of literature, including short story, poetry, and drama. Designed to develop analytical reading skills and an appreciation for literature that reflects a range of diverse cultures. (Prerequisite: ENG 1123)</P>

<P>ENG 3113 Children’s Literature 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A course designed to accommodate wide reading in literature for children, with emphasis on a variety of cultures, genres, and award-winning authors and illustrators. Includes emphasis on personal and educational values of literature for children. </P>

<P>ENG 3123 English Literature I 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey of the masterpieces in English literature, both prose and poetry, from the Anglo-Saxon Medieval Ages, Renaissance, and Age of Reason. (Replaced by ENG 3383)</P>

<P>ENG 3143 Creative Writing in Elementary	3 Hours</P>

<P>A course designed to develop writers by instilling a habit of close reading that can be applied to any genre, for any age group. Includes emphasis on the importance of voice in writing. (Prerequisites: ENG 1113, ENG 1123)</P>

<P>ENG 3153 Modern American Authors	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of significant twenty and twenty-first century American literature to investigate the way different authors engage aspects of American culture. This course will include a mix of literary genres and will emphasize close reading and critical writing.</P>

<P>ENG 3163 Christian Thought In Literature	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of writers, both past and present, who integrate faith into their works. Authors may include John Bunyan, Gerard Manley Hopkins, J.R.R. Tolkien, C. S. Lewis, Randy Alcorn, and selected others.</P>

<P>ENG 3173 Special Topics in Literature	3 Hours</P>

<P>Intensive examination of the literature of one or more authors, periods, regions, minorities, genres, or other selected topics.  May be repeated once for credit when topics vary.</P>

<P>ENG 3183 19th Century American Literature	3 Hours</P>

<P>American poetry, prose, and drama from 1800 to 1900.  Special emphasis will be given to the development of the American novel from its origins through the beginning of the 20th century, to consider the close ties between novels and social, scientific, and political issues in their day. Readings may include works by James Fennimore Cooper, Nathaniel Hawthorne, Herman Melville, Louisa May Alcott, Henry James, Harriet Beecher Stowe, Mark Twain, Sarah Orne Jewett, and Frank Norris.</P>

<P>ENG 3233 English Literature II 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey of the masterpieces in English literature, both prose and poetry, from the Romantic and Victorian eras and the Twentieth-Century. (Replaced by ENG 3433)</P>

<P/>

<P>ENG 3283 Teaching English as a Second Language and Diversity I    	 3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the theory and methods of teaching English as a second language with specific attention to methods of teaching listening, speaking, reading, and writing. This course covers oral proficiency level ratings, pronunciation, reading skills appropriate for different levels, and vocabulary development.</P>

<P>ENG 3293 Teaching English as a Second Language and Diversity II   	3 Hours</P>

<P>A continuation of ENG 3283, this course will focus on methods teaching the structure of English and writing  to speakers of other languages. (Prerequisite: ENG 3283)</P>

<P>ENG 3343 Young Adult Literature 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey course of the award-winning authors, contemporary and classic, in the field of young adult literature. Emphasis will be placed on the intersection of the literature with cultural trends, pedagogical issues, and identity formation. </P>

<P>ENG 3363 Creative Writing in Middle/Secondary	3 Hours</P>

<P>A course designed to nurture writers by instilling a habit of close reading in any genre to discover how effective writers structure and develop their works. Includes emphasis on the importance of voice in writing. (Prerequisites: ENG 1113, ENG 1123. Same as JOU 3363) </P>

<P>ENG 3373 Bible as Literature 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A course designed to develop an appreciation for the artistry and beauty of the literature of the Bible. Emphasis will be placed upon literary genres, such as heroic narrative, epic, tragedy, lyric, poetry, and pastoral romance. This approach complements historical and theological approaches to the study of the Scriptures. (Same as BIB 3373)</P>

<P>ENG 3383 British Literature I	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of the masterpieces in British literature, both prose and poetry, from the Anglo-Saxon Medieval Ages, Renaissance, and Age of Reason.

ENG 3413 Introduction to Linguistics	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the theories, methods, and basic terminology of linguistics, including descriptive linguistics (phonetics, phonology, morphology, syntax, and semantics), socio, psycho, and neurolinguistics. Each area will consider the diverse cultures within our complex society. This course provides a foundation in linguistics for educators.</P>

<P>ENG 3423 Linguistics II	3 Hours</P>

<P>A continuation of ENG 3413  providing an in-depth study of descriptive linguistics (phonetics, phonology, morphology, syntax, and semantics). Principles and methods of socio and historical linguistics will be covered within the context of diverse cultures. (Prerequisite: ENG 3413)</P>

<P>ENG 3433 British Literature II	3 Hours
A survey of the masterpieces in British literature, both prose and poetry, from the Romantic and Victorian eras and the Twentieth-Century.</P>

<P>ENG 3513 Rhetorical Studies in Film I	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of films using a rhetorical analysis framework, with an overview of objective, mimetic, pragmatic, and expressive theories applied to the film, the writer, and the culture. Various genres of film will be examined, such as comedy, drama, mystery, science fiction, musical, and animation. (Same as COM 3513)</P>

<P>ENG 3523 Rhetorical Studies in Film II	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course focuses on the viability of film as an effective tool to communicate biblical and Christian values, those of the Church, for all of culture. Films pertaining to evangelism and discipleship, marriage and family, eschatology, missiology, and other doctrinal truths of the Bible will be analyzed rhetorically for their thematic, artistic, social, and cinematic effectiveness. (Same as COM 3523)</P>

<P>ENG 4133 Introduction to Literary Theory	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course surveys important trends in literary theory, to highlight the impact of philosophy and cultural theory on the study of literature, with an emphasis on the twentieth and twenty-first centuries. Attention will be directed to the specific aesthetic problems that surface in reading and interpreting literature, considering tensions that exist between a literary work, its readers and cultural contexts. A primary focus will be answering questions raised by postmodern theory about the nature and function of the literary critic - from a biblical worldview, with the intent to develop Christian literary critics/apologists. This class is the capstone course for critical thinking in the English B.A. and will be required for students who plan to enroll in graduate school.</P>

<P>ENG 4143 The Victorian Period	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course examines the genre of the Victorian novel, poetry, and/or drama.  Questions to be addressed include why the novel  emerges in this period to challenge the preeminence of poetry, why realism becomes its dominant style, and how particular novelists respond to the substantial changes occurring in British society, including industrialization, political reform, and changing relations between the sexes and classes.</P>

<P>ENG 4153 American Drama	3 Hours</P>

<P>Representative plays by the major playwrights of the American theatre in a variety of eras.  Movements in theater and changes in theatrical conventions will provide a historical context.  Limited readings in criticism.</P>

<P>ENG 4173 Contemporary American Poetry	3 Hours</P>

<P>Intensive study of contemporary American poets, poetic movements and relevant issues in aesthetics.</P>

<P>ENG 4413 Advanced Grammar and Composition	3 Hours </P>

<P>Advanced expository writing course reviewing the composing process and principles of research writing. Examples from classic and contemporary writing that will reflect diverse cultures will be provided. The terminology, functions, and usage of English grammar will be included. (Prerequisite: 15 hours of English) </P>

<P>ENG 4423 World Literature 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey of world literature that reflects many different cultures, including masterpieces from the time of Homer to John Milton. </P>

<P>ENG 4433 Shakespeare 	3 Hours</P>

<P>An analysis of the major tragedies, comedies, histories, and </P>

<P/>

<P>romances of Shakespeare. These works will be studied within the historical and cultural context of the Renaissance Age. </P>

<P>ENG 4443 Advanced Communication Arts 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Designed specifically for elementary education majors, this course focuses on the role of language in effective communication, with emphasis on the history of the English language, on word and sentence formation, and on the basics of traditional grammar.  </P>

<New_Style_Sheet>GENERAL EDUCATION STUDIES</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>GES 0011 AIM I   	1 Hour </P>

<P>This remedial course is designed for students entering SAGU needing additional academic preparation to meet the challenges of college level work. Under the guidance of the Director of the Learning Center, students work individually with peer tutors in developing competence in critical study skills. Some of the basic skills emphasized are time management, organization, note taking methodologies, memory improvement, and test-taking strategies. Students entering the University on conditional acceptance are required to take this course.</P>

<P>GES 0021 AIM II 	1 Hour </P>

<P>AIM II is the continuation of remedial skill development from AIM I. Emphasis is placed on the student’s current courses. The peer-tutor model is still employed but each student will be expected to independently demonstrate competency in the appropriate application of study strategies. The identification of challenges and the setting of academic goals will be done with the tutor staff. Students will also be required to take the career assessment in the Career Office, if not previously taken. All students entering SAGU with a conditional acceptance are required to complete both semesters of the course.</P>

<P>GES 0031 Crossroads   	1 Hour</P>

<P>Crossroads is designed for students needing additional academic support and is a requirement for all students in a first time academic probationary status or a continuing academic probationary status (as defined by the current catalog). With the staff and the Director of the Learning Center, students will identify academic areas for emphasis and design a plan for academic success. Each student will be assigned a peer tutor who will give weekly academic assistance. Students meeting satisfactory academic achievement levels, as defined above, will be considered as successfully completing the requirement. A recommendation from the Dean of Academic Services is also required.</P>

<P>GES 0113 Reading Enrichment Strategies 	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course addresses major areas of reading: reading speed, comprehension, and vocabulary. Strategies will be taught that will increase the student’s performance in each of the aforementioned concentrations. All students reflecting reading deficits in the ACT or SAT test scores are required to enroll in this class.</P>

<P>GES 1122 Strategies for Student Success 	2 Hours </P>

<P>This course aids incoming students in the process of acclimation to the University environment. The curriculum addresses student growth in knowledge, skills and attitudes in academic, social, personal, and spiritual areas. This course also provides an avenue for students to learn operational aspects of the University.</P>

<P>GES 1173 Computer Applications 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Develop and apply basic knowledge of microcomputers and applications: word processing, spreadsheet analysis, presentation graphics, and Internet research.</P>

<P>GES 2223 Data Analysis   	3 Hours</P>

<P>Introduction to quantitative analysis using electronic spreadsheet software. The study of formulas, functions, multiple worksheets, amortization tables, pivot tables, integration of databases, and statistical problems. </P>

<New_Style_Sheet>HISTORY</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>ARC 3113 Introduction to Archaeology	3 Hours</P>

<P>An overview of the history, practices, and methods of archaeology. Various forms of archaeology are studied with the goal of giving students a foundation for further study in the field.</P>

<P>ARC 3333 Archaeological Methodology	3 Hours</P>

<P>An in-depth study of archaeological techniques and methods. Students will gain knowledge about techniques, from the humanities and the natural sciences, used by archaeologists to locate, excavate, date, and interpret archaeological sites and artifacts. The potentials as well as the limitations of interpreting past societies are outlined.</P>

<P>ARC 4113 Pre-classical Mediterranean	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of the Mediterranean basin from the earliest societies to the dawn of the age of Classical Greece. Subjects that receive special emphasis include Minoan and Mycenaean civilizations, Egypt, Phoenicia, and other early societies and civilizations of the region. Coverage includes significant archaeological finds of the era. (Prerequisites: HIS 2123, HIS 4113)</P>

<P>ARC 4123 Ancient Ships and Harbors	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of seafaring in the ancient world. The development of boats and ships, nautical technology, the design and function of various significant ancient harbors, and the relationship between all of these subjects and archaeology receive detailed treatment in the course.</P>

<P>ARC 4133 Special Studies	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of selected topics significant to the study of archaeology. Course content and subject matter varies. May be repeated for credit as topics change.</P>

<P>ARC 4143 Archaeology Field Project	3 Hours</P>

<P>Hands-on work at an archaeological dig. Students will be able to put into practice archaeological techniques they have learned through coursework in the discipline. (Prerequisite: ARC 3113)</P>

<P/>

<P>GEO 2223 Geography 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A broad overview of various aspects of geography including major sections on landforms, bodies of water, political units, and cultural variations. Research tools and methodologies will be applied to the study of the state of Texas, the United States and the world. Includes field experience.</P>

<P>GOV 2213 National and State Government 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An analysis of national, state, and local government in the United States. Study is made of the Articles of Confederation, the Federal Constitution, the national party system, the departments of government, and other areas pertaining to national government. Histories of state governments and constitutions are examined, with special emphasis upon the Constitution of the State of Texas. The state legislature, the governor and state administration, the state court system, local government, local government problems, and other state and local government issues are analyzed. </P>

<P>GOV 2333 World Political Systems 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An overview of the evolution of political and economic systems and cultures. Students will be exposed to research strategies, sociological topics, and geographic information in order to develop a framework for understanding society. </P>

<P>HIS 1113 American History I 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey of the exploration of America, the founding and development of the English colonies, the War of Independence, the establishment of the U.S. Government, the War of 1812, westward expansion, states’ rights, slavery, the Civil War, and Reconstruction. America’s changing society and the interaction of individuals of differing cultural backgrounds in the early United States receive special attention.</P>

<P>HIS 1123 American History II 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Emphasis on post-Civil War conditions, settlement of the trans-Mississippi region, the struggle of Americans of various cultures and origins for a place in American society, the Populist and Progressive movements, the two world wars, and the Great Depression. The administrations of recent presidents from Harry Truman to the present administration, and the importance of the United States as a world power are included. </P>

<P>HIS 2113 Introduction to Economic History	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of economic practices in various societies throughout history. Special emphasis is placed on media of exchange, banking and lending, economic customs and theories, trade and commerce, agricultural and manufacturing production, use of resources, and government’s relation to production.</P>

<P>HIS 2123 World Civilizations I	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the major civilizations of Asia, Africa, Europe, and the Americas from the dawn of history to the seventeenth century. Emphasis is placed on the unique cultural, political, social, and technological contributions which each civilization made to the world of its time and the world of today, with a special focus on significant periods of cultural exchange between Eastern and Western civilization.</P>

<P>HIS 2133 World Civilizations II	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the major civilizations of Asia, Africa, Europe, and the Americas from the seventeenth century to the present day. Emphasis is placed on the unique cultural, political, social, and technological contributions which each civilization made to the world of its time and the world of today, with a special focus on the exchange and blending of diverse cultures and on the relationships among different peoples and nations.</P>

<P>HIS 2213 Western Civilization I 	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of the political, social, and cultural aspects of Western Civilization from its roots in the ancient empires of Mesopotamia and Egypt through the Roman period and medieval Europe. Special emphasis is placed on the forces and people that brought change and progress in the region. </P>

<P>HIS 2243 Western Civilization II 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey of the political, social, and cultural aspects of European and American civilization from the Age of Discovery until the present time. Nationalism, colonization, technology, revolutions, and industrialization receive special emphasis. </P>

<P>HIS 3113 American Early Federal and Jacksonian Eras 
	3 Hours</P>

<P>Political, constitutional, cultural, and economic developments in the U.S. during the formative period of the Republic, 1776-1849. Topics will include the Revolution, the Constitution, the Federalist administrations of Washington and Adams, the policies of Jefferson, the War of 1812, Jacksonian democracy, the Second Awakening, reform movements, westward expansion, and the growth of slavery. (Prerequisite: HIS 1113 or permission of professor)</P>

<P>HIS 3123 American Sectional Conflict and Gilded Age
	3 Hours</P>

<P>Political, cultural, and economic developments in the U.S. from 1849-1900. Topics will include abolition, slavery, sectionalism, the Civil War, Reconstruction, religious movements, the market revolution, party politics, women’s work and status, reform movements, and immigration. (Prerequisite: HIS 1113 or permission of professor)</P>

<P>HIS 3133 America Since 1900	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of American social, political, economic, cultural, and diplomatic history from the turn of the century to the present time. Topics that receive in-depth coverage include the major wars, the Great Depression, increasing pluralism in American society, the Cold War, the decade of the 1960’s, and the fall of communism. (Prerequisite: HIS 1123)</P>

<P>HIS 3313 Ancient Civilizations                                  3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the Egyptian, Israelite, Assyrian, Babylonian, Greek, and Roman civilizations along with other civilizations of importance found in the Middle East and Mediterranean regions. The course traces the history, religion, government, and society of each civilization. </P>

<P>HIS 3333 Advanced Topics in American History Through 1900	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the most important issues of American history from colonial times through 1900. Topics that receive major emphasis include interaction between Native Americans and European settlers, American political ideology, the frontier, manifest destiny, industrialization, slavery, reform movements, the Civil War and Reconstruction, and segregation. (Prerequisite: HIS 1113) </P>

<P>HIS 3343 Technology and Inventions 	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of technological advances throughout history and their effects on civilization and society. Major emphasis is placed on architectural, military, agricultural, and industrial innovations, with supplementary coverage of scientific and medical applications.</P>

<P>HIS 3413 Israel in the Ancient World                 	3 Hours</P>

<P>An in-depth study of the ancient nation of Israel from the calling of Abraham through the destruction of Jerusalem and the deportation of most of the Jewish population by the Romans in the first and second centuries A.D. The place of Israel in the larger context of the Near East during the period receives significant emphasis. (Prerequisite: HIS 2123)</P>

<P>HIS 4113 The Ancient Near East                         	  3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the Egyptian, Sumerian, Assyrian, Babylonian, Persian, and other civilizations found in the Near East in ancient times. The course traces elements of the religion, government, technology, and society of each civilization. (Prerequisite: HIS 2123 or professor approval)</P>

<P>HIS 4123 The Classical World	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of Greek and Roman civilizations to the fall of the Western Roman Empire. The course covers the Hellenistic period in the eastern Mediterranean, in addition to the purely classical societies of Greece and Rome. It traces elements of the religion, government, technology, philosophies, and society of each civilization. (Prerequisite: HIS 2123)</P>

<P>HIS 4133 Medieval Western History	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of European civilization from the fall of Rome to the Age of Discovery. The course focuses particular attention on Western and Central Europe and on the topics of feudalism, the Church, social classes, trade, agriculture, and warfare. (Prerequisite: HIS 2123)</P>

<P>HIS 4143 The Modern Western World	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of European and New World societies from the Age of Discovery to the present. The course covers religious and governmental changes, the Scientific Revolution and Enlightenment, major political revolutions, the age of Napoleon, colonialism, and the two world wars, as well as other aspects of society and culture. (Prerequisite: HIS 2133)</P>

<P>HIS 4413 Texas History	3 Hours</P>

<P>Texas history from the earliest Spanish explorations to the present time as established by the TEKS. Topics that receive special emphasis are multi-cultural settlements of Texas, the Revolution, the Civil War, the frontier, the Populist Era, and the growth of Texas industry. </P>

<P>HIS 4433 Western History Through Literature 	3 Hours</P>

<P>An interdisciplinary approach to the history of the Western world through representative literature. Various significant works of fiction and nonfiction from ancient through modern times are studied in their historical context. Major intellectual trends, political ideas, issues, and elements of social history receive primary consideration.</P>

<P>HIS 4443 Institutions and Customs of Western Society	
	3 Hours </P>

<P>A topical study of the origins and continued development of key institutions, ideas, and customs of the Western world. Such topics as the family, individual liberty, church-state relations, centralized versus decentralized government, education, and law are explored in detail to give the student an understanding of the roots of many facets of today’s world. </P>

<P>HIS 4913 Selected Topics	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of topics significant to understanding human history. Course content and subject vary; may be taken for up to six hours’ credit.	</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>HUMANITIES</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>HUM 1133 Introduction to Fine Arts 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Emphasis will be given to Texas Art and Music Standards. This </P>

<P>course will give an overview of the principles, elements, and techniques of the visual arts, architecture, music, photography and theater, as well as the terms and methods used to evaluate and appreciate works of art, music, drama, and other art forms. Also included will be an introduction to people who have made significant contributions in the history of the various art forms. The student will explore and apply comprehensive knowledge of music history, music evaluation, and musical perception and performance.</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>INTERCULTURAL STUDIES</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>ICS 2113 Islam in America	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the birth of American Islam, the early waves of Muslim immigration, and the evolution of American Islam toward orthodoxy. Emphasis is placed on the implications of Islam’s rapid growth in American society and the Christian’s responsibility to address this challenge.</P>

<P>ICS 2153 Spiritual Development	3 Hours</P>

<P>In this course, students will develop a biblical understanding of the principles and practices of spiritual growth and development. Biblical methods of sharing the Christian faith and mentoring spiritual maturity of believers will be introduced. Emphasis also will be placed on the biblical qualities necessary for those involved in planting and developing communities of believers.</P>

<P>ICS 2163 Strategic Opportunities for U.S. Service	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will explore four major areas of cross-cultural service in the United States: church planting (especially among immigrants), college ministries (especially among foreign students), intercultural ministries and the chaplaincy. A history of past successes and failures in these areas will be addressed. Contemporary strategies will be introduced.</P>

<P>ICS 3113 Holistic Relief and Development	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will present new methods for reaching out to hurting populations through various compassion ministries through both relief and development. Various strategies of establishing community involvement for long-term impact will be a major focus. Strong emphasis will be given to the scriptural precedents that point to the validity of this outreach and ways of accomplishing spiritual ends.</P>

<P>ICS 3123 Understanding the Spirit World	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course deals with the realms of spirits: The realm of God, the realm of angelic spirits - evil and good, and the realm of human spirits - un-regenerated and regenerated. Various syncretistic movements will be studied in order to understand the spirit world as comprehended by different immigration groups. (Replaced by ICS 3163)</P>

<P>ICS 3133 Women in Islam	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course examines the identity and role of women in historic and contemporary Islam as taught by the Qur’an, the traditions and throughout society in various Muslim contexts. The student will examine the current debates about gender issues in Islam. This course will examine the implications of the religious role and status of Muslim women, their social status, as well as their place in the family, their home and Muslim society.</P>

<P>ICS 3143 Transforming Conflict	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course focuses on sharpening peer-to-peer relationship skills. The course integrates research proven cognitive-behavioral skills with biblical practices to enhance interpersonal relationships. Special emphasis is placed on managing conflict in cross-cultural environments.</P>

<P>ICS 3163 Understanding the Spirit World	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course deals with the realms of spirits as depicted in Scripture: the realm of God, the realm of angelic spirits--evil and good, and the realm of human spirits--un-regenerated and regenerated. The course focuses on discovering the source of spiritual oppression in any given conflict. (Prerequisite: BIB 1223)</P>

<P>ICS 3173 Personal Adjustment for Cross-Cultural Service</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course assists the students to assess their personal characteristics which are critical to cross-cultural adjustment. Then, various culture-clusters are examined to discover how their constituents generally respond in situations revolving around such cultural dynamics as time/event, crisis/non-crisis, task/personal relationship, etc. Finally, the students self-prescribe the personal changes they would need to make to effectively serve in a given cultural setting.</P>

<P>ICS 3183 Fundraising and Stewardship	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the key aspects of personal and non-profit resource management specifically for workers in intercultural settings. The course will introduce the student to fundraising, donor management and financial reporting, with an emphasis on required forms and reporting for the Assemblies of God system. The course will also introduce basic principles of financial ethics, budgeting, and record keeping.</P>

<P>ICS 3193 Intercultural Communication	3 Hours</P>

<P>The course examines the basic principles of cross-cultural communication including a focus on cultural contexts and potential communication barriers and the potential implications of these issues for Christian witness. (Prerequisite: BIB 1223)</P>

<P>ICS 3223 Introduction to Islam	3 Hours</P>

<P>Introduction to Islam will provide an overview of Islam, including its historical background, development, spread, its diversity and why it has such worldwide appeal. We will examine the main beliefs and practices of Muslims, noting similarities and crucial differences with Christianity in order to help Christian workers recognize both difficulties in evangelizing Muslims as well as the great opportunities. Special attention will be given to develop Christ-like attitudes and approaches for effective ministry to Muslims. (Prerequisite: BIB 1223) (Same as THE 3223)</P>

<P>ICS 3331 Seminar 	1 Hour </P>

<P>A seminar providing opportunity to bring to the campus highly qualified persons with expertise in different phases of missions and cross-cultural evangelism. The experience and insights of the guest lecturers will serve as valuable resources for prospective ministers in missions and cross-cultural evangelism. (Maximum of three seminars may be counted toward graduation.) </P>

<P>ICS 3363 World Religions 	3 Hours </P>

<P> This course seeks to equip the student with necessary knowledge to intelligently approach those of the non-Christian religions of the world. It views the tenets of the major religious systems comparatively. Religions studied include Pre-historic and tribal religions, Hinduism, Jainism, Sikhism, Buddhism, religions of East Asia, Zoroastrianism, Judaism, Christianity, and Islam. (Same as THE 3363)</P>

<P>ICS 3912 Intercultural Service Internship Block	12 Hours</P>

<P>Students will participate in a 12-week cross-cultural field internship experience. They will be assigned to a qualified mentor and actively participate in supervised intercultural service, community development, and other specializations depending on trip location. Students will complete assignments designed to demonstrate growth in intercultural understanding, knowledge of the principles and practices of intercultural service, understanding the distinct issues in intercultural leadership development and the ability to complete guided field research. A student must make application to and be approved by the Missions Department Committee before registering for this block. Students should apply for their internship as soon as they have completed 45 hours of study. (Prerequisite: BIB 1223)</P>

<P>ICS 3923 Cross-Cultural Field Seminar	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is designed for students from majors other than Intercultural Studies. Students will participate in a cross-cultural field experience. They will be assigned to a qualified mentor and actively participate in supervised intercultural service, community development, and other specializations depending on trip location. Students must apply for their Field Seminar at least 6 months in advance and be approved by the Missions Department committee to be eligible for credit. (Prerequisite: CMN 1223)(Replaced by REL 3133)</P>

<P>ICS 4123 Cults, Occults and Folk Religions	3 Hours</P>

<P>These studies involve practical research and materials review as to the content and form of major “Christian” cults. The focus of the course is upon the development of mental and spiritual sensitivity to these teachings and practices when engaging in cross-cultural ministry. (Same as THE 4123)</P>

<P>ICS 4143 Priorities for Intercultural Service	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course examines the various paradigms of intercultural services with the goal of helping students develop a more integrated framework that embraces what are often seen as competing priorities: holistic service versus spiritual development. Special emphasis is given to the development of strategies rooted in Scripture, proven principles from history and cultural analysis. Special attention will be given to the spiritual needs of frontier contexts. Assemblies of God efforts to expand the global community of faith will be analyzed. (Prerequisite: BIB 1223)</P>

<P>ICS 4153 Strategies for Multiethnic Service	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will address the historical background of American immigration. Attention will be given to present day demographic patterns and obstacles created by tradition, prejudice and lack of knowledge. Students will examine strategies being successfully employed in multiethnic churches in the U.S. (Prerequisite: BIB 1223)</P>

<P>ICS 4173 Cultural Anthropology	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is designed to study the significant characteristics of cultural diversity that would affect the anticipated outcomes of cross-cultural service. General principles of cultural anthropology will be studied in the light of distinct ethnic cultures in the USA and abroad. Special emphasis will be given to communicating cross-culturally. (Prerequisite: BIB 1223)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>JOURNALISM</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>JOU 1131 Yearbook 	1 Hour </P>

<P>A course designed for the publication of the Southwesterner, the University yearbook. Students who elect this course serve as staff members of the Southwesterner and meet regularly for instruction and work assignments. The course may be repeated for a maximum of three hours credit. </P>

<P>JOU 1141 The Image	1 Hour</P>

<P>This course is designed to provide students with a strong emphasis on editing, layout, and design from an aesthetic perspective, to display quality literature, artwork, and photography in an e-journal format that is visually pleasing where every aspect speaks of artistic unity, or intentionality. The course will provide much practical experience that will benefit students in a number of professions. </P>

<P>JOU 1151 Campus Newspaper 	1 Hour </P>

<P>A course designed for the publication of The Lion’s Roar, the University newspaper. Students who elect this course serve as staff members of The Lion’s Roar and meet regularly for instruction and work assignments. The course may be repeated for a maximum of three hours credit.</P>

<P>JOU 3363 Creative Writing in Middle/Secondary	3 Hours</P>

<P>A course designed to develop writers by instilling a habit of close reading in any genre to discover how effective writers structure and develop their works. Includes emphasis on the importance of voice in writing.  (Prerequisites: ENG 1113, ENG 1123. Same as ENG 3363)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>KINESIOLOGY</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>KIN 2123 Human Anatomy and Physiology I	3 Hours</P>

<P>Anatomy and Physiology I is the first part of a two course sequence.  This course covers fundamental principles of body systems and their functions.  Topics include basic chemistry, cells, tissues and organs of the following systems: integumentary, skeletal, muscular, nervous and special senses. Relationships among systems and regulation of physiological functions involved in maintaining homeostasis will be emphasized. Laboratory work includes dissection of preserved specimens, microscopic study, examining models, and physiological and computer simulations experiments. (Same as BIO 2123)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>LINGUISTICS</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>LNG 3113 Topics in Linguistics	3 Hours</P>

<P>An intensive study of current topics in linguistics research and cross cultural communication.  (Prerequisites: ENG 3413, ENG 3423)</P>

<P>LNG 3123 Morphology and Syntax	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of syntactic and morphological patterns as related to language use. This course will primarily focus on prevalent patterns in English with an additional focus on transformational grammar and universal grammatical patterns. (Prerequisite: ENG 3413)</P>

<P>LNG 4113 Sociolinguistics	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of speech acts, code switching, bilingualism, and conversation analysis will be used to analyze language in society. The course will address linguistic variation  in the context of gender, ethnicity, social class, geography, and age.  (Prerequisites: ENG 3413, ENG 3423)</P>

<P>LNG 4123 Grammar and Morphology	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of universal grammatical patterns and morphological principles. This course will introduce principles of transformational grammar including structure and distribution of words, phrases, clauses, sentences, and larger units. (Prerequisites: ENG 3413, ENG 3423)(Replaced by LNG 3123)</P>

<P>LNG 4133 Cross-cultural Communications and the EFL 	                  Classroom  	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of basic principles of cross-cultural communication and conflict resolution with tools for applying English language acquisition pedagogy in a homogenous foreign environment. (Prerequisite: ENG 3283 or permission from advisor)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>MATHEMATICS</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>MTH 0013 Developmental Mathematics 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A developmental study of decimals, fractions, ratios and proportions, percents, signed numbers, polynomial operations and equations. Placement is determined by evaluation of ACT and Math Placement Exam scores. This course does not fulfill the requirement for Math in the core curriculum. (Replaced by MTH 0043)</P>

<P>MTH 0023 Beginning Algebra 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A fundamental study of real numbers, variable expressions, solving equations and inequalities, polynomials, factoring and algebraic fractions. Placement is determined by evaluation of ACT and Math Placement Exam scores or successful completion </P>

<P>of MTH 0013. This course does not fulfill the requirement for Math in the core curriculum. </P>

<P>MTH 0033 Intermediate Algebra 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the real number system, exponents and polynomials, equations, equation of lines, graphing and quadratic equations. This course does not fulfill the Math requirement in the core curriculum. (Prerequisite: Successful completion of MTH 0023 or placement determined by one year of high school algebra and placement determined by evaluation of ACT and Math Placement Exam scores.)</P>

<P>MTH 0043 Developmental Math Sequence	3 Hours </P>

<P>The Developmental Math Sequence course is designed to prepare students to succeed in college level math and can be repeated for credit until the prerequisite skills needed for general education math courses have been mastered. Initial placement is determined by ACT or SAT scores. This course does not fulfill the requirement for mathematics in the core curriculum.</P>

<P>MTH 1113 College Mathematics 	3 Hours </P>

<P>The study of modern concepts including elementary logic, set notation, number systems, systems of linear equations, quadratic equations, graphing, inequalities, progressions and elements of probability. (Prerequisite: Successful completion of MTH 0023 or placement determined by evaluation of ACT and Math Placement Exam scores.) </P>

<P>MTH 1123 College Algebra 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A thorough study of the binomial theorem, progressions, exponents, quadratic equations, and ratio and proportion. The theory and use of logarithms are included. (Prerequisite: Successful completion of MTH 0043 or  placement determined by evaluation of ACT and Math Placement Exam scores.)</P>

<P>MTH 2211 Calculus I Lab 	1 Hour </P>

<P>The weekly lab meetings are an integral part of Calculus I (MTH 2213). These labs are designed to provide hands-on activities that will further the understanding of calculus and to provide an introduction to and instruction in the use of modern computer software. (Prerequisite: Enrollment in MTH 2213)</P>

<P>MTH 2213 Calculus I 	3 Hours </P>

<P>The first semester of Calculus: limits, continuity, derivatives, rules of differentiation, applications of differentiation optimization, L’Hopital’s Rule, curve sketching, integration, the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus. This course is taken in tandem with lab course MTH 2211. (Prerequisite: ACT Math score of 21 or permission of Program Coordinator based on SAGU placement test.)</P>

<P>MTH 2221 Calculus II Lab 	1 Hour</P>

<P>The weekly lab meetings are an integral part of Calculus II (MTH 2223). These labs are designed to provide hands-on activities that will further the understanding of calculus and to provide an introduction to and instruction in the use of modern computer software. (Prerequisite: Enrollment in MTH 2223)</P>

<P>MTH 2223 Calculus II 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Applications of integration, techniques of integration, parametric equations, polar coordinates, sequences, series vectors, dot product, cross product, planes and quadric surfaces. This course will be taken in tandem with MTH 2221. (Prerequisite: MTH 2213)</P>

<P>MTH 2313 Elementary Analysis	3 Hours
Develops an understanding of topics needed before calculus. Topics include an introduction to logarithmic functions, vectors, trigonometric form of a complex number, matrices, sequences and series, probability, conics, parametric equations, and polar equations. (Prerequisites: MTH 1123 with C or higher or equivalent scores on SAT/ACT or equivalent transfer courses)</P>

<P>MTH 3313 Calculus III 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Partial differentiation, multiple integrals (with applications), line integrals, Green’s Theorem, surface integrals, Stokes’ Theorem, divergence theorem. (Prerequisite: MTH 2223)</P>

<P>MTH 3323 Introduction to Proofs and Discrete Mathematics</P>

<P>	3 Hours </P>

<P>An introduction to methods of mathematical proof, formal logic, functions, induction, and set theory.</P>

<P>MTH 3333 Introduction to Linear Algebra 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An introduction to the fundamentals of linear algebra, including Gaussian elimination, solution of systems of linear equations, finite dimensional vector spaces, matrices, and determinants. The main emphasis of the course is on applications and computational methods, with a view to facilitate the use of linear algebra in business, computer science, and the natural and social sciences.</P>

<P>MTH 3343 Linear Algebra 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of vector spaces, linear transformations, invariance, and the theory of matrices including eigenvalues and eigenvectors.</P>

<P>MTH 3413 Statistics	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of basic statistical methods of distributions, central tendency, variability, correlation, sampling techniques, and hypothesis testing. (Prerequisite: Successful completion of MTH 1123. Same as BUS 3413)</P>

<P>MTH 4113 Abstract Algebra I	3 Hours </P>

<P>Groups including Lagrange’s Theorem, Cauchy’s Theorem, the Isomorphism theorems, and symmetric groups. (Prerequisite: MTH 3343)</P>

<P>MTH 4123 Real Analysis I 	3 Hours </P>

<P>The study of the properties of the real number line and the theory of functions of a real variable including limits, sequences, continuity, derivatives, and Riemann integration. (Prerequisite: MTH 3313)</P>

<P>MTH 4133 Numerical Methods 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An introduction to numerical methods, both the mathematical methods for solving equations numerically and the programming of these methods on computers. Topics include interval-halving, Newton’s and Bairstow’s methods for a single equation; Gaussian elimination and Gram-Schmidt orthogonalization for solving systems of linear equations; interpolating polynomials; and methods of numerical differentiation and integration. TI-83/84 Plus graphing calculator required. (Prerequisite: Upper level standing)</P>

<P>MTH 4153 Modern Geometry 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Finite geometries, transformations, motion of the Euclidean plane and 3-space, similarity transformations, convexity, and other topics.  (Prerequisites: C or better in MTH 3343)</P>

<P>MTH 4163 Abstract Algebra II	3 Hours </P>

<P>Ring theory up to and including prime and maximal ideals; unique factorization domains, and classification of groups of small order; introduction to field theory and the fields Q, R, and C. (Prerequisite: MTH 4113)convexity, and other topics.</P>

<P/>

<P>MTH 4163 Problem Solving	3 Hours</P>

<P>Strategies of problem solving; methods for teaching and applying different strategies; assessment of problem solving skills. (Prerequisite: Upper level standing)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>MEDIA</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>MED 2123 Introduction to Media Production	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of the three most essential elements of video media production: videography, lighting, and editing. As an introduction to the entire media production process, this course provides the necessary foundation for visual storytelling in the 21st century. This course requires a technology fee.</P>

<P>MED 2153 Broadcast Production I	3 Hours</P>

<P>Provides exposure to fundamental elements of broadcast production for both in-studio and field or remote on-location events. Emphasis is on theoretical approaches to broadcast components such as camera operation, audio recording and synchronization, technical directing, producing, and floor directing. The course provides a basis for the Broadcast Production II course. This course requires a technology fee. (Prerequisite: MED 2123; COM 2133 to be taken concurrently with MED 2153)</P>

<P>MED 2163 Broadcast Production II	3 Hours</P>

<P>Provides an in-depth exposure to broadcast production elements. Practical assignments in camera operation, audio, technical directing, producing, and floor directing provide a basis for skill development for both studio and remote broadcasting productions. Builds on theoretical learning obtained in the Broadcast Production I course. This course requires a technology fee. (Prerequisites: MED 2123, MED 2153)</P>

<P>MED 2173 Audio Production and Aesthetics I	3 Hours</P>

<P>The course is a survey of various types of microphones and techniques for proper vocal and instrument recording. Creating special effects, audio filters and other post-production techniques are examined with practical assignments and class exercises. Special attention is given to mixing and mastering digital audio tracks on computer software and builds on the knowledge and skills required in prerequisite courses. (Prerequisite: Approval of the instructor)</P>

<P/>

<P>MED 3143 Cinematic Pre-production	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is designed to provide the student with an understanding and practice of making a film. Coursework will engage students in various pre-production exercises preparing for the post-production stages of film-making. Students will be assigned a crew position for the ensuing summer student film project and are part of the pre-production meetings pertaining to specific crew responsibilities. (Prerequisite: MED 2123 which may be taken concurrently.)</P>

<P>MED 3153 Short Film Principle Photography	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is designed for the practical application with the ensuing summer student film project. Students are part of the production meetings pertaining to specific crew responsibilities engaging the students in short film’s principle photography and offered as a summer course. The students are required to be available for a rigid and fluid schedule with no other responsibilities of work or classes for a block of time, generally two to three weeks. May be repeated. (Prerequisites: MED 2123, MED 3143)</P>

<P>MED 3163 Electronic Field Production	3 Hours</P>

<P>An in-depth study of video production as applied to single-camera cinematography. The course examines the key components of continuity, composition, lenses, lighting, and field audio. In addition, the course provides more development of the post-production editing process with practical assignments and class exercises. This course requires a technology fee. (Prerequisites: COM 2143, MED 2123, MED 2153)</P>

<P>MED 3283 Worship Technologies	3 Hours
Principles and techniques of live audio/video/lighting production for use in the local church. (Prerequisite: MED 2173)</P>

<P>MED 3373 Audio Production and Aesthetics	3 Hours</P>

<P>The course is a survey of various types of microphones and techniques for proper vocal and instrument recording. Creating special effects, audio filters and other post-production techniques are examined with practical assignments and class exercises. Special attention is given to mixing and mastering digital audio tracks on computer software and builds on the knowledge and skills acquired in prerequisite courses. (Prerequisites: Approval of the instructor.) (Replaced by MED 2173)</P>

<P>MED 3413 Audio Production and Aesthetics II	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of various techniques for sound design for visual media, such as film and television. Sound effects, foley, voice-overs, automated dialogue replacement, and advanced production techniques are examined with practical assignments and class exercises. Special attention is given to mixing and mastering digital audio tracks on Digital Audio Workstations and builds on the knowledge and skills acquired in prerequisite courses. Enrollment requires approval of the instructor. (Prerequisite: MED 2173)</P>

<P>MED 4123 Audio Production and Aesthetics II	3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of various techniques for sound design for visual media, such as film and television. Sound effects, foley, voice-overs, automated dialogue replacement, and advanced production techniques are examined with practical assignments and class exercises. Special attention is given to mixing and mastering digital audio tracks on Digital Audio Workstations and builds on the knowledge and skills acquired in prerequisite courses. Enrollment requires approval of the instructor. (Replaced by MED 3413)</P>

<P>MED 4233 Post Production and Delivery	3 Hours</P>

<P>Students will work in a team environment to complete the required elements of the post-production process for an official SAGU Cinema product. This may include some or all of the following: assembly of raw footage into a workable rough cut, final visual editing, dialogue replacements, sound foley, music bed/score insertions, special effects, final audio mixing, and master output to a variety of deliverable formats. Typical assignments will be either a summer film project or a Mission TEN documentary, but may also include additional projects as assigned by instructor. Students should anticipate exposure to multiple software platforms such as Final Cut, Premiere, After Effects, Pro Tools and other applications as needed. (Prerequisite: Instructor approval)</P>

<P>MED 4243 Principles of Film Industry	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course explores the industry of filmmaking from a business perspective. Topics of study include solutions for monetizing cinematic productions through both traditional and emerging methods of distribution and marketing. Case studies from previously produced films will also survey aspects of fundraising and budgeting. (Prerequisite: MED 2123)</P>

<P>MED 4413 Advanced Digital Editing	3 Hours</P>

<P>Builds on the knowledge and skills acquired in pre-requisite courses. Emphasis is placed on exploring advanced techniques and artistic decisions in the video editing process. These areas of discipline may include certain aspects of: history of editing, contemporary methods of editing, dialogue editing, audio mixing, motion graphics, special effects, color correcting, collaborative re-editing, and master deliverables. This course requires a technology fee. (Prerequisites: COM 2143, MED 2123, MED 3163)</P>

<P>MED 4583 Media Internship    	3 Hours</P>

<P>Students may seek a position which relates to their major with a cooperating business in the communication industry. Students are required to work 40 hours for each academic credit hour received. A weekly report to the supervising professor is required.  May be repeated for up to six units. (Prerequisite: Approval of the department chair.)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>MUSIC</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>MAP 1000 Recital Attendance 	0 Hours </P>

<P>Required of all music majors each semester of full-time enrollment. From initial enrollment, students will be required to attend a minimum of seventy percent of the on-campus recitals. (A minimum of six semesters of recital attendance is required for graduation with a degree in music.) Grading will be on a Pass/No Pass basis. </P>

<P>MAP Applied Music 	1 or 2 Hours </P>

<P>Private music instruction. Applied lessons will emphasize technique, sight reading and repertoire. Each credit involves a 30-minute private lesson and a minimum of 5 hours of practice each week. Students will continue to register for lower-level study until the completion of the Proficiency Examinations which, if passed, will permit the student to register for upper level study.</P>

<New_Style_Sheet_2>MUSIC MAJORS</New_Style_Sheet_2>

<P>Lower Level</P>

<P>MAP 1111 or 1112 Piano</P>

<P>MAP 1121 or 1122 Viola </P>

<P>MAP 1211 or 1212 Voice </P>

<P>MAP 1311 or 1312 Flute </P>

<P>MAP 1321 or 1322 Clarinet </P>

<P>MAP 1331 or 1332 Saxophone </P>

<P>MAP 1341 or 1342 French Horn</P>

<P>MAP 1351 or 1352 Trumpet</P>

<P>MAP 1361 or 1362 Trombone</P>

<P>MAP 1371 or 1372 Baritone</P>

<P>MAP 1381 or 1382 Percussion</P>

<P>MAP 1391 or 1392 Violin</P>

<P>MAP 1611 or 1612 Cello</P>

<P>MAP 1711 or 1712 Guitar</P>

<P>MAP 1811 or 1812 Bass Guitar</P>

<P>Upper Level</P>

<P>MAP 3111 or 3112 Piano</P>

<P>MAP 3121 or 3122 Viola </P>

<P>MAP 3211 or 3212 Voice</P>

<P>MAP 3221 or 3222 Jazz Improvisation </P>

<P>MAP 3311 or 3312 Flute </P>

<P>MAP 3321 or 3322 Clarinet </P>

<P>MAP 3331 or 3332 Saxophone </P>

<P>MAP 3341 or 3342 French Horn </P>

<P>MAP 3351 or 3352 Trumpet </P>

<P>MAP 3361 or 3362 Trombone </P>

<P>MAP 3371 or 3372 Baritone</P>

<P>MAP 3381 or 3382 Percussion</P>

<P>MAP 3391 or 3392 Violin</P>

<P>MAP 3611 or 3612 Cello</P>

<P>MAP 3711 or 3712 Guitar</P>

<P>MAP 3811 or 3812 Bass Guitar</P>

<P>Students taking applied music for non-music majors will not be required to meet the recital attendance requirement for music majors. Course repertoire will be left to the discretion of the individual applied instructor and the student. All lessons will include basic technique. </P>

<New_Style_Sheet_2>NON-MUSIC MAJORS</New_Style_Sheet_2>

<P>Lower Level</P>

<P>MAP 1021 or 1022 Clarinet</P>

<P>MAP 1031 or 1032 Saxophone</P>

<P>MAP 1041 or 1042 French Horn</P>

<P>MAP 1051 or 1052 Trumpet </P>

<P>MAP 1061 or 1062 Trombone</P>

<P>MAP 1071 or 1072 Baritone </P>

<P>MAP 1081 or 1082 Percussion</P>

<P>MAP 1091 or 1092 Violin </P>

<P>MAP 1101 or 1102 Piano </P>

<P>MAP 1201 or 1202 Voice </P>

<P>MAP 1301 or 1302 Flute</P>

<P>MAP 1601 or 1602 Cello </P>

<P>MAP 1701 or 1702 Guitar </P>

<P>MAP 1801 or 1802 Bass Guitar</P>

<P>MAP 1901 or 1902 Viola</P>

<P>MAP 2000 Piano Proficiency 	0 Hours </P>

<P>All music majors are required to pass the Piano Proficiency Exam as a graduation requirement. Students should attempt this exam at the end of the sophomore year. </P>

<P>MAP 2100 Voice Proficiency 	0 Hours </P>

<P>All music majors declaring voice as their primary applied area  and all music education majors are required to pass the Voice Proficiency Exam as a graduation requirement. Students should attempt this exam at the end of the sophomore year. </P>

<P>MAP 2200 Instrumental Proficiency	0 Hours</P>

<P>All music majors declaring instrumental as their primary applied area are required to pass the Instrumental Proficiency Exam as a graduation requirement. Students should attempt this exam at the end of the sophomore year.</P>

<P>MAP 3200 Junior Recital	0 Hours</P>

<P>Performance of at least 30 minutes of music, including classical music literature from selected periods of music history and Christian or gospel music repertoire for music performance majors; lead a minimum of 30 minute music worship session, incorporating varied hymns and contemporary worship selections for music ministries majors. (Prerequisite: Students must have passed proficiency requirements for their primary performance area before the recital can be performed - MAP 2000 for piano majors; MAP 2100 for vocal majors; MAP 2200 for instrumental majors. Required of all music performance and music ministries majors.)</P>

<P>MAP 4000 Senior Recital 	0 Hours </P>

<P>Performance of at least one hour of music, including classical music literature from all periods of music history and Christian or gospel music repertoire. (Prerequisites: Students must have completed all Music Theory requirements and passed all proficiency requirements for their primary performance area before the recital can be performed; senior, upper-division standing in major applied area and departmental approval. Required for all performance majors.) (Replaced by MAP 4010)</P>

<P>MAP 4010 Senior Recital	0 Hours</P>

<P>Performance of at least one hour of music, including classical music literature from all periods of music history and Christian or gospel music repertoire for music performance and music education majors; leading at least a one hour music worship session, incorporating varied hymns and contemporary worship selections for music ministry majors. (Prerequisites: Students must have completed all required music courses [or be enrolled in the final required courses] and passed all proficiency requirements before the recital can be performed; Senior, upper-division standing in major applied area and department approval.)</P>

<P>MUE 1121 Band 	1 Hour </P>

<P>An instrumental group open to students from all departments for ministry in campus chapel services and special events, using instrumental arrangements from a broad spectrum of musical literature. </P>

<P>MUE 1131 Jazz Ensemble 	1 Hour </P>

<P>Patterned after both contemporary big band and the large popular groups of the 1930s and 1940s, this group devotes itself to the performance of jazz literature of the past and present as well as sacred jazz literature. Open to all University students by audition. There will be public concerts each semester as well as performance for Chapel. </P>

<P>MUE 1161 Choir 	1 Hour </P>

<P>A choir open to students from all departments for ministry in chapel services, special events and minimal travel for representation and promotion of SAGU. This choral group prepares a repertoire giving the students an extensive range of music literature experience.</P>

<P>MUE 1181 Chorale 	1 Hour </P>

<P>A choral ensemble open to students from all departments, which will give a limited number of on-campus concerts and local performances. The ensemble will perform a cappella and accompanied selections from all the major periods of music history and a cappella arrangements of contemporary gospel music. Admission by audition. </P>

<P>MUE 1190 Music Ensemble	0 Hour
An instrumental or vocal group open to students from all departments for ministry in campus chapel services and special events, using instrumental and vocal arrangements from a broad spectrum of musical literature.</P>

<P>MUE 1221 String Ensemble 	1 Hour </P>

<P>Small instrumental ensemble open to all students from all departments for ministry in campus chapel services and special events, using literature written for violin, viola, cello and string bass in a variety of genres including all musical periods as well as sacred selections. (Replaced by MUE 1241)</P>

<P>MUE 1231 Ministry Ensemble	1 Hour</P>

<P>An ensemble open to students from all departments for ministry in chapel services, special events and the representation and promotion of SAGU in churches throughout the SAGU region.</P>

<P>MUE 1241 Chamber Ensemble	1 Hour</P>

<P>Small instrument ensemble open to all students from all departments for ministry in campus chapel services and special events, using literature written for specified instrumentation in a variety of genres including all musical periods as well as sacred selections.</P>

<P>MUE 1251 Chapel Worship	1 Hour</P>

<P>Chapel Worship is open to students from all departments for ministry in chapel service and special events. Students will be exposed to a broad repertoire that will help them minister in a variety of settings.</P>

<P>MUE 1311 Piano Ensemble	1 Hour</P>

<P>A piano ensemble open to students from all departments. The ensemble will perform piano works written for four or more hands in a variety of genres and styles. There will be on- and off-campus performances each semester. Admissions by audition.</P>

<P>MUS 0012 Basic Musicianship I 	2 Hours </P>

<P>The study of fundamentals in elementary theory of music, note reading, rhythm, letter names, bass clef, and treble clef. Development of aural skills with sight-singing and ear-training. (Required of all students whose Theory Placement Assessment score indicates a need for rudimentary studies.) </P>

<P>MUS 0022 Basic Musicianship II 	2 Hours </P>

<P>The study of fundamentals in elementary theory of music,  rhythm, major scales, minor scales, part writing, intervals, chords, and harmonies. Further development of aural skills with sight-singing and ear training. (Required of all students whose Theory Placement Assessment score indicates a need for rudimentary studies.)</P>

<P>MUS 0051 Class Voice 	1 Hour </P>

<P>Group music instruction. Class Voice will emphasize basic vocal technique, posture, breathing, tone color, note and rhythm reading, and basic performance techniques.  (Course is to be repeated until proficiency is attained. Required of all music majors whose Vocal Placement Assessment score indicates a need for rudimentary studies.)</P>

<P>MUS 1114 Music Theory I 	4 Hours </P>

<P>Basic musical elements including pitch notation, rhythmic notation, key signatures, meter signatures, intervals, scales, chords, cadences, inversions, and part writing. Singing in treble and bass clefs; introduction to alto and tenor clefs. Aural study of intervals; study of beats and divisions of beats; and melodies having harmonic backgrounds of principal chords. These elements are learned through hearing, singing, and keyboard activities, while developing skills in reading and writing simple melodies. (Prerequisite: Pass Music Theory Placement Assessment)</P>

<P>MUS 1124 Music Theory II 	4 Hours </P>

<P>Continuation of MUS 1114 using similar activities to develop skills in four-part diatonic harmony, non-harmonic tones, seventh chords, binary and ternary forms, secondary dominants, and modulation. Aural study of intervals and melodies with diatonic harmonic backgrounds and further study of the subdivision of beats. (Prerequisite: MUS 1114)</P>

<P>MUS 1211 Class Piano I	1 Hour
Group music instruction. Class Piano will emphasize basic piano instruction, note reading, pedaling, major scales, intervals, simple improvisation, and basic accompaniment patterns. This course sequence is designed for those students who are not piano majors to attain proficiency at the piano. Required of all music majors with a specialization other than piano, whose Piano Placement Assessment score indicates a need for rudimentary studies.</P>

<P>MUS 1311 Class Piano II	1 Hour
Group music instruction. Continuation of the skills mastered in MUS 1211 including major scales, minor scales, arpeggios, cadential patterns, intervals, sight-reading, simple improvisation, transposition, harmonization, and basic accompaniment patterns. This course sequence is designed for non-piano majors to attain proficiency at the piano. (Prerequisite: MUS 1211 or approval of the instructor)</P>

<P>MUS 1323 World Music	3 Hours
A study of musical traditions from differing world cultures focusing on development, outlook, theory, and practice of contemporary ethnomusicology. Emphasis will be placed on analysis of specific genres, common and opposing trends in musical styles, and the effects of ethnocentric music in the local church.</P>

<P>MUS 2212 Diction for Singers 	2 Hours </P>

<P>Diction and pronunciation skills for singing. Introduction to phonetic analysis in English, Italian, German, and French. No attempt will be made to develop grammar or vocabulary skills. </P>

<P>MUS 2214 Music Theory III 	4 Hours </P>

<P>Continuation of MUS 1124 using similar activities to further develop skills in part writing and analytical skills through study of harmonic sequence, secondary dominants, modulations, sevenths, mode mixture. Neapolitan chords, augmented sixth chords, and standard formal structures. Aural skills such as syncopation (simple and compound), melodic and harmonic dictation with intervals in contexts other than tonic and dominant, and inversions of major, minor, diminished and seventh chords will be studied. (Prerequisite: MUS 1124) </P>

<P>MUS 2224 Music Theory IV 	4 Hours </P>

<P>Continuation of MUS 2214 using similar activities to study simple to complex harmonic patterns, as well as late 19th century and impressionistic theoretical concepts. Studies will also include 9th, 11th, and 13th chords with complex harmonic progressions. Compositional techniques of the 20th century will be studied as well. (Prerequisite: MUS 2214) </P>

<P>MUS 2231 Accompanying 	1 Hour </P>

<P>Techniques of piano accompanying. Review of sight-reading skills with repertoire from simple art songs. Assignment to accompany applied music lessons. Three semesters required for piano major/concentration. (Prerequisite: approval of the piano faculty) </P>

<P>MUS 2322 Introduction to Music Composition	2 Hours</P>

<P>This course is designed to provide opportunity for developing basic skills in the manipulation of musical materials in tonal, modal and post-tonal contexts. Emphasis is placed on composition for piano and solo voice/instrument with piano accompaniment. Students will have the opportunity to present a work at a Composition Recital. (Prerequisite: MUS 1114, MUS 1124)</P>

<P>MUS 2411 Class Piano III	1 Hour
Group music instruction. Continuation of the skills mastered in Class Piano I and Class Piano II including major scales, minor scales, arpeggios, cadential patterns, sight-reading, basic improvisation, transposition, harmonization, and introduction to early intermediate piano repertoire. This course sequence is designed for non-piano majors to attain proficiency at the piano. (Prerequisites: MUS 1311 or approval of the instructor) </P>

<P>MUS 2421  Class Piano IV	1 Hour
Group music instruction. Continuation of the skills mastered in Class Piano III including major scales, minor scales, arpeggios, cadential patterns, sight-reading, basic improvisation, transposition, harmonization, and introduction to early intermediate piano repertoire. This course sequence is designed for non-piano majors to attain proficiency at the piano. (Prerequisites: MUS 2411 or approval of the instructor)</P>

<P>MUS 3113 Biblical Perspective of Music and Worship	3 Hours</P>

<P>Study of the role of music in worship. Theological implications, style of music, qualifications for worship leadership, and the spiritual dynamics of worship are explored.</P>

<P>MUS 3121 Brass Techniques 	1 Hour </P>

<P>One hour techniques courses in brass. Rehearsal objectives, instrumental techniques and materials specific to beginning band and orchestra; rehearsal management and organization; visual and aural diagnostic skills for teaching performance fundamentals.</P>

<P>MUS 3131 Percussion Techniques 	1 Hour </P>

<P>One hour techniques courses in percussion. Rehearsal objectives, instrumental techniques and materials specific to beginning band and orchestra; rehearsal management and organization; visual and aural diagnostic skills for teaching performance fundamentals.</P>

<P>MUS 3141 Strings Techniques 	1 Hour </P>

<P>One hour techniques courses in strings. Rehearsal objectives, instrumental techniques and materials specific to beginning band and orchestra; rehearsal management and organization; visual and aural diagnostic skills for teaching performance fundamentals.</P>

<P>MUS 3151 Woodwinds Techniques 	1 Hour </P>

<P>One hour techniques courses in woodwinds. Rehearsal objectives, instrumental techniques and materials specific to beginning band and orchestra; rehearsal management and organization; visual and aural diagnostic skills for teaching performance fundamentals.</P>

<P>MUS 3312 Choral Conducting 	2 Hours </P>

<P>Conducting gestures, score analysis, rehearsal procedures for choirs, and development of choral ensembles. (Prerequisite: MUS 1124)</P>

<P>MUS 3322 Instrumental Conducting 	2 Hours </P>

<P>Specific conducting techniques, rehearsal and performance procedures, and development of musical interpretation. Emphasis will be placed upon instrumental music. (Prerequisite: MUS 1124)</P>

<P>MUS 3331 Music Seminar 	1 Hour </P>

<P>The seminar shall bring to the campus eminent persons with experience in different phases of music. They shall function as resource persons whose experience and insights provide exposure for prospective Music majors. (Maximum of three music seminars may be counted toward graduation.) Grading will be on a Credit/No Credit basis. </P>

<P>MUS 3332 Song Writing 	2 Hours </P>

<P>Introduction to song writing. Emphasis will be placed on praise and worship and contemporary Christian songs. (Prerequisite: Student must have completed all Music Theory requirements) </P>

<P>MUS 3333 Church Music History 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey of music from the Old Testament period to the twentieth-century Pentecostal movement. Emphasis will be placed on the analysis of trends in church music history through means of musical literature and listening examples. Special correlation between music trends and concurrent theological movements will be examined.  </P>

<P>MUS 3342 Choral Arranging 	2 Hours </P>

<P>Study of vocal ranges and techniques for writing arrangements for choral groups and smaller vocal ensembles. (Prerequisite: MUS 2224) </P>

<P>MUS 3352 Form and Analysis 	2 Hours </P>

<P>Study of formal and harmonic structure of various musical styles. Analysis of varied vocal and instrumental works. (Prerequisite: MUS 2224) </P>

<P>MUS 3373 Music History I 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the historical development of musical forms and styles up to and including the Baroque period. Emphasis will be placed on analysis of specific genres, common trends in musical styles, and listening examples. (Prerequisite: MUS 2224) </P>

<P>MUS 3383 Music History II 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the historical development of musical forms and styles from the Baroque to the present. American music and ethnomusicological topics will also be discussed. Emphasis will be placed on analysis of specific genres, common trends in musical styles, and listening examples. (Prerequisite: MUS 2224) </P>

<P>MUS 4123 Worship Leadership	3 Hours</P>

<P>Practical applications for worship leading, development of the worship team, use of modern praise/worship songs, and integration of them into the worship service of the church. (Prerequisite: MUS 3113)</P>

<P>MUS 4143 Principles and Practices of Music Ministry	3 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of the principles, development and administration of a church music program including staff relationships, management and leadership, recruitment and training of musicians, choral/instrumental literature, musical productions and budget preparation.</P>

<P>MUS 4154 Instrumental Literacy and Pedagogy	4 Hours</P>

<P>A study and survey of instrumental literature from all periods of music history appropriate for secondary school bands and instrumental performers. Examines appropriate techniques for managing, maintaining and caring for an instrumental music program with emphasis placed upon pedagogical material for brass, woodwind, strings and percussion, selection of instruments, uniforms, testing and rehearsal procedures.</P>

<P>MUS 4164 Piano Literacy and Pedagogy	4 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of keyboard literature from all periods of music history. Examines and evaluates methods and materials designed for elementary and intermediate level students. Explores issues related to the piano teaching profession. Studio policy and management. Class demonstrations and studio observations.</P>

<P>MUS 4174 Vocal Literacy and Pedagogy	4 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of vocal literature from 1600 to the present. Examines appropriate musical examples for each natural voice part from art song literature. Concepts and techniques for the teaching of singing which includes respiration, phonation, resonance, diction (an introduction to the IPA with special emphasis on </P>

<P/>

<P>English, Italian, German and French) and articulation. Class demonstrations and studio observations.</P>

<P>MUS 4183 Jazz Theory 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Basic musical concepts relating to jazz scales, harmonies, and styles. Ear-training of the melodic, harmonic, and rhythmic materials that are idiomatic to jazz. Includes the dictation and transcription of jazz melodies, rhythms, and chord progressions. (Prerequisite: Applicable MAP courses [2000, 2100, 2200], MUS 2224)</P>

<P>MUS 4212 Jazz Arranging	2 Hours </P>

<P>Arranging in the jazz and commercial idioms with emphasis on the large ensemble. Transcriptions for various jazz ensembles. Study of scores for specific techniques and writing arrangements for jazz ensembles. (Prerequisite: MUS 2224, MUS 4183)</P>

<P>MUS 4223 Jazz History 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A chronological survey of the major styles and artists of jazz, from its African and European roots, its acculturation in the New World to the present. Development of intelligent listening habits with regard to standard small and large ensemble repertoire. (Prerequisite: MUS 2224, MUS 4183)</P>

<P>MUS 4312 Instrumental Arranging 	2 Hours </P>

<P>Basic ranges and transpositions of instruments. Transcriptions for various instrumental combinations and small orchestras. Study of scores for specific instrumental techniques, and writing arrangements for various ensembles. (Prerequisites: MUS 2224,  MUS 3322)</P>

<P>MUS 4493 Music Internship	3 Hours</P>

<P>The student is assigned to a qualified mentor, and actively participates in a supervised music ministry program. (Prerequisites: All Music Theory requirements met; all Conducting requirements met; MUS 3113, MUS 4143) </P>

<New_Style_Sheet>PASTORAL MINISTRIES</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>PMN 3213 Ministerial Ethics 	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course addresses ethical foundations provided in Scripture and the cultural challenges confronted by today’s ministry leader. The student will be taught the biblical basis for ethical decision-making and learn to address the core challenges to such a life presented by modern culture. Special emphasis will be given to developing the student’s personal integrity and explore the strategies needed to lead a community of believers in biblical response and ethical decision-making. Assignments will involve the student in the type of discussions faced by ministers today and provide students with a foundational process for engaging the new challenges that will arise in the future.</P>

<P>PMN 3363 Biblical Preaching Laboratory 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A basic course in sermon delivery. Special attention is given to the variety of sermons that can be delivered utilizing an expository philosophy including evangelistic messages and first person narratives. A creative team format will be applied to produce contemporary sermons that incorporate the effective use of multimedia, video and drama. (Prerequisite: CMN 3333) </P>

<P/>

<P>PMN 3413 Introduction to Rural Ministry	3 Hours
This is a specialized study in rural ministry within the United States of America. The course is designed to challenge students with real-world problems faced by rural ministers as well as present the unique opportunities and challenges faced in rural churches and communities. The primary focus of this course is to help the student discover and effectively minister within the rural culture and embrace methods that will strengthen ministry to rural churches.</P>

<P>PMN 4413 Pastoral Leadership	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the varied responsibilities and duties of pastoral ministry. Practical concerns such as administrative responsibilities, pastoral care, ceremonies, legal matters, ethical issues, interpersonal skills in ministry, the business meeting, and denominational responsibilities and relationships are addressed. </P>

<P>PMN 4423 Grief, Death, and Dying 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A course designed to help the student offer pastoral care and counseling to the dying and those close to the dying. This course examines the biblical view of grief, death, and dying. This course explores the dynamics of loss and examines current literature of the subject of ministry to the dying and bereaved. (Same as PSY 4423) </P>

<New_Style_Sheet>PHYSICAL EDUCATION</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>PED 1101-2291 Activity Classes 	1 Hour </P>

<P>PED 1111 Tennis </P>

<P>PED 1121 Basketball</P>

<P>PED 1141 Physical Conditioning (M) </P>

<P>PED 1151 Physical Conditioning (M &amp; F) </P>

<P>PED 1161 Volleyball </P>

<P>PED 1171 Fitness Walking </P>

<P>PED 1181 Archery </P>

<P>PED 1211 Soccer</P>

<P>PED 1311 Flag Football </P>

<P>PED 1411 Physical Activity</P>

<P>PED 1511 Self Defense</P>

<P>PED 1911 Cheerleading </P>

<P>PED 2211 Jogging </P>

<P>PED 2221 Weight Training </P>

<P>PED 2241 Softball </P>

<P>PED 2261 Intermediate Volleyball </P>

<P>PED  2271 Intermediate Physical Conditioning </P>

<P>PED 2281 Aerobics </P>

<P>PED 2112 Personal and Community Health	2 Hours</P>

<P>An examination of personal, physical, and emotional health in the context of the community health, the nation’s health, health care delivery and environmental health and safety. </P>

<P>PED 2113 Introduction to Kinesiology	3 Hours</P>

<P>The course provides a broad spectrum of the academic discipline of kinesiology. Fundamental concepts and meaning of movement/physical activity will be explored. Current issues and career options within kinesiology are presented.</P>

<P>PED 2123 Coaching Theory	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the principles of coaching with an emphasis on organization, coaching strategies, behavioral management, philosophy, planning and the unique responsibilities of coaching.</P>

<P/>

<P>PED 2213 Team Sport Skills	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course provides the opportunity to develop knowledge, skills, rules, tactics and strategies in teaching team sport skills. Emphasis is placed on methodology of teaching these concepts in the K-12 school setting. (This course satisfies general activity course requirement.)</P>

<P>PED 2223 Individual and Dual Sport Skills	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course provides the opportunity to develop knowledge, skills, rules, tactics, and strategies for individual and dual sport skills and games. Emphasis is placed on methodology of teaching these concepts in the K-12 school setting. (This course satisfies general activity course requirement.)</P>

<P>PED 2232 Wellness and Lifestyle 	2 Hours </P>

<P>A comprehensive review of principles relating to cardiovascular fitness, exercise, diet, and the development of a healthy lifestyle. The course will be a combination of classroom lecture and physical activity. Among the topics to be discussed are dietary contributions to wellness and fitness, aerobic training principles, exercise and weight control, and life sports. This course includes a life sports lab with the student choosing from options such as: archery, tennis, jogging, fitness walking, cycling, and bowling. </P>

<P>PED 2301 First Aid 	1 Hour </P>

<P>An introduction and study of basic first aid principles and techniques. The life support procedure of cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) will be reviewed and practiced. This course will provide experience helpful in response to emergency situations. </P>

<P>PED 2413 Theory of Coaching Soccer	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will provide students the knowledge of the fundamentals, theory, principles, philosophy, techniques, and strategies of soccer for the elementary, secondary, and collegiate levels. Communication and motivational skills will be presented.</P>

<P>PED 2423 Theory of Coaching Baseball and Softball	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will provide students knowledge of the fundamentals, theory, principles, philosophy, techniques, and strategies of coaching baseball and softball for the elementary, secondary, and collegiate levels. Communication and motivational skills will be presented.</P>

<P>PED 2433 Theory of Coaching Football	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will include coaching fundamental skills, techniques, and methods applicable to coaching football. Included will be offensive, defensive and special team strategies and basic formations. Communication and motivational skills will be presented.</P>

<P>PED 2443 Theory of Coaching Basketball	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will provide students the knowledge of the theory, principles, philosophy, techniques, and strategies of basketball at elementary, secondary, and collegiate levels. Communication and motivational skills will be presented. (Prerequisite: PED 2123 and sophomore status)</P>

<P>PED 3000 Varsity Athletics 	1 Hour </P>

<P>For those students participating in recognized varsity level, intercollegiate sports, it is possible to receive the equivalent of one semester of physical education credit per semester of participation. Involvement and requirements for individual and </P>

<P>team sports established by the University will be administered by the athletic director.</P>

<P>PED 3311 Women’s Varsity Volleyball </P>

<P>PED 3321 Men’s Varsity Football </P>

<P>PED 3331 Men’s Varsity Basketball </P>

<P>PED 3341 Women’s Varsity Basketball </P>

<P>PED 3351 Varsity Track and Field </P>

<P>PED 3361 Varsity Baseball</P>

<P>PED 3371 Varsity Cheerleading</P>

<P>PED 3381 Varsity Soccer</P>

<P>PED 3391 Varsity Women’s Softball</P>

<P>PED 3411 Varsity Cross Country</P>

<P>PED 3911 Women’s Varsity Soccer</P>

<P>PED 3143 Nutrition for Fitness and Sport   	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of nutritional considerations and implications for individuals active in physical fitness and sporting activities.</P>

<P>PED 3153 Care and Prevention of Athletic Injuries 	3 Hours</P>

<P>An overview of athletic training including the care and prevention, management, and rehabilitation of athletic injury. </P>

<P>PED 3163 Motor Development and Learning	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will provide a basic overview of the processes and mechanisms underlying the development of motor skills. Topics such as developmental motor patterns, cognitive, emotional, and physiological development, and fundamental motor pattern analysis for proper development over the lifespan will be included. (Prerequisite: PED 3133 or taken concurrently)</P>

<P>PED 3173 Management in Health and Sport   	3 Hours</P>

<P>Principles of organization and implementation of policies and procedures relating to the management of health/fitness and sport related programs. </P>

<P>PED 4113 Tests and Measurements   	3 Hours</P>

<P>Application of measurements in health fitness and sports settings, including tests of strength, physical fitness, sports skills, and progress. </P>

<P>PED 4123 Adapted Physical Activity   	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introductory survey course in adapting physical activity for individuals with physical limitations. History, legal implications, assessment, programming, and adapting instruction will be discussed.</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>PSYCHOLOGY</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>PSY 1113 Psychology of Selfhood and the Christian Faith			3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is to integrate psychological and clear biblical instruction in order to: identify and understand the nature of one’s quest for significance; recognize and challenge inadequate answers; apply sound biblical and psychological solutions to one’s search for significance. </P>

<P>PSY 1153 Introduction to Psychology 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An introduction to the basic procedures in the study of behavior and the elementary principles of conditioning, motivation, emotion, personality, sensation, perception, abnormal psychology, and social dynamics.</P>

<P>PSY 2323 Developmental Psychology 	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course is a foundational study of the life span from conception to death taking into account bio-psycho-social and spiritual influences on human development. Special attention will be given to guidance toward responsible behavior and control from a Judeo-Christian perspective. </P>

<P>PSY 2413 Statistics for Behavioral Sciences 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a study of organizing and interpreting psychological and behavioral science research data. It includes a survey of statistical description, including measure of central tendency, dispersion, and correlation. Basic research principles and methods of research are studied. (Same as SWK 2413)</P>

<P>PSY 2423 Cultural Issues in the Helping Professions	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course provides a psychological study, with a Christian perspective, of culturally and religiously diverse populations with an emphasis on various issues relevant to particular types of intervention. This subject is relevant to students who might work in a variety of cultural and religious areas . (Same as SWK 2423)</P>

<P>PSY 2513 Counseling Methods in Chemical Dependency and Other Addictions 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A course in counseling methods and techniques with the substance abusing and/or addictive client. Individual, family and group processes and interventions are explored in rehabilitation and recovery programs such as criminal justice agencies, therapeutic communities, and various faith-based community addictions services. Current models of prevention and intervention are studied as well as the 12-step recovery approach. One area of focus includes the special skills and techniques utilized with the Alcohol and Other Drug (AOD) client, incorporating the 12 core functions of an addiction counselor. i.e., screening, intake, assessment, treatment planning, case management, counseling, crisis intervention, client education, referral, report and record keeping, and consultation. (Same as COU 2513)</P>

<P>PSY 2523 Professional, Ethical and Special Issues for the Addictions Professional 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course includes a systematic review of the competencies and knowledge areas required in preparation for licensure as a chemical dependency counselor in Texas. However, there should be significant overlap with those seeking licensure in other states. The competence, role and function of the addiction counselor are reviewed in relation to such issues as stress, burn-out, resilience, dealing with denial and resistance, client defense mechanisms, confidentiality, scope of practice and type of clientele. Ethical guidelines and dilemmas are explored along with such special issues as criminal behavior and the criminal justice system, cultural norms and influences, family-of-origin dynamics, alcohol family roles, codependency, domestic violence, child abuse, HIV-AIDS awareness, women’s issues, and Judeo-Christian perspectives on addictive behavior. (Same as COU 2523)</P>

<P>PSY 2533 Pharmacology of Addiction	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course examines the psychological, physiological, and sociological effects of mood altering substances and behaviors and their implications for the addiction process, including signs and symptoms of addictive behavior and phases of relapse. There is an emphasis on pharmacological effects of tolerance, dependency/withdrawal, cross addiction, and drug interaction. HIV, AIDS, STDS, and addiction related pathology are also covered. (Same as COU 2533)</P>

<P>PSY 3111 Practicum in Substance Abuse Counseling I 	1 Hour </P>

<P>This course focuses on practical, general workplace training supported by an individualized learning plan developed by the employer, University, and student. This course fulfills 100 of the required 300 hours practicum for LCDC. (Prerequisite: COU 2123, COU 2223, COU 2513, COU 2523, COU 2533, PSY 3443) (Same as COU 3111)</P>

<P>PSY 3121 Practicum in Substance Abuse Counseling II	1 Hour </P>

<P>This course focuses on practical, general workplace training supported by an individualized learning plan developed by the employer, University, and student. This course fulfills 100 of the required 300 hours practicum for LCDC. (Prerequisite: COU 2123, COU 2223, COU 2513, COU 2523, COU 2533, PSY 3443) (Same as COU 3121)</P>

<P>PSY 3131 Practicum in Substance Abuse Counseling III</P>

<P> 	1 Hour </P>

<P>This course focuses on practical, general workplace training supported by an individualized learning plan developed by the employer, University, and student. This course fulfills 100 of the required 300 hours practicum for LCDC. (Prerequisite: COU 2123, COU 2223, COU 2513, COU 2523, COU 2533, PSY 3443) (Same as COU 3131)</P>

<P>PSY 3313 Abnormal Psychology 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of theoretical approaches, etiology, development, symptomatology, classification and treatment of abnormal behaviors. Epidemiological variables and research contributions are reviewed in relation to the occurrence and treatment of problematic behaviors and mental disorders. Students also learn how to utilize the professionally accepted diagnostic classification system. (Prerequisite: PSY 1153)</P>

<P>PSY 3331 Counseling Seminar 	1 Hour </P>

<P>The University provides a counseling psychology seminar as part of an annual continuing educational conference for pastoral and professional counselors. The two day conference features a key note speaker, workshops, discussion and process groups and significant opportunities for student seminar participants to interface with professionals in the field. The conference convenes on campus and may be taken for one hour of academic course credit.</P>

<P>PSY 3333 Theories of Personality 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An introductory study of some of the major approaches, methods, and findings in the field of personality. It represents an overview of the basic theories, strategies, issues and conclusions in the psychology of personality. (Prerequisite: PSY 1153) </P>

<P>PSY 3443 Crisis Intervention and Management 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a study of crisis intervention and management with a Christian perspective. This course reviews theoretical models of crisis development in a variety of settings. Students will develop an understanding of intervention and management techniques demonstrating a competency in crisis intervention skills. Special emphasis is given to suicide, family crisis, and major catastrophes. (Same as COU 3443, SWK 3443)</P>

<P>PSY 3453 Social Psychology 	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the psychological study of social behavior to include an exploration of social cognition, influence, change, group structure and interpersonal processes. Social interaction and interpersonal communication variables are explored. </P>

<P>PSY 3463 Theories and Principles of Learning 	3 Hours</P>

<P>Basic theories and processes of learning and conditioning in humans and animals are studied. These include classical and operant conditioning as well as social and cognitive approaches. Selected behavior management techniques and their applications are reviewed.</P>

<P>PSY 4113 History and Systems of Psychology 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of evolution of thought in psychology from its inception as an experimental science to significant systems, issues, and experiments of theories of today. </P>

<P>PSY 4213 Introduction to Clinical Psychology 	3 Hours </P>

<P>This course provides a survey of historical foundations, ethical principles, basic assessment methods including practical interviewing and schools of counseling and psychotherapy related to clinical psychology. An orientation to the field and requirements for professional practice is provided. </P>

<P>PSY 4313 Behavioral Science Research 	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the various research methods in the behavioral sciences. Emphasis is on the techniques used as well as the process and ethics of research. Topics investigated include: sampling, hypothesis development and testing, and research design. (Prerequisite: PSY 2413. Same as COU 4313, SWK 4313)</P>

<P>PSY 4333 Introduction to Psychological Tests and Measurements 	3 Hours</P>

<P>Surveys a variety of psychological assessment techniques typically used in psychological evaluation and assessment. Some attention is given to test construction and measures of reliability and validity. The ethics involved in psychological testing is also considered. The course of study is limited to counseling and psychology majors. (Prerequisite: PSY 1153)</P>

<P>PSY 4343 Introduction to Biopsychology 	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introductory study of the nervous system which includes the relationship to bodily function and behavior. Specific topics studied include sensory and motor function, perception, cognition, motivation, emotion, learning and memory. Various neurological disorders as well as aspects of their assessment and treatment are reviewed. (Prerequisites: BIO 1113 [preferred], PSY 1153)</P>

<P>PSY 4423 Grief, Death, and Dying 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A course designed to help the student offer pastoral care and counseling to the dying and those close to the dying. This course examines the biblical view of grief, death, and dying. This course explores the dynamics of loss and examines current literature of the subject of ministry to the dying and bereaved. (Same as PMN 4423) </P>

<P>PSY 4433 Psychology of Religion 	3 Hours</P>

<P>A course designed to guide the student in thinking psychologically, from the perspective of evangelical Christianity, about religious phenomena. The assumptions and methods in psychological approaches to the study of religious beliefs, experiences, and behaviors are also examined as they relate to integration of psychology and theology. Included is a review of research findings as constructs are applied to selected aspects of religious behavior. </P>

<P>PSY 4483 Human Sexuality 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A course of study that considers the biological-psychological and social dimensions of human sexuality from a Bible-based perspective. The initial consideration of human sexuality is formed by the Genesis account of human creation. Areas of focus include dynamic formulation of sexual identity and gender roles, human sexuality throughout the life cycle, sexual deviancy, and contemporary sexual issues. </P>

<P>PSY 4513 Special Issues in the Behavioral Sciences	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course focuses on research, defense and logical argumentation of special and controversial issues in the behavioral sciences from a Christian perspective. Students will apply theoretical, biblical and research-based studies to these discussions. Strategies for researching background information and behavioral science studies as well as appropriate participation in the discussions and debates will be emphasized. (Same as COU 4513) (Replaced by PSY 4523)</P>

<P>PSY 4523 Advanced General Psychology	3 Hours</P>

<P>This is a capstone course designed for upper level senior advanced undergraduate students in psychology to review, prepare and assist in developing a more in-depth orientation to main domains of psychology. A Major Studies Examination in psychology is provided over multiple domains in the discipline. This course explores the integration of knowledge in psychological science with a Christian worldview. The student is required to complete a senior level research project under the supervision of a major professor in psychology. (Prerequisites: PSY 2413, PSY 3313, PSY 4113, PSY 4213, PSY 4313)</P>

<P>PSY 4583 Field Practicum 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course requires the student to complete 120 hours in an off-campus setting allowing him or her the opportunity for experiential learning. Students will complete assignments designed to demonstrate knowledge, competency of the profession, and the ability to complete guided field research. (Permission of academic advisor or department chair required.)</P>

<P>PSY 4993 Special Topics   	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will focus on a specific topic including those which demand further intensive study as well as contemporary issues. In this regard, this course allows for recent developments and latest issues in the field related to a specific topic as well as the possible research interests of the professor. This course is intended to provide the student the opportunity to enhance their knowledge of a selected topic by examination of salient, current critical issues. This course may be taken as a general elective and may be repeated for another topic. (Prerequisites: Permission to take this subject has to be approved by the program coordinator or department chair.)</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>READING</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>RDG 3413 Foundations of Literacy Instruction	3 Hours</P>

<P>Foundations of emergent literacy frameworks, instructional practices and strategies are introduced from birth to grade 3. Guidance and practice in planning and organizing for instruction for the five essential components of reading instruction: phonemic awareness, phonics, fluency, vocabulary, and comprehension. Reading and language arts theory, content and methods will be emphasized according to research and state standards. Includes field experience hours.	</P>

<P>RDG 3423 Reading and Writing Across the Curriculum	                                                                                       		3 Hours</P>

<P>Guidance and practice in planning and organizing phonics, vocabulary, fluency, and comprehension instruction in the intermediate grades 3-8. Includes strong emphasis on integrating strategies to use multiple sources of information and technology in the content areas for the purpose of reading and writing to learn. Reading and language arts theory, content, and methods will be emphasized according to research and state standards. Includes field experience hours. (Prerequisite: RDG 3413)</P>

<P>RDG 3433 Literacy Assessment and Instruction	3 Hours</P>

<P>Presents current research practices and methods in literacy development and assessment. Focuses on informal and formal assessment practices with an emphasis on gathering, analyzing, and interpreting data for the purpose of making data-driven instructional decisions. Examines characteristics and uses of a wide variety of evaluation and assessment tools. Includes field experience hours. (Prerequisite: RDG 3413)</P>

<P>RDG 3452 Adolescent Literacy Instruction	3 Hours</P>

<P>Guidance and practice in planning and organizing integrated instruction for reading, writing, speaking, listening, viewing, and visually representing for adolescents. Strong emphasis on integrating the language arts state standards through reading and writing instruction. Includes field experience hours.</P>

<P>RDG 4513 Content and Disciplinary Literacy Instruction</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>Guidance and practice in theory, content, and methods for integrating reading and writing in content and disciplinary areas of instruction. Emphasis on literacy processes and their interrelatedness to all instruction and learning, strategies for text comprehension, developing vocabulary, reading and writing to learn, and using study and inquiry skills with a variety of texts. Includes field experience hours. (Prerequisites: RDG 3413, RDG  3423, RDG 3433) </P>

<New_Style_Sheet>RELIGION/PHILOSOPHY</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>PHL 2223 Introduction to Philosophy 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An introductory course in which a study is made of the major philosophers and schools of philosophical thought from the earliest known system to contemporary thought, inclusive of western philosophies of religion.</P>

<P>PHL 2233 Logic, Reason, and Persuasion 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Examination of the logical structure of argumentation and the development of skills in reasoning. Emphasis is placed on the essential principles in constructing valid arguments and identifying classic fallacies.</P>

<P>PHL 3113 History of Philosophy	3 Hours</P>

<P>A comprehensive survey of the major thinkers and schools of thought in the Western Philosophical Tradition from classical Greece to the present. The course pays special attention to how ideas found in these traditions have contributed and opposed a Christian worldview.</P>

<P>PHL 3123 Philosophy of Religion 	3 Hours </P>

<P>Introduction to philosophical issues concerning religion, including the origin and nature of evil, the existence and nature of God, and religious knowledge and language.</P>

<P>PHL 3143 Christian Ethics	3 Hours</P>

<P>In this course the Bible is used in shaping attitudes, motivation and purposes. The Bible will provide the essential data for forming a Christian world view. The course will give students an understanding and grasp of Christian truth for effective Christian witness. The ethical content of the Old Testament is examined with attention given to the ethics of the law, the prophets, and wisdom literature. The ethical teachings of Jesus, Paul, and other New Testament writers are considered, with particular attention given to the role of the Holy Spirit in morality. (Replaced by REL 3153)</P>

<P>REL 1133 Authentic Christianity	3 Hours</P>

<P>The experience and ethics of authentic Christianity within contemporary culture. Using the Word of God, students embrace its unique world view as a foundation for exemplary living, decision making, exploring personal aspirations, facing dilemmas and problem solving. Christian devotion and service in the Church and the marketplace are emphasized as well as the essential spiritual disciplines for character formation:  engaging Scripture, personal and intercessory prayer, the dynamic of the Holy Spirit, and purity in lifestyle. Students are challenged to discover (and become one with) God’s view of themselves, the current times, and God’s purposes in the world.</P>

<P>REL 1153 New Testament Literature                       3 Hours</P>

<P>An overview study of the New Testament. Special emphasis is given to the content, genre, themes, and historical setting of each of the books of the New Testament, along with the intent and purpose of each writer. The study includes a unit dealing with the life of Christ, as well as how the New Testament was  produced and handed down in their present form. Significant passages of Scripture relating to the role of the Holy Spirit within the church and each Christian are studied.</P>

<P>REL 1163 Old Testament Literature                        	3 Hours</P>

<P>An overview study of the Old Testament. Special emphasis is given to the content, genre, themes, and historical setting of each of the books of the Old Testament, along with the intent and purpose of each writer. How the Scriptures were produced, preserved and handed down in their present form is briefly reviewed with an emphasis on the Old Testament. The continuing theme of redemption is given special emphasis.</P>

<P>REL 1173 Introduction to Biblical Literature	3 Hours</P>

<P>An exposition of the biblical narrative from Genesis to Revelation with an emphasis on the redemptive story that unites the Scriptures. It acquaints students with the major characters, narratives, and theological themes within the cultural and historical backgrounds of the biblical worlds.</P>

<P>REL 3113 Christianity in the Ancient and Middle Ages	                                                                                  		3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of the history of Christianity from the New Testament era to the eve of the Reformation. Special attention is given to the persecution and early challenges to the church, Christological Controversies, Monasticism, Constantine, the rise and fall of the papacy, Scholasticism, Wycliffe, and Hus.</P>

<P>REL 3123 Christianity from the Reformation to the
Postmodern Era                                                       3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of the history of Christianity from the Protestant Reformation to contemporary times. Special attention is given to the Reformation and the Counter Reformation, Puritans, Pietism, Wesley and the Holiness Movement, the impact of the Enlightenment, and revivals.</P>

<P>REL 3133 In-Context Experience                           3 Hours</P>

<P>Students will participate in a cross-cultural field experience in a location overseas or in the United States. They will be assigned to a qualified mentor or training location and actively participate in supervised intercultural service, community development, and other activities depending on practicum location. Students must apply for their practicum one semester in advance and be approved by the ICS Committee to participate. Students must successfully complete a field experience for a minimum of 12 weeks. (This course is designed for students with majors other than Intercultural Studies.) (Prerequisite: BIB 1223)</P>

<P>REL 3143 Second Temple History                               3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the history and literature of the Second Temple Period that frames the transition from the world of the Old Testament to the New Testament era. (Prerequisites: REL 1153, REL 1163)</P>

<P>REL 3153 Christian Ethics                                         3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the moral principles that govern human conduct with particular attention to normative ethical theories as applied from a Christian perspective to contemporary ethical issues.</P>

<P>REL 4113 History of Modern Revivals                        3 Hours</P>

<P>A survey of modern revivals and awakenings from the birth of Evangelicalism in the eighteenth century to the modern era.</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>SCIENCE </New_Style_Sheet>

<P>BIO 1111 Introductory Biology Lab                            1 Hour </P>

<P>Introduction to the tools and methods of the biologist. The student will learn to use the light microscope; how to identify, examine, and dissect selected lab specimens; how to use laboratory aids; and how to report results of laboratory observations. (Prerequisite: BIO 1113, concurrent enrollment with BIO 1113) </P>

<P>BIO 1113 Biological Science 	3 Hours </P>

<P>The fundamental concepts of biology. An emphasis is on human biology including the organ systems. The place of people in their environment and the importance of their environment to them are both examined from a biblical perspective. The lab allows students to use the scientific method to examine and test many of the facts and concepts presented.  </P>

<P>BIO 2111 Human Anatomy and Physiology I Lab	1 Hour</P>

<P>This course is a lab course to be taken by students in the A.S. degree in Health Science. It is the lab connected to the Human Anatomy and Physiology course. (Prerequisite: Lab Manual)</P>

<P>BIO 2123 Human Anatomy and Physiology I	3 Hours</P>

<P>Anatomy and Physiology I is the first part of a two course sequence.  This course covers fundamental principles of body systems and their functions.  Topics include basic chemistry, cells, tissues and organs of the following systems: integumentary, skeletal, muscular, nervous and special senses. Relationships among systems and regulation of physiological functions involved in maintaining homeostasis will be emphasized. Laboratory work includes dissection of preserved specimens, microscopic study, examining models, and physiological and computer simulations experiments. (Same as KIN 2123) </P>

<P>BIO 2124 Human Anatomy and Physiology II with Lab	</P>

<P>	4 Hours</P>

<P>This course is the second of a two part course sequence. Topics include the endocrine, cardiovascular, lymphatic, respiratory, digestive, urinary, and reproductive systems as well as human development, genetics, metabolism, nutrition, acid-base balance, and fluid and electrolyte balance. Upon completion, students should be able to demonstrate an in-depth understanding of principles of anatomy and physiology and their interrelationships. Laboratory work includes dissection of preserved specimens, microscopic study, examining models, and physiological and computer simulations experiments. (Prerequisites: BIO 2111, BIO 2113)</P>

<P>BIO 2214 Microbiology with Lab	4 Hours</P>

<P>This course covers principles of microbiology with emphasis on microorganisms in human disease. Topics include morphology and physiology of microorganisms, growth and control of microbial pathogens, aspects of medical microbiology, disease transmission, immunology, antimicrobial agents, and infectious diseases. Laboratory procedures include staining techniques, culturing and sensitivity determinations.</P>

<P>CHE 1114 Chemistry for Health Science with Lab	4 Hours</P>

<P>This course introduces concepts of general and biological chemistry. Topics include measurement, molecular structure, nuclear chemistry, solutions, acid-base chemistry, gas laws, and the structure, properties and reactions of major biological groups. Additional topics include the structure, function, and metabolism of lipids, carbohydrates, proteins, and nucleic acids. The laboratory will provide experimental applications of these chemical topics.</P>

<P>PHY 1111 Introduction to Physical Science Lab 	1 Hour </P>

<P>Introduction to the tools and methods of the physical scientist. Students will confirm many of the basic concepts of physics and chemistry. Methods of testing and identifying rocks and minerals will be included. (Prerequisite: PHY 1113, concurrent enrollment with PHY 1113) </P>

<P>PHY 1113 Physical Science 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A survey of the basic concepts and history of physics, chemistry, physical science, geology, and astronomy. Students will confirm many of the basic concepts of physics and chemistry. Astronomical observations include identifying certain planets, stars, and constellations. Methods of testing and identifying rocks and minerals will be included. </P>

<New_Style_Sheet>SOCIAL WORK</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>SOC 2213 Introductory Sociology 	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of human nature and human behavior as the product of group life. Emphasis is placed on the organization of society and processes involved; class, status, caste, race relations, communications, public opinion, and propaganda. </P>

<P>SOC 2253 Marriage and Family Relationships	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the historical and comparative importance of the family, the effect and impact of modern industrial society and social change upon the family, and family integration and disintegration. </P>

<P>SOC 3323 Social Problems	3 Hours</P>

<P>An analysis of the nature and diversity of social and personal disorganization, social change as a source of social problems, and social planning and social movements as solutions. </P>

<P>SWK 2113 Introduction to Social Work   	3 Hours</P>

<P>An overview of the profession of social work with a focus on philosophy, historical development, concepts and methods in relation to the social welfare system. Aspects of integrating professional practice and a Christian perspective are reviewed.</P>

<P>SWK 2123 Social Work Practice I	3 Hours</P>

<P>Introduction to general social work practice with emphasis on person in environment construct. Ethical principles and critical thinking in practice as well as incorporating diversity are taught. Research-informed for the generalist practitioners using a wide range of prevention and intervention methods with individuals, families and small groups are taught. (Prerequisite: SWK 2113)</P>

<P>SWK 2133 Social Welfare Policies, Programs and Issues 
	3 Hours</P>

<P>An analysis of the contemporary organization and function of the social service delivery system in the United States with a focus on social welfare programs, policies and issues in light of the impact of socioeconomic and political variables. The role of values and the church is addressed in light of the social service delivery system. </P>

<P>SWK 2143 Human Behavior in the Social Environment I</P>

<P>3 Hours</P>

<P>Provides a basic conceptual framework for creating and organizing theories and knowledge about generalist practice regarding human behavior and social environments. Students analyze biological, psychological, sociological, cultural, and spiritual variables to examine human growth and development across the lifespan. Considers how human behavior and social environments inform social work practice with various populations, including those at risk. Addresses the impact of diversity, discrimination, and oppression on development. Students utilize conceptual frameworks to guide the processes of assessment, intervention and evaluation, and critique and apply knowledge to understand person and environment.. (Prerequisite: SWK 2113)</P>

<P>SWK 2153 Women’s Studies   	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course offers an introduction to Women’s Studies, an interdisciplinary academic field that explores critical questions about women in society across the life-span, both historical and contemporary. Students will become familiar with key issues, questions, and debates in the study of women. Included is a critical analysis of the micro, mezzo and macro levels of interventions with respect to culture, laws, education, the workplace, communities, churches, medicine, social policy and the family. A study of women in the Bible and modern-day Christian women who have made a positive impact across the globe. </P>

<P>SWK 2163 International Social Work 	3 Hours</P>

<P>Introduction to general social work in a global context. The course will look at the types of groups or organizations doing humanitarian work and social development throughout the world including orphanages and human trafficking interventionists. An examination of the impact on society and cultures by global phenomena such as migration, environmental degradation, natural disasters, war, civil strife, terrorism, abuse/neglect, addiction, and human trafficking. The course will explore challenges of cross-cultural social work, critically analyze social development, and provide examples of how social workers collaborate to address problems, advocate, empower, network, and educate within the populations of various countries, but also beyond. Cultures will be examined from a Christian worldview through interventions, strategies, community participation, sustainable development, root causes, promotion of human rights and social justice. (Prerequisite: SWK 2113)</P>

<P>SWK 2173 Forensic Social Work 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is designed to teach students the nature and dynamics of Forensic Social Work. The course content will focus on social work within the criminal justice system and legal system. Included is an approach to theory, practice, intervention and advocacy within diverse populations including offenders, victims, juveniles, and related systems. The course includes an exploration and examination of the interaction between forensic social work and the micro, mezzo and macro levels of interventions. (Prerequisite: SWK 2113)</P>

<P>SWK 2213 Counseling Children and Adolescents	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course presents assessment, diagnosis, and remedial therapeutic techniques unique to the practice of counseling children and adolescents and presenting parents with tools to utilize in facilitating growth in their children. (Prerequisite: CMN 2313 or COU 2283) (Same as COU 2213)</P>

<P>SWK 2223 Addictive Behavior and Recovery 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will explore assessment and treatment of various addictions including substance abuse (drug and alcohol), sexual addictions (pornography), self mutilation, and other compulsive addictive behavior, and will focus on strategies for recovery. (Same as COU 2223)</P>

<P>SWK 2233 Abuse and Neglect	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is designed to provide a comprehensive introduction to child abuse and neglect from a social work perspective. Students learn the extent of the problem, effects on children, treatment issues and social worker’s role in a multidisciplinary team approach. (Prerequisite: SWK 2113)</P>

<P>SWK 2413 Statistics for Behavioral Sciences 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a study of organizing and interpreting psychological and behavioral science research data. It includes a survey of statistical description, including measure of central tendency, dispersion, and correlation. Basic research principles and methods of research are studied. (Same as PSY 2413)</P>

<P>SWK 2423 Cultural Issues in the Helping Professions	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course provides a psychological study, with a Christian perspective, of culturally and religiously diverse populations with an emphasis on various issues relevant to particular types of intervention. This subject is relevant to students who might work in a variety of cultural and religious areas . (Same as PSY 2423)</P>

<P>SWK 3113 Church and Community Social Work	3 Hours</P>

<P>A course designed to focus on the church as a complex organizational structure in relation to outreach functions and social service delivery processes.  Attention is given to effective methods for church-community interaction in the efficient delivery of vital services such as dream centers, para-church ministries and various church-related non-profit community outreach endeavors. Community assessment processes are surveyed as well as denominational policies for church related social service ministry. </P>

<P>SWK 3133 Delinquent Behavior and Rehabilitation 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a study of the nature, extent, causation, prevention and rehabilitation processes of juvenile delinquency.  Case management as well as procedures and operation of juvenile justice systems are also included. (Same as CJU 3133)</P>

<P>SWK 3143 Human Behavior in the Social Environment II</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is the second in a two-course foundation Human Behavior in the Social Environment sequence. This course explores various factors and components of human behavior and the social environment in a framework for studying the person-in-environment ecological approach. In this regard it focuses on contextual influences to include groups, communities and organizations and provides a conceptual model of behavior from a holistic perspective taking into consideration empowerment, professional values and ethics. (Prerequisite: SWK 2113)</P>

<P>SWK 3213 Social Work Practice II	3 Hours</P>

<P>Students explore frameworks, values, and skills to meet individual and family needs through interventions with work groups, organizations and communities. (Prerequisites: SWK 2113, SWK 2123)</P>

<P>SWK 3443 Crisis Intervention and Management 	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course is a study of crisis intervention and management with a Christian perspective. This course reviews theoretical models of crisis development in a variety of settings. Students will develop an understanding of intervention and management techniques demonstrating a competency in crisis intervention skills. Special emphasis is given to suicide, family crisis, and major catastrophes. (Same as COU 3443, PSY 3443)</P>

<P>SWK 4211 Integrative Practice I	1 Hour
The primary goal of this first integrative practice is fostering students to utilize the process of increasing self-awareness and reflection as a tool for practice while integrating content with their concurrent classes and agency field experiences. This practice class aims to promote and to increase the student’s professional social work identity and emerging practice competencies at the BSW level while integrating theory and ethics with practice. Case studies are reviewed and assessed for additional practice. The student earns one credit hour by successfully completing course requirements in the weekly one hour class, which mimics clinical social work supervision groups.  (Prerequisite: Taken concurrently with SWK 4814 in senior year)</P>

<P>SWK 4222 Integrative Practice II	2 Hour
The primary goal of this second integrative practice is fostering students to utilize the process of increasing self-awareness and reflection as a tool for practice while integrating content with their concurrent classes and agency field experiences. This practice class aims to promote and to increase the student’s professional social work identity and emerging practice competencies at the BSW level while integrating theory and ethics with practice. Emphasis will be placed on achieving a more complex integration of theory with practice and on critical evaluation of practice. Case studies will be reviewed and assessed for additional practice. The student earns two credit hours by successfully completing course requirements in the weekly one hour and fifteen minutes class. (Prerequisite: Taken concurrently with SWK 4824 in senior year)</P>

<P>SWK 4313 Behavioral Science Research 	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the various research methods in the behavioral sciences. Emphasis is on the techniques used as well as the process and ethics of research. Topics investigated include: sampling, hypothesis development and testing, and research design. (Prerequisite: PSY 2413. Same as COU 4313, PSY 4313)</P>

<P>SWK 4413 Methods and Techniques in Marriage and Family Counseling	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the use of particular techniques for working with marriages and families in counseling. Theory and practice will be integrated to identify when and how to use techniques with couples and families in the counseling setting. Role play and practice will be an integral part of this course. (Same as COU 4413)</P>

<P/>

<P/>

<P/>

<P>SWK 4483 Social Work Field Practicum I  	3 Hours</P>

<P>Supervised social field work experience of 200 hours in a community social service agency. (Prerequisites: Completion of SWK  2214, 2273, 2323, 3383, 3453 and a majority of the 3000 level subjects plus permission of the field practicum supervisor) (Replaced by SWK 4814)</P>

<P>SWK 4583 Social Work Field Practicum II   	3 Hours</P>

<P>Supervised social field work experience of 200 hours in a community social service agency. The same agency may not be used for Social Work Field Practicum I and II.  (Prerequisite: SWK 4483)(Replaced by SWK 4824)</P>

<P>SWK 4814 Social Work Field Practicum I	4 Hours
Field practice experience in social service agency setting approved by the Field Director or Program Director to apply and integrate skill, cognitive and affective learning within a formalized service system. BSW majors are required to successfully complete 225 clock hours for this practicum. (Prerequisites: Co-requisite with SWK 4211. SWK 2123, SWK 2143, SWK 3143, SWK 3213)</P>

<P>SWK 4824 Social Work Practicum II	4 Hours
Field practice experience in social service agency setting approved by the Field Director of Program Director to apply and integrate skill, cognitive and affective learning within a formalized service system. BSW majors are required to successfully complete 225 clock hours for this practicum. (Prerequisites: Co-requisite with SWK 4222. SWK 2123, SWK 2143, SWK 3143, SWK 4814)</P>

<P>SWK 4993 Special Topics   	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will focus on a specific topic including those which demand further intensive study as well as contemporary issues. In this regard, this course allows for recent developments and latest issues in the field related to a specific topic as well as the possible research interests of the professor. This course is intended to provide the student the opportunity to enhance their knowledge of a selected topic by examination of salient, current critical issues. This course may be taken as a general elective and may be repeated for another topic. (Prerequisites: Permission to take this subject has to be approved by the program coordinator or department chair.)	</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>THEOLOGY</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>THE 1113 Person and Work of the Holy Spirit 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the person, offices, gifts and administration of the Holy Spirit.</P>

<P>THE 2113 Introduction to Theology and Apologetics	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introductory survey of significant theological perspectives, personalities, and terms. The relationship of theology to the task of interpreting Scripture and the mission of the Church will be emphasized incorporating a basic defense of biblical Christianity. The relationship between biblical theology, systematic theology, and historical theology will be explored. The individual categories of systematic theology will be given individual treatment and consideration.</P>
</Story>

<Story>
<P>THE 2333 Pentecostal Doctrine and History 	3 Hours </P>

<P>An historical theological study of the Pentecostal and Charismatic movements from the beginning of the 20th century until the present with special attention given to the doctrines of the Assemblies of God. The theology of the movements is analyzed from a New Testament biblical perspective. </P>

<P>THE 3113 Christian Apologetics	3 Hours</P>

<P>An introduction to the philosophical study and defense of the Christian faith. This course includes an examination of the apologetic task, a critique of opposing worldviews and the rational justification for belief in the exclusive claims of Christianity.</P>

<P>THE 3123 Systematic Theology I	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the doctrine of God, Scripture, creation, providence, angels, the unity and constitution of man, the fall of man, and the doctrine of sin. (Prerequisite: THE 2113)</P>

<P>THE 3133 Systematic Theology II	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of Christology, the doctrine of salvation, both theory and application, including atonement, calling, conviction, justification, adoption, regeneration, and sanctification. It also includes the doctrine of the Church, the ordinances, and eschatology. (Prerequisite: THE 2113)</P>

<P>THE 3223 Introduction to Islam	3 Hours</P>

<P>Introduction to Islam will provide an overview of Islam, including its historical background, development, spread, its diversity and why it has such worldwide appeal. We examine the main beliefs and practices of Muslims, noting similarities and crucial differences with Christianity in order to help Christian workers recognize both difficulties in evangelizing Muslims as well as the great opportunities. Special attention will be given to develop Christ-like attitudes and approaches for effective ministry to Muslims. (Same as ICS 3223) (Prerequisite: BIB 1223)</P>

<P>THE 3363 World Religions	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course seeks to equip the student with necessary knowledge to intelligently approach those of the non-Christian religions of the world. It views the tenets of the major religious systems comparatively. Religions studied include Pre-historic and tribal religions, Hinduism, Jainism, Sikhism, Buddhism, religions of East Asia, Zoroastrianism, Judaism, Christianity, and Islam. (Same as ICS 3363)</P>

<P>THE 4123 Cults, Occults and Folk Religions	3 Hours</P>

<P>These studies involve practical research and materials review as to the content and form of major “Christian” cults. The focus of the course is upon the development of mental and spiritual sensitivity to these teachings and practices when engaging in cross-cultural ministry. (Same as ICS 4123)</P>

<P>THE 4133 Twentieth-Century Theology	3 Hours</P>

<P>A selective study of major theologians of the twentieth century and their unique theological contributions. The course will include an overview of Schleiermacher, Hegel and Ritschl as providing a theological trajectory for the twentieth century. </P>

<P/>

<P>THE 4143 Seminar in Theology	3 Hours</P>

<P>An advanced study of a biblical, historical or systematic topic of theology. This course may be repeated provided the topic matter is distinct.</P>

<P>THE 4150 Senior Paper	0 Hours</P>

<P>The senior paper represents the culmination of the student’s biblical and theological training. The choice of topic must be made in consultation with the Department of Bible and Theology and an advisor will be assigned to guide the student during the writing process.  The course must be taken during the first semester of the senior year. (This course is available only to Bible and Theology, Biblical Studies, and Theological Studies majors) (Same as BIB 4150)</P>

<P>THE 4151 Senior Paper	1 Hour</P>

<P>The senior paper represents the culmination of the student’s biblical and theological training. The choice of topic must be made in consultation with the Department of Bible and Theology and an advisor will be assigned to guide the student during the writing process.  The course must be taken during the first semester of the senior year. (This course is available only to Bible and Theology, Biblical Studies, and Theological Studies majors) (Same as BIB 4151)(Replaced by THE 4150)</P>

<P>THE 4153 Nineteenth-Century Holiness Movement</P>

<P>	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the history and theology of the nineteenth-century Holiness movement and its influence on Pentecostalism. (Prerequisite: THE 2113)	</P>

<P>THE 4163 Reformation Theology	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of the history and theology of the reformation with emphasis on the contributions of Martin Luther, Huldrych Zwingli, John Calvin, and Menno Simons. (Prerequisite: THE 2113)</P>

<P>THE 4393 Old Testament Theology	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the key theological concepts and important doctrines of the Old Testament. Attention is given to the progressive steps in divine revelation and the relation of God to His people. (Prerequisite: THE 2113) </P>

<P>THE 4413 New Testament Theology 	3 Hours </P>

<P>A study of the key theological concepts and important doctrines of the New Testament. Attention is given to the question of Jewish, Hellenistic, and pagan origins of New Testament thought, including a unit on the history of New Testament interpretation. </P>

<New_Style_Sheet>WRITING</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>WRT 2143 Scriptwriting for Theatre and Film	3 Hours</P>

<P>The exploration of the basic principles required to develop and write scripts for theatre and film production. Topics of study and application include: story treatments, research, source interviews, early script drafts, and final script submissions. (Same as COM 2143)	</P>

<P>WRT 3113 Writing and Publishing Poetry	3 Hours</P>

<P>An intensive genre study of poetic forms and styles in a workshop environment, where students will build a portfolio of original works. Emphasis is placed on researching potential markets and submitting work to magazines and journals, including the University’s e-journal, The Image.</P>

<P>WRT 3123 Writing and Publishing Nonfiction	3 Hours</P>

<P>An intensive genre study of nonfiction writing, such as article, editorial, and memoir, in a workshop environment where students will build a portfolio of their own work. Emphasis is placed on researching potential markets and submitting work to magazines and journals, including the University’s e-journal, The Image. Emphasis will also include the technical writing field and its opportunities for employment.</P>

<P>WRT 4113 Studies in Short Fiction	3 Hours</P>

<P>An intensive genre study of the short story in a workshop environment, where students will produce a significant body of their own work.</P>

<P>WRT 4123 Writing and Publishing Long Fiction	3 Hours</P>

<P>An intensive genre study of the novel and/or drama in a workshop environment where students will produce a significant body of their own work. Emphasis is placed on researching potential markets, finding literary agents, and working with editors and publishers to get manuscripts published.</P>

<P>WRT 4133 Writing and Publishing Short Fiction	3 Hours</P>

<P>An intensive genre study of the short story in a workshop environment, where students will produce a significant body of their own work. Emphasis is placed on researching potential  markets and submitting work to magazines and journals.</P>

<New_Style_Sheet>YOUTH AND STUDENT MINISTRIES</New_Style_Sheet>

<P>YSM 2111 Youth and Student Ministries Internship I	
	1 Hour</P>

<P>The student is required to participate in practical ministry to youth in a local church, district, national, campus ministry or para-church setting.</P>

<P>YSM 2113 Youth and Student Ministry Leadership	3 Hours</P>

<P>The course will deal with developing a healthy student ministry. Attention will be given to the lifestyle of the leader, establishing a philosophy of youth ministry, developing adult leaders, and cooperation with the ministries of the Assemblies of God District and National Youth Department.</P>

<P>YSM 3111 Youth and Student Ministries Internship II	
	1 Hour</P>

<P>The student works with a qualified mentor, and actively participates in a supervised ministry to youth. The ministry may take place in an approved local church, district, national, campus ministry or para-church setting.</P>

<P>YSM 3113 Bridging Between Children and Youth	3 Hours</P>

<P>A study of principles and methods for effectively helping individuals transition from childhood to adolescence within church ministries. Emphasis will be placed upon cooperative </P>

<P>efforts between children’s and youth pastors to facilitate successful transition. (Same as CFM 3113)</P>

<P>YSM 3123 Contemporary Issues in Youth Culture	3 Hours</P>

<P>A course focusing on the current cultural issues facing adolescents. The course will recognize the need to speak cross-culturally from the adult world to the youth culture. Focus is given to issues such as peer and family relationships, violence, media, adolescent sexuality, and substance abuse. The student will gain the tools to properly understand the current youth culture and how to biblically address the needs of today’s adolescents.</P>

<P>YSM 3331 Youth and Student Ministries Seminar	1 Hour</P>

<P>A seminar in youth ministries introducing to the campus eminent persons with experience in different phases of youth ministries. These guest lecturers function as resource persons whose experience and insights provide stimulation for prospective youth ministers.</P>

<P>YSM 4111 Youth and Student Ministries Internship III	
	1 Hour</P>

<P>The student works with a qualified mentor, and actively participates in a supervised ministry to youth. The ministry must take place in an approved local church.</P>

<P>YSM 4113 Youth and Student Evangelism	3 Hours</P>

<P>The course will study the critical issues of presenting the gospel to a student at his or her level of understanding. Campus ministry, outreaches, personal evangelism, equipping students for evangelism, mission trips and other forms of student evangelism will be discussed. Students will also have the opportunity to participate in outreach efforts.</P>

<P>YSM 4123 Spiritual Formation of Youth	3 Hours</P>

<P>A course designed to teach biblical methods of adolescent spiritual formation. Emphasis will be placed on nurturing spiritual growth, faith development, and organizing and leading small groups of students. The course will also allow students the opportunity to participate in a discipleship experience.</P>

<P>YSM 4133 Strategies for Youth and Student Ministry	
	3 Hours</P>

<P>This course will prepare the student to locate student ministry opportunities with special attention to developing the relationship with the lead pastor. Special attention is given to the distinctive of Pentecostal student ministry, growing a relevant student ministry, working in a small church, and creative communication. (Prerequisite: YSM 2113)</P>
