<P>AAD 5001, 5011, 5021, 5031, 5041.  Internship in Athletic/Activity Administration - 1 hour each semester   </P>

<P>Designed to provide the student with valuable supervised practical experience in athletic/activity supervision and administration.  As part of the degree program students will be required to enroll in the internship each of the semesters they are in the program.  Internships are sequential and students must complete the previous internship before moving to the next.  Internship Fee: $50 per class.   </P>

<P>AAD 5002.  Leadership Philosophy in Athletics - 2 hours  </P>

<P>The goal of this course is to provide the student with an understanding of issues of leadership and to examine applications of leadership principles to the college and high school athletic environment.  The course serves as an overview for interscholastic athletic administration and introduces the philosophy of athletic administration, then focuses on the roles of the NIAAA, the NFHS, the State Athletic/Activity Associations, and the State Athletic Administrator’s Associations.  The NIAAA Leadership Training and Certification Program LTC 501 will be part of this course.  Successful completion of the material will lead toward initial athletic administration certification.  </P>

<P>AAD 5003.  Organization and Administration of Athletics - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course provides an overview of the theoretical foundations and applied areas in administration of athletic programs.  Topics to be covered include: human resources management, facility management, sport marketing, budgeting, fundraising, ethics, and the future of athletics administration.  The course is intended as a basic introduction into the principles of athletic administration.  Successful completion of the material will lead toward initial athletic administration certification. </P>

<P>AAD 5012.  Public Relations in Athletics - 2 hours </P>

<P>This course examines the marketing process in interscholastic athletics.  Through the process, the student will study the theories, research, and development of sport marketing and public relations.  The course focus will be on the implementation of a sport marketing plan.  The course will also look at the communications and public relations activity as it pertains to sport organizations and emphasizes athletic promotion, fundraising, finance, economics, and marketing.   </P>

<P>AAD 5022.  Facility and Game Management - 2 hours </P>

<P>This course focuses on the application of both theory and practice of planning and managing facilities and athletic events in interscholastic athletics.  Upon completion of the course, participants will be able to understand the complexities involved in managing various types of athletic facilities and in planning, production, and evaluation of athletic events.  Topics to be covered in this course include planning and design of athletic facilities, management of athletic facilities, housekeeping and maintenance, event planning, and production.  </P>

<P>AAD 5023.  Legal Issues in Athletics - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course provides in-depth coverage of all aspects of liability for sports injuries and risk management, including the duties imposed on athletic administrators, coaches, athletic trainers, and other athletic personnel.  In addition, fundamentals of an effective risk management program and development of a strategic plan for risk management will be discussed.  This course will also include an extensive study of Title IX and gender equity in athletic programs.  Successful completion of the material will lead toward initial athletic administration certification.   </P>

<P>AAD 5032.  Technology for Athletic Administration - 2 hours </P>

<P>This course introduces advanced features in Word, e-mail applications, EXCEL and PowerPoint to improve the quality and presentation of materials.  Additional areas covered are mail merge using Microsoft Word, and creating charts in Microsoft Excel, Mansker, and other athletic software, and web page development.  The course requires the student to interact with the software in the process of developing presentations and daily administrative reports.   </P>

<P>AAD 5033.  Character Development in Coaching - 3 hours </P>

<P>Character-based educational athletic principles will be used to encourage improved communication between school boards, superintendents, principals, parents and boosters.  This character-based program will help support and embrace the values and views lived daily in the school setting by the student athletes, coaches, athletic department and school faculty.  This course will empower the athletic administrator to motivate the entire community by creating strategies to use in the school community.   </P>

<P>AAD 5043.  Sports Psychology and Stress Management - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course introduces participants to managing human resources in interscholastic athletic organizations, such as athletic departments in middle and high schools.  Various aspects of managerial functions and human behavior in </P>

<P>interscholastic athletic organizations, intervening stress as well as the importance of communication, leadership, negotiation, motivation, and decision making will be addressed.   </P>

<P>AAD 5033.  Diversity in Athletics - 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide an overview of current issues in athletics and to teach learners what diversity is and how it applies to sports in general and more specifically to gender, race, religion and various cultures.  This course will help learners understand the unique challenge for sports leaders to better understand diversity and through this understanding help all participants involved in athletic programs.   </P>

<P>AAD 5063.  Finance &amp; Fundraising in Athletics - 3 hours   </P>

<P>Examination of current fiscal challenges and concerns in athletics.  The knowledge and skill sets of this course serve as a foundation for administration of athletics at various levels.  Topics include financial pressures for sports leaders, fundraising practices, effective marketing, public relation campaigns, fiscal management, accountability and stewardship. Students exercise analytical thinking skills and develop a respect for financial stewardship for successful athletic administration. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>EDUCATION </P>

<P>EDU 5000. Comprehensive Exam Seminar </P>

<P>All M.S. certification students planning to take the Comprehensive Examination will be enrolled in EDU 5000 and are required to complete the seminar and quiz. Once they have completed the quiz, they will receive a letter from the office of graduate studies in education that will serve as their admission into the exam site. Students who do not complete the seminar and quiz will not be admitted into the Comprehensive Exam. The student will not be assessed a fee for EDU 5000. </P>

<P>EDU 5002.  Teaching Social Sciences I -  2 hours </P>

<P>A study of social sciences in the elementary school with emphasis on methods and techniques of presenting important concepts from the several disciplines comprising the social sciences.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, EDU 2121, EDU 2313, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Offered only on the Bolivar campus during the fall and spring semesters. </P>

<P>EDU 5003.  Adapted Physical Education  -  3 hours </P>

<P>Basic terminology, fundamental values, and an overview of special populations and their problems related to physical education.  Surveys of settings, services, resources, and programs in physical education for the handicapped.   </P>

<P>EDU 5022.  Teaching Social Sciences II  - 2 hours </P>

<P>A study of social sciences in elementary/middle schools with emphasis on methods and techniques of presenting concepts from geography and economics.  The focus will be on the five central themes of geography and the four major concepts of economics.  Assessment of social studies skills in geography and economics will be addressed.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, EDU 2313, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. </P>

<P>EDU 5023.  Curriculum Design and Development -  3 hours </P>

<P>The study of principles and theory of curriculum design and procedures for developing curriculum in elementary and secondary education.  Emphasis is on the role of the teacher in curriculum development in the local school.  Review of literature relating to curriculum development and study of current school curriculum guides are an important part of the course. </P>

<P>EDU 5033.  Learners and the Learning Process - 3 hours </P>

<P>The study of how students learn with emphasis on current theories of learning, the relationship between learning and development, the characteristics of learners and effective methods for measuring learning.  The overarching purpose of the course is to enhance endeavors of teachers to improve student learning. Prerequisite: EDU 2113 or hold teaching certificate. </P>

<P>EDU 5043. Brain-Based Teaching and Learning for Special Needs Students - 3 hours </P>

<P>Examination of how to address the unique learning problems of students with special needs, with a focus on insights gained from research on the function of the human brain.  Quality learning experiences will be designed based on knowledge acquisition and learning modalities of students.  Strategies will be discussed/developed to create learning environments for special needs students.   </P>

<P>EDU 5053. Philosophies of Education - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course provides an in-depth examination of major philosophies of education, and their relation to teaching practice, methods, curriculum, and educational administration. Philosophies examined include idealism, perennialism, pragmatism, existentialism, romanticism, hermeneutics and perspectivism. </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>EDU 5063.  Human Growth and Development - 3 hours  </P>

<P>A &quot;Life-Span&quot; study of human growth and developmental processes including physiological, psychological and sociological influences and effects.  Students receiving credit for this course cannot receive credit for both PSY 3053 and PSY 4033. Prerequisites: PSY 1013 or EDU 2113. </P>

<P>EDU 5073.  Master’s Capstone - 3 hours </P>

<P>Students will demonstrate in writing and through performance assessment how knowledge gained in their MS in Education program has impacted the teaching and learning process in their classroom, department and/or building.  Prerequisites for this course are EDU 5023, EDU 5033, and EDU 5083. </P>

<P>EDU 5083.  Educational Research - 3 hours </P>

<P>Concepts of research design, methodology, sampling techniques, internal and external validity, the scientific method in educational problem solving, and statistical treatment.  Included are assumptions underlying the use of statistical tests, selection of appropriate statistical techniques, and the interpretation of the results of the analysis.  Critical analysis and evaluation of published educational research studies and the writing of educational proposals are major components. </P>

<P>EDU 5093.  Master's Project - 3 hours </P>

<P>The Master's Research Project consists of a field based project centering upon a practical problem of special interest to the student.  The student will identify the problem and develop a proposed plan, complete the project under supervision (usually in one's place of work), and develop a comprehensive report.  The written report will be bound and placed in the Hutchens Library.  Prerequisite:  EDU 5083. </P>

<P>EDU 5103.  Cooperative Learning - 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course will provide basic information concerning the history, development, strategy, and forms of cooperative learning. Students will develop strategies that can be used in their respective disciplines. </P>

<P>EDU 5112.  Teaching Writing - 2 hours </P>

<P>This course is designed to stress the teacher's role in the writing process and introduce writing activities that may be implemented in the classroom for different areas of the curriculum.  A variety of instructional approaches to teaching middle school students to write will be addressed.  The course will focus on writing as process and product.  Preservice teachers will experience assessing students' writing.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, 2141, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Must be taken as part of the professional block semester unless permission is granted by the Director of Teacher Education or the Coordinator of Clinical Experiences for it to be taken in another semester.  Offered only on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5114.  Teaching Reading/Language Arts I - 4 hours </P>

<P>Explores the rationale for and methods of integrating the teaching of the language arts (reading, writing, speaking, listening, viewing, and visually representing) in today's elementary classroom.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2121, 2313, 2343, 2353, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.   </P>

<P>EDU 5123.  Teaching in the 21st Century - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course addresses possible approaches/solutions to critical issues facing educators in the future. Many subjects will be identified and discussed concerning issues facing teachers in the 21st century.  </P>

<P>EDU 5124.  Teaching Reading/Language Arts II - 4 hours </P>

<P>Emphasizes application of the principles of integrated language arts teaching throughout the curriculum.  Preservice teachers will plan instruction and prepare materials to be used to foster developmental and functional reading strategies which enable students to use reading as a tool to learn.  Preservice teachers will also assess and evaluate students with diverse needs.  Prerequisites:  EDU 2113, 2121, 2313, 2343, 2353, and 3.00 GPA. </P>

<P>EDU 5133.  Developing Positive Attitudes &amp; Motivation in Students - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will examine topics and strategies to create a more positive classroom. All types of motivational strategies will be applied to the classroom teachers’ perspective. Students will share viewpoints on topics such as humor in the classroom, student-centered learning, motivational techniques, and self-motivation.  </P>

<P>EDU 5143.  Integrating Art, Music and Physical Education into the Classroom - 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed to enable the student to integrate art, music and physical education into the classroom.  Prerequisites:  EDU 2113, 2121, 2313, 2343, 2353, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. </P>

<P>EDU 5162.  Teaching Integrated Math - 2 hours </P>

<P>Study of methods of teaching math in the elementary/middle school and of integrating mathematics in other content areas, particularly science, in ways that are developmentally appropriate and are reflective of the NCTM standards.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2121, 2313, 2343, 2353, 3.00 GPA, two (2) college level math courses above MAT 0123, two (2) science courses   one (1) in a biological science (BIO) with a lab and one (1) in a physical science   Chemistry (CHE), Earth Science or Introduction to Physical Science, etc. (PHS), or Physics (PHY)   with a lab and Teacher Education requirements.   </P>

<P>EDU 5173.  Learning Styles - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course is based on the recognition that there are distinct personality characteristics that are intrinsic to an individual’s method of learning. Personalities are identified and a climate is created where communication is developed to bring about an increase in a student’s sense of dignity, respect, worthiness, and esteem.  </P>

<P>EDU 5182.  Teaching Integrated Science - 2 hours </P>

<P>Study of methods of teaching and integrating science in the elementary/middle schools with a particular emphasis on process inquiry skills.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2121, 2313, 2343, 2353, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. </P>

<P>EDU 5183.   Brain Based Teaching and Learning - 3 hours </P>

<P>Students will examine how the brain processes information/learns, including the role of emotions and the aspect of multiple intelligence. Quality learning experiences will be designed based on knowledge acquisition and learning modalities of students. Strategies will be discussed/developed to create learning environments that facilitate the construction of knowledge and retention of information. </P>

<P>EDU 5203.  Curriculum Methods in Early Childhood Education - 3 hours </P>

<P>Exploration of the subject of early childhood programming with a focus on the importance of preparing materials and learning techniques to advance the physical, emotional, and cognitive development of young children.  Emphasis is on adapting materials and methods to the needs of young children.  Offered only on the Bolivar campus. </P>

<P>EDU 5213. Current Issues in Educational Technology - 3 hours </P>

<P>Instructional technology is at the center of many of both the opportunities and the controversies in education and training today. Using a problem-based learning instructional strategy, this course helps students examine many of the issues at the forefront of our field, from what instructional technology is through designing instruction to what students might find on the Internet. The set of issues is always shifting as the field grows and changes. The course is meant for those nearing the completion of their degree, not for beginners. </P>

<P>EDU 5223.  Issues and Trends in Early Childhood Education - 3 hours </P>

<P>Current trends and issues in early childhood education with emphasis on the study of research and recent findings in the development, modification and implementation of programs for young children. </P>

<P>EDU 5233.  Literature for the Young Child - 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed to acquaint the student with exemplary literature for the young child and to develop competency in the use of effective and sound methods for using books to enrich the lives of young children. </P>

<P>EDU 5243.  Creative Writing in Secondary Classrooms - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will focus on learning how to create and maintain an exciting and motivating environment for creative writing in the classroom.  </P>

<P>EDU 5253.  Educational Grant Writing - 3 hours </P>

<P>Individuals enrolled in this course will become familiar with grant writing procedures employed in the basic fill in the blank type grants as well as the procedures and formats utilized in the more complex grants. </P>

<P>EDU 5263.  Literature Based Classrooms - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will focus on the effective use of literature in all content areas throughout the curriculum. Special attention will be given to American literature as a tool to motivate students into research and critical thinking skills. This course is designed for teachers K-12. Balanced literacy, guided reading and literature circles will be a focus of this course. </P>

<P>EDU 5273.  Teaching Reading Comprehension - 3 hours </P>

<P>Strategies for improving decoding and comprehension skills through individual leaning styles of students and teacher. Emphasis will be upon how to diagnose and remedy common reading deficiencies, how to assess level of performance and to utilize effective instructional strategies and how to determine students’ learning styles in order to help them attain better comprehension. </P>

<P>EDU 5283. Teaching Students To Study Smarter, Not Harder - 3 hours </P>

<P>The course focuses on how to teach students to learn. Study skills will be taught that incorporate preferred learning styles, memory strategies, concentration and listening skills, note-taking, textbook mastery, test-taking, time management, and motivation strategies. </P>

<P>EDU 5293.  Creating Lifetime Writers - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will focus on learning how to create and maintain an exciting and motivating environment for creative writing in the classroom. </P>

<P>EDU 5313. Clinical Field Study - 3 hours </P>

<P>The completed field study will require the student to chair a committee designed to address one goal of their district/building strategic plan from development to completion. The study may be done in cooperation with a public or private school district or appropriate agency. In order to complete this task the student must (1) have a comprehensive review of the literature pertaining to this goal, (2) strategic plan included time line, budget, person(s) </P>

<P>responsible, resources needed to achieve the goal, (3) a formal presentation to the board of education outlining the approach to achieving the desired outcomes, (4) formal presentation to the board of education summarizing the committees activities and accomplishments as they relate to the achievement of the district/building goal. </P>

<P>EDU 5323. Improving Instruction - 3 hours </P>

<P>The course will provide practical field-tested teaching strategies designed to impact the teaching and learning process at the classroom and building level. Students will be exposed to and apply current theory and practices designed to improve classroom instruction. </P>

<P>EDU 5333.  Principles and Methods of Secondary School - 3 hours </P>

<P>Emphasis on the basic teaching methods, the teaching of critical thinking skills, analysis of various teaching models, analysis of learners and the learning process, and development of communication skills.  EDU 5333 must be taken at SBU.  A Field Based Internship must be taken concurrently.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2141, 2313, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Offered only on the Bolivar campus during the fall and spring semesters. </P>

<P>EDU 5343. The Leadership Brain - How Classroom Teachers Lead Effectively - 3 hours </P>

<P>Students will examine how brain-compatible practices can sustain effective teaching and learning.  Making use of the latest cognitive neuroscience insights about how the brain interacts with the learning environment will provide a basis for understanding: learning differences, brain-compatible curriculum and assessment, higher-order thinking, the nature of creativity, ethical and spiritual leadership, and the role of thinking habits on learning.  The course will also address initiating and leading productive school change.   </P>

<P>EDU 5353.  Reading Miscue Analysis - 3 hours </P>

<P>The study of a procedure based upon whole language and psycholinguistic theory that enables the teacher to investigate and understand the reading of an individual reader, to develop an understanding of how readers transact with text to build comprehension, and to use this procedure as a base for constructing and implementing an individual developmental or remedial plan.  Offered only on the Bolivar campus. </P>

<P>EDU 5373.  Issues and Trends in Reading Instruction - 3 hours </P>

<P>An intensive analysis of reading problems from the standpoint of current development and remedial methodologies.  Offered only on the Bolivar campus. </P>

<P>EDU 5383.  Supervision of Instruction in Reading - 3 hours </P>

<P>The supervisory responsibilities and problems concerned with reading, including the building of reading programs appropriate for a school population and community, utilizing appropriate research in the operation of a quality reading program, using supervisory techniques appropriate to the task, and serving as a leader in the change process of a school reading program.  Offered only on the Bolivar campus. </P>

<P>EDU 5413.  Internet Applications for Teachers - 3 hours </P>

<P>An introduction to the variety of educational resources on the Internet and the essential skills of use of Internet e-mail, FTP, Telnet, and World Wide Web through Netscape. Basic computer skills are required. Students will print, save to disk, and create portfolios that can be used in their curriculum.  </P>

<P>EDU 5423.  Computer Applications in Education - 3 hours </P>

<P>Introduces the role of computers in education, including classroom instruction, administration, and counseling.  Emphasizes computer assisted instruction, computer managed instructional techniques, and administrative uses.  Includes practical experience in software development for educational applications. Lab fee $15. </P>

<P>EDU 5433.  Blogs, Podcasts, Wikis &amp; Web Page Application for Teachers - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course is designed for educators who are interested in creating and maintaining blogs, podcasts, Wikis, and web pages to enhance internal and external communication and the teaching and learning process.  Participants will learn how to create a podcast as well as how to create and maintain a Wiki, blog, and web page.    </P>

<P>EDU 5463.  Middle School Philosophy and Organization - 3 hours </P>

<P>A focus on the historical and philosophical foundations of the traditional junior high and subsequent middle school movement emphasizing a connection between practice and  research.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2131, 2313, and 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5473.  Psychology of the Middle School Student - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course offers a broad overview of the history of young adolescent psychology, its advocates, researchers, and its implications for middle level educational practices.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2131, 2313, 2463, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5493.  Middle School Curriculum - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course offers an in-depth study of curriculum development and instructional strategies targeting the young adolescent.  As a result of this course, students will develop pedagogical practices that meet the vast physical, emotional, social, intellectual, and affective developmental needs of young adolescents.  A Field Based Internship </P>

<P>must be taken concurrently.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2131, 2313, 2463, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the spring semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5502. Methods of Teaching Theatre – 2 hours  </P>

<P>An introduction to methods of teaching theatre in the secondary school.  Topics include curriculum development; teaching strategies; and assessment.  Additionally, this course addresses strategies for organizing and implementing a production schedule.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2141, 2313 and 3.00 GPA </P>

<P>EDU 5503.  Organization and Administration of Physical Education - 3 hours </P>

<P>Advanced organization and management of physical education and interscholastic athletic programs.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5512.  Methods of Teaching Art, K 12 - 2 hours </P>

<P>Understanding motivation, materials and techniques in school art programs.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience I, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Offered only on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5513.  Methods of Teaching Mathematics in the Middle and Secondary Schools - 3 hours </P>

<P>Theory and application of current practices in teaching mathematics in middle and secondary schools.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience I, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the spring semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5522.  Methods of Teaching Science in the Middle and Secondary Schools - 2 hours </P>

<P>Course will provide practical methods for the prospective teacher to use for the instruction of middle and secondary school students in such areas as laboratory safety, investigative and questioning skills.  Course activities will include inquiry teaching, use of demonstrations in teaching, budgeting and supply ordering, science fairs and projects, and the use of the computer in the science classroom.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience I, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5523.  Methods of Teaching Business Subjects in the Secondary School - 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed to analyze instructional techniques and procedures utilized in teaching business subjects.  Special attention given to objectives, subject matter content, instructional materials, class activities and methods of evaluating in typewriting, accounting, shorthand, office practice, and general business.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, and Teacher Education requirements. Only offered on the Bolivar campus on sufficient demand. </P>

<P>EDU 5533.  Methods of Teaching Health and Physical Education, 5-12 - 3 hours </P>

<P>Teaching methods, selection of activities, program planning, emphasis on development of a progressive curriculum (restricted to health and physical education majors and minors).  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience I, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5542.  Methods of Teaching Social Studies in the Middle and Secondary Schools - 2 hours </P>

<P>Exploration of basic concepts within each of the social sciences and possible teaching methods.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience I, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the spring semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5543.  Methods of Teaching Writing in the Secondary School - 3 hours </P>

<P>Theory and application in the teaching of writing and grammar in secondary schools with emphasis on the writing process.  A requirement for secondary English majors.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience I, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the spring semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5552.  Methods of Teaching Speech in the Middle  and Secondary Schools - 2 hours </P>

<P>Emphasis on principles, techniques and problems that are unique in teaching speech.  Unit and course plans are developed for all areas of speech.  Attention is given to directing forensics and dramatic activities.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience I, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester. </P>

<P>EDU 5553. Measurement and Evaluation in Physical Education - 3 hours </P>

<P>A course to acquaint students with various evaluation methods in physical education. Practice is given to administering tests and interpreting results with appropriate statistical procedures. </P>

<P>EDU 5562.  Methods of Teaching Instrumental Music in the Middle and Secondary Schools - 2 hours </P>

<P>Study of philosophy of music education, administrative and teaching techniques, and materials for teaching instrumental music in the middle and secondary schools.  Music majors and minors only.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, MUS 1621, MUS 1623, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester (even years). </P>

<P>EDU 5563.  Methods of Teaching Foreign Language - 3 hours </P>

<P>Study of methods of teaching modern languages in public school.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience I, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus on sufficient demand.  </P>

<P>EDU 5573.  Methods of Teaching Vocal Music in the Middle and Secondary Schools - 3 hours </P>

<P>Study of philosophy of music education, administrative and teaching techniques, and materials for teaching vocal music in middle and secondary schools.  Music majors and minors only.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2141, 2313, MUS 1621, MUS 1623, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall semester (odd years). </P>

<P>EDU 5583.  Character Education - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will provide a knowledge and background of Character Education. We will explore the development of good. Character building skills, such as respect, responsibility, and work ethic will be addressed. Students will discuss methods of initiating a Character Education program into a school system as well as incorporating character skills into curriculum. </P>

<P>EDU 5593.  Spiritual Issues in Public Schools - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course is designed to help teachers plan curriculum in ways that stay true to one’s faith and helps teach Christian values in a multicultural community. Students will review which laws determine the religious rights of students and teachers in public schools and how to apply these laws to real situations in the classroom.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, Field Experience 1, EDU 2313, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. </P>

<P>EDU 5603.  Issues and Trends in Education - 3 hours </P>

<P>This class is focused on developments, trends and issues in education with emphasis on relating current research to contemporary educational practice. Legal issues will be addressed.  </P>

<P>EDU 5613.  Teaching Reading in the Content Areas - 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed to assist middle school/junior high and/or secondary teachers in the use of functional reading strategies which enable students to use reading as a tool to learn in various content areas.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2131, 2313, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall and spring semesters. </P>

<P>EDU 5623. Working With At-Risk Students - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course examines why significant numbers of students fail to achieve their academic potential. Principles of effective thinking skills programs are examined. </P>

<P>EDU 5643. Sport and Physical Education in American Society - 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of the place of sports and physical activity in American society. Principles, historical events and current status of sports and physical activity will be studied. </P>

<P>EDU 5653.  Counseling for the Classroom Teacher - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will emphasize the application of counseling, guidance, and counseling psychology principles in the classroom. Teachers will improve upon their skill for dealing with students’ academic, personal, and social problems.  </P>

<P>EDU 5663.  Child Abuse and Neglect - 3 hours </P>

<P> This course is designed to acquaint the student with child abuse and neglect, causes, treatment and prevention.  </P>

<P>EDU 5673.  Teaching Critical Thinking Skills - 3 hours </P>

<P>In this course students will learn to think about their thinking and understand the ways people think. Students will define critical thinking, select suitable thinking outcomes for their lessons and remodel lesson plans to help their own students engage in higher order thinking.  </P>

<P>EDU 5683.  Effective Inclusion Practices - 3 hours </P>

<P>Students will investigate the Individuals With Disabilities Education Act and its implications for teachers. Special placement, the continuum of service models, and the areas of exceptionality will be defined. Modifications required in the regular classroom for implementation of IEP’s will be explored.  </P>

<P>EDU 5693.  Understanding Human Addictions - 3 hours </P>

<P>The intent of this course is to enable educators to further their understanding of the issues involving drugs, to further develop a personal philosophy regarding drug issues based on this knowledge and to help the educator utilize this knowledge and philosophy into their daily teaching.  </P>

<P>EDU 5703. Physiology of Exercise - 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of the effects of exercise on the organs and systems of the body; special emphasis on the cardio-respiratory system. Course fee $12. </P>

<P>EDU 5713.  Current Problems in Physical Education -3 hours </P>

<P>Recognizing, classifying, and reporting problems in physical education.  Studying techniques and methods of solving problems.  Current issues and problems in the field of physical education are studied.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus. </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>EDU 5733.  Adolescent Development - 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of the development processes of the adolescent, beginning at puberty and continuing through the late adolescence. Prerequisites: EDU 2113, Field Experience 1, EDU 2313, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. </P>

<P>EDU 5753.  Web Tools, Design and Applications - 3 hours   </P>

<P>This course focuses on the role of web tools in education, including classroom instruction, administration, and communication. Emphasis is placed on computerized instruction and computer-managed instructional techniques  including Web Design. Content includes practical experience in software development for educational applications.  </P>

<P>EDU 5773.  Leadership Styles in the Media – 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed to have students observe and analyze a variety of leadership styles as presented in visual and print media. Students will apply this knowledge to better understand their personal leadership style as well as the style(s) of those they work with. Through this analysis students will better understand how the style of leadership impacts change, motivation and followership. </P>

<P>EDU 5783. Developing Mathematical Understanding – 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed for classroom k-12 teachers to develop a better understanding of how students learn math. This knowledge will be acquired through the development and application of classroom activities. Students will leave with hands on application of course concepts.   </P>

<P>EDU 5793. Delinquent Behaviors K-12 – 3 hours                                                                                                            </P>

<P>An extensive view of delinquent behaviors from the teacher/counselor viewpoint.  Identification skills and prevention methods will be discussed.   </P>

<P>EDU 5803. Essentials in Writing – 3 hours  </P>

<P>Twelve writing essentials for grades K-12 will be explored in this course.  Educators will become more knowledgeable  about how to teach writing by building on best practices and effective writing strategies. </P>

<P>EDU 5823.  Integrating Technology Into the Classroom - 3 hours </P>

<P>The course focuses on knowledge and skills which:  (1) make a person computer literate, (2) enable one to use computers in a variety of personal applications, (3) equip a person to use computers in teaching and learning, and (4) enable one to make effective use of a wide variety of media and technological systems in teaching.  Prerequisites: CIS 1103, EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience 1, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Designed for MS Certification Students only.  Lab fee $20. </P>

<P>EDU 5832.  Assessment and Evaluation of Learners - 2 hours </P>

<P>Study of history of measurement, statistical terms and processes used in education, principles of constructing teacher made tests, and examination of various testing programs for public school systems.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience 1, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Must be taken as part of the professional block semester unless permission is granted by the Director of Teacher Education or the Coordinator of Clinical Experiences for it to be taken in another semester.  Only offered on the Bolivar campus during the fall and spring semesters. </P>

<P>EDU 5833.  Behavior and Classroom Management - 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed to introduce the student to procedures for managing the classroom, including organization, administration, and communication.  Methods of discipline and behavior management are explored for various levels of teaching, and with individuals and small and large groups under varying conditions.  The development of knowledge and attitudes that will enhance teachers' ability to develop pupil self-esteem and confidence are addressed.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Only offered for middle school, junior high, and/or secondary teachers on the Bolivar campus during the fall and spring semesters. </P>

<P>EDU 5842.  Teaching Diverse Learners - 2 hours </P>

<P>Mentally, emotionally, and physically exceptional children are studied.  Diagnosis and methods of teaching gifted, mentally retarded, visual and sound impaired, learning disabled, physically handicapped children, and children with communication and behavior problems are included.  Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2313, Field Experience 1, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements.  Must be taken as part of the professional block semester unless permission is granted by the Director of Teacher Education or the Coordinator of Clinical Experiences for it to be taken in another semester.   </P>

<P>EDU 5853.  Classroom Management - 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of methods of discipline and behavior management in the classroom and of procedures for managing the classroom, including organization, administration, scheduling, record keeping and communication with administration and parents.  Various models and systems are explored. Students will focus on aspects of classroom discipline and behavior management unique to their level of preparation. Prerequisites: EDU 2113, 2121, 2313, 2343, 2353, 3.00 GPA, and Teacher Education requirements. Offered for elementary education teachers during the fall and spring semesters. </P>

<P>EDU 5863.  Schools By Design - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course offers a broad overview of the ideas, programs, strategies, research and results for school improvement. The course has two major themes: (1) building community relations for school change and (2) creating schools designed around the best practices.  </P>

<P>EDU 5873.  Integrating Technology into K-12 Classrooms - 3 hours </P>

<P>This survey course will introduce experienced educators to educational technology. Topics covered in this course will be areas that impact or have the potential to impact educators in the classroom. Special emphasis will be on constructing relevant and appropriate instructional environments. </P>

<P>EDU 5883.  The School &amp; Community Relations - 3 hours </P>

<P>This class will look at various media and at research leading to effective and responsive communications to meet the needs of the public. Participants will formulate, develop and implement a procedure for positive school and community relations in public education.  </P>

<P>EDU 5893.  School Law for Teachers - 3 hours </P>

<P>The study of Missouri and federal statutes, legal opinions and court decisions as applied to education is the focus of this course. Topics such as non-renewal and dismissal of teachers and collective bargaining will be discussed.  </P>

<P>EDU 5903. Professional Learning Communities – 3 hours  </P>

<P>Students will learn the parameters of a professional learning community, including the development of a focus, the skills of developing a relationship with teachers as a facilitator, the implementation of strategies for effective group work, and the ability to clearly communicate and guide the discussion process. All knowledge and skills will be directed toward a better understanding and support for the teaching/learning process.   </P>

<P>EDU 591(1-3).  Workshop - 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Workshops focusing on practical classroom application of the subject addressed are offered in areas of major interest and need by students.  Some of the workshops that have been offered are: Basic DOS and Windows in the Classroom; Classroom Learning Centers; Computer Graphics for the Classroom; Cooperative Learning; Creative Writing; Displays for Learning; Internet in the School; Using Hypercard, CD ROM and Interactive Video; Using TV in Teaching; Whole Language; Working with the At Risk Student; Working with the Aggressive Student. </P>

<P>EDU 593(1-3).  Readings - 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Readings may be developed in reference to an area of major interest and need of an individual student.  The required reading and reporting are specified in writing with signatures of the student and instructor indicating agreement.   </P>

<P>EDU 595(1-3).  Special Topics - 1-3 hours </P>

<P>A special topic may be offered which focuses upon a subject of major interest and need by a group of students.  Topic courses usually focus upon areas not covered by regular courses in the graduate curriculum.   Among topics that have been offered are: Addressing the Needs of the Mainstreamed Child; Behavior Modification in the Classroom; Counseling for the Classroom Teacher; Instructional Improvement in the Secondary School; Movement Education; Parent Education; Teaching through Educational Tours. </P>

<P>EDU 596(1-3).  Physical Education Seminar - 1-3 hours </P>

<P>A seminar may be offered relative to a subject of major interest and need by a group of students.  Seminars usually focus at advanced levels on specific subjects not covered in depth in the regular graduate curriculum.  Among seminars that have been offered are: Issues and Trends in Education; Seminar in Educational Change; Seminar in Middle School Education. </P>

<P>EDU 597(1-3).  Symposium - 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Symposium credit may be earned by special approval of the advisor, the graduate faculty member who is to supervise the experience and the Office of Graduate Studies.  Symposium credit is usually associated with participation to a significant degree in a professional development conference, workshop, or similar program sponsored by an organization not associated with the University.   </P>

<P>EDU 598(1-3).  Internship/Practicum - 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Planned and supervised work experience related to the student's graduate study, usually in an elementary or secondary school setting.  Internships and practicums may be taken only with advanced planning and approvals involving the supervising graduate faculty member, the department in which the credit is earned, and the Office of Graduate Studies.  No more than four hours of credit from internships and practicums may normally be applied toward completion of the master's degree. </P>

<P>EDU 599(1-3).  Independent Study - 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Directed study by an individual student of an area not covered in the regular graduate curriculum.  Independent study may be taken only by advance approval of the supervising graduate faculty member, the department chair, and the Office of Graduate Studies. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>EDU 6013.  Analyzing and Amending Reading Problems - 3 hours  </P>

<P>In this course, students will learn about instructional techniques, reading assessments, diagnostic evaluations, and learning materials specifically designed to detect and correct reading difficulties. Students will administer and interpret a variety of reading assessments in order to diagnose students’ difficulties and plan remediation lessons and activities. Students will practice test administration and diagnosis with students who are struggling with literacy development, demonstrating the ethics of testing procedures and reporting. </P>

<P>EDU 6043.  Learner Development and the Classroom - 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course is concerned with the psychological development of children and adolescents during the school age years. The course will focus primarily on the cognitive, physical, social, personal and moral development of children and adolescents and the impact of these developmental areas on learning and behavior in the school classroom. </P>

<P>EDU 6063.  Incorporating Differentiated Instruction into the Classroom – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This class will provide teachers with strategies to successfully differentiate instructions by differentiating the content, process, product or making accommodations.  Teachers will use curriculum materials to create lessons using a variety of differentiation strategies to help all students achieve the curricular goals.  Strategies will include tiered assignments, acceleration and deceleration, and flexible grouping from a K-12 perspective in reading, math, science, social students and specials. </P>

<P>EDU 6073.  Instructional Strategies That Work – 3 hours   </P>

<P>Based on the works of Robert Marzano, This course is designed to give students and insightful look at teaching strategies that have been proven successful. Students will be exposed to and apply current theory and practices designed to improve classroom instruction.  </P>

<P>EDU 6083.  Bullying – 3 hours </P>

<P>Recognizing, identifying, and dealing with bullying in public schools is critical to a safe learning environment.  This course will help provide the skills needed to deal with bully situations in the classroom, on the playground, and before/after school hours.  Teachers are one of the critical elements in stopping this behavior that can lead to violent situations.   </P>

<P>EDU 6093.  K-12 Mental Health Issues – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course explores the biological, emotional, and physiological components of predominant mental health issues affecting school age students. Common characteristics of mental health issues and prevalent concomitant factors will be identified. Classroom management and practical application strategies to address student needs will be presented.  </P>

<P>EDU 6103.  Teaching Strategies That Go Beyond Surface Learning – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will focus on the effective use of Webb’s Depth of Knowledge (DOK) model.  Special Attention will be given to align assessment and instruction through lesson planning using the DOK model.  Educators will leave with a greater understanding of the DOK model as it relates to Bloom’s Taxonomy.   </P>

<P>EDU 6113.  Sixty Strategies to Improve Test Scores – 3 hours </P>

<P>Learn multiple strategies that can be used every day in any classroom that will help teachers improve scores in all high stakes testing.  </P>

<P>EDU 6123.  What Great Teachers Do – 3 hours   </P>

<P>Based on the work of Todd Whitaker this course will examine beliefs, behaviors, and attitudes that make great teachers. Practical ideas will be presented to help teachers increase student performance and make a greater impact in their schools. In addition to the course text, supplemental resources will reinforce the learning and provide both a practical and scholarly perspective.  </P>

<P>EDU 6133.  SMART boards and Technology in the Classroom – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This class is an introduction on using a SMART board.  Participants will create lessons using SMART Notebook 10 and the interactive tools featured on a SMART board.  Participants will also create a wiki that can be used as a classroom website that will host the SMART Notebook lessons.  Wikis also allow teachers to easily add student websites, upload files for use in the classroom and imbed videos.  Technology knowledge for this class is basic.  </P>

<P>EDU 6143.  Dealing with Difficult Students – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course will examine practical strategies for dealing with challenging students in the classroom. Educators will learn how to develop healthy relationships with all students, how to eliminate or minimize problem behaviors, and how to respond to any situation that may occur in the classroom.  </P>

<P>EDU 6153.  Teaching Children of Poverty – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will provide and extensive review of poverty in American and the ramifications it has on public schools.  Topics will range from academic achievement to delinquent behaviors.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>EDU 6163.  Habits of the Heart for Teachers – 3 hours </P>

<P>The Habits of the Heart, Nurturing Attitude, Responsibility, Dependability, Friendship, Brotherhood, High Expectations, Courage, and Hope are the building blocks toward a tradition of excellence. In an environment built around these habits, students can become the best and brightest people their skills and talents permit.   </P>

<P>EDU 6173.  Brain Based Teaching and Learning for Special Needs Students – 3 hours </P>

<P>Examination of how to address the unique learning problems of students with special needs, with a focus on insights gained from research on the function of the human brain. Quality learning experiences will be designed based on knowledge acquisition and learning modalities of students. Strategies will be discussed/developed to create learning environments for special needs students.  </P>

<P>EDU 6183.  Introduction to RtI  – 3 hours </P>

<P>Response to Intervention (RtI) is a system for identification and remediation of learning deficits; specifically in reading, writing, math and behavior. This course will introduce multi-tiered intervention strategies with hands-on  </P>

<P>EDU 6193.  Developing Student Capabilities – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will examine the perceptions and skills necessary for students to become successful in the classroom as well as in life. Through the process of this course, it will become evident that the development of these skills and perceptions is critical to the development of capable people.  </P>

<P>EDU 6203.  Servant Leadership Strategies for Teachers – 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed for all teachers who are committed to their students’ learning and to their own personal </P>

<P>development. Developing the servant leader approach is necessary for an educational community to energize </P>

<P>students and improve achievement..  </P>

<P>EDU 6253.  Planning for Literacy Instruction  – 3 hours </P>

<P>Elementary educators will explore current instructional practices for reading instruction in this book study of Diller’s text, Making the Most of Small Groups. Practical tips, sample lessons, and templates will be provided along with an opportunity to develop literacy materials for classroom use.   </P>

<P>EDU 6223.  Using Mentor Texts to Guide Literacy Instruction – 3 hours </P>

<P>Educators will have an opportunity to examine strategic instruction that will strengthen students’ reading and writing abilities while fostering enjoyment of children’s literature. K-8 educators will leave the course with a resource guide of annotated bibliographies and lesson materials to put into immediate use.   </P>

<P>EDU 6233.  Crafting Writers Through Literature – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide clear insight into recognizing and teaching qualities of good writing through children’s literature. Educators will explore how students can become enthusiastic, confident writers using literature as the foundation in all writing modes.  </P>

<P>EDU 6243.  Essentials in Reading – 3 hours </P>

<P>Reading essentials for grades K-12 will be explored in this course. Teachers will become more knowledgeable about teaching reading by building on best practices and effective strategies.  </P>

<P>EDU 6263.  Principles of Coaching – 3 hours </P>

<P>The study of how the coaching process enhances the effectiveness and efficacy of teachers in classroom work and collaboration with peers. Examples of various coaching processes will be explored through declarative and procedural knowledge. The purpose of this course is to increase the effectiveness of teachers as leaders within a school setting through awareness and proficiency in coaching. </P>

<P>EDU 6273.  Effective Communication – 3 hours </P>

<P>Students will develop an understanding of communication strategies that promote self-directedness and come from a growth mindset. This class will teach skills in working with colleagues in group settings, as well as with administrators, parents and students.  Attention will be given to effective feedback that promotes teacher growth resulting in increased student learning. </P>

<P>EDU 6293. Assessment and Data Collection – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will examine the use of assessment data within the classroom as a means of conducting contextually based research that will improve the teaching/learning process. Students will understand why data influence school improvement, what types of data are critical in making a difference, and how the use of data can improve student learning. Students will develop a perspective that looks beyond the single classroom through an inquiry stance, and will learn how to clearly communicate findings to the larger school setting. </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>EDUCATIONAL ADMINISTRATION </P>

<P>EAD 6001.  Introduction to Technology for School Administrators - 1 hour </P>

<P>Introduction to technology is an online course designed to introduce prospective administrators to the technology standards for school administrators, review the process for developing a building level technology plan and review sources of funding for technology.  Additionally students will be introduced to the portfolio component of Bb so they may begin the process of developing their online administrative portfolio. </P>

<P>EAD 6002.  Foundations of Educational Administration - 2 hours </P>

<P>Designed to provide an overview of the essential elements of organizations and management theory for the student entering the program.  Administration history, basic theories, and major areas of responsibility in school administration will be discussed. </P>

<P>EAD 6014.  School Administration - 4 hours </P>

<P>Designed as a course in building level K-12 administration to prepare prospective school administrators in the areas of instructional leadership, decision-making and problem solving.  School improvement, building management and basic personnel and program management are also part of this course. </P>

<P>EAD 6024.  School Curriculum - 4 hours </P>

<P>Designed to provide K-12 administrators principles and theory of curriculum design and procedures for developing curriculum in the K-12 setting.  Emphasis is placed on the role of the teacher and the administrator in curriculum development and evaluation. </P>

<P>EAD 6053.  School Supervision - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will focus on the problems, processes and techniques in the evaluation, supervision and improvement of instructional programs.  Focus will be placed upon leadership roles necessary for creating a supportive climate for change.  </P>

<P>EAD 6063/6073. Internship - 3 hours (each) </P>

<P>Practical experience intended to augment classroom instruction under the supervision of a practicing administrator and a university supervisor.  Foundations of Educational Administration (EAD 6002), School Supervision (EAD 6053), School Administration (EAD 6014), School Curriculum (EAD 6024) and admission to the program are prerequisites for the internship.  Internship Fee:  $50. </P>

<P>EAD 6083.  Essentials in School Law, Finance and Buildings - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course is designed to prepare future building level administrators by studying laws and current legislation affecting public and private schools.  It will also view school revenue sources, expenditure practices and management responsibilities as they relate to the building budget.  Finally students will examine problems in building planning and plant utilization. </P>

<P>EAD 6093. Administration of Special Programs - 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed to prepare principals for their responsibilities related to the supervision of special education programs.  The legal basis for special education, legal concern, the budget, management and supervision will be emphasized.  </P>

<P>EAD 6113.  Administrative Communication, Innovation and Management - 3 hours </P>

<P>Intensive examination of the school and its environment.  Emphasis is placed on  interacting with internal and external publics.  </P>

<P>EAD 6143.   Educational Organizations, Leadership and Change - 3 hours  </P>

<P>Designed to help students develop a diverse set of perspectives for analyzing organizations and for taking effective leadership in them.  The focus of the course will be to understand how organizations work and what to do to make them better through organizational change, to allow students to look at their own ideas of leadership and to assess themselves on the skills they will need to be effective leaders, and to respond to emerging challenges in today’s schools. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>EDUCATIONAL SPECIALIST </P>

<P>EAD 7000. Continuous Enrollment </P>

<P>As needed to complete the field study.  Students will be charged for one credit hour at the specialist rate each semester the research paper is not completed. Students not enrolled in any specialist course work will not be charged the one credit hour. No credit is given for EAD 7000.  Course fee $215. </P>

<P>EAD 7002. Educational Technology - 2 hours  </P>

<P>Hands on application of technology used in day-to-day functions of the superintendent as well as tools used for research in the field of education.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>EAD 7003. School District Administration - 3 hours </P>

<P>Prepare prospective superintendents in the areas of instructional leadership, decision-making, problem solving and the change process at the district level.  School improvement, district management, and personnel and program management will be included in this course.  </P>

<P>EAD 7013. Personnel Administration - 3 hours </P>

<P>Processes and procedures required in implementing policies and practices of effective school personnel administration including instructional and non-instructional personnel.  </P>

<P>EAD 7023. Advanced School Finance - 3 hours </P>

<P>The study of school budgeting procedures, revenue and expenditure accounting, problems related to local, state, and federal financing of public school operations. </P>

<P>EAD 7033. School Planning &amp; Maintenance - 3 hours </P>

<P>The development of a master plan and educational specifications for a school facility.  Attention will be given to site and building evaluations, bond issues, remodeling, energy conservation, contractor and architectural responsibilities, equipping and maintaining plants and barrier-free facilities.  </P>

<P>EAD 7043. Research and Statistics - 3 hours  </P>

<P>A study of current research techniques and related statistical application.  The course will be taken in conjunction with or prior to the initiation of the field study in educational administration.   </P>

<P>EAD 7053. Advanced School Law - 3 hours </P>

<P>Constitutional, statutory and case law that relates to all staff personnel, students, school district and board members’ legal rights and responsibilities. </P>

<P>EAD 7063. Field Study - 3 hours  </P>

<P>The completion of a field project in the form of a specialist research paper.  The study may be done in cooperation with a public school district or appropriate agency.  Requires formal investigation and survey of a recognized problem with a selected institution.  The nature of the investigation may also be an in-depth independent research relevant to current practice in the field of education.  An advisory committee made up of full-time college instructors must approve the subject for research.  An oral review of the project must be presented.  </P>

<P>EAD 7072/7082. Internship in Superintendency - 2 hours (each) </P>

<P> Field experience in the superintendency.   </P>

<P>EAD 7093. Politics in Education - 3 hours  </P>

<P>Origins, nature and impact of political forces surrounding and influencing schools.  The course will also include the increasingly complex political web of American education as well as the debate of local control versus the expanding role of state and federal government.  Education and the social order will be analyzed from the perspective of school politics, demands made in the school community and the intervening variables associated with school issues.  </P>

<P>EAD 7123. The Superintendency - 3 hours </P>

<P>Taken in conjunction with the internship, students will analyze and discuss topics related to current problems of school district management involving decision making, data processing, operations, research, work and wages, unions and management, state and federal control and purchasing.  </P>

<P>EAD 7132. Capstone - 2 hours </P>

<P>Designed to bring all aspects of the superintendency together through summary and synthesis of the knowledge and skills acquired throughout the program.  Students will develop a personal growth plan for continuing their professional endeavors. Focus will be placed on the preparation for the national assessment for superintendents.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>DOCTORATE OF EDUCATION </P>

<P>BUS 6002 Non-Profit Financial Management – 2 hours </P>

<P>This course provides an understanding of the fundamental concepts underlying financial management, controls, and analysis in the nonprofit sector. Various topics, including strategy, budgeting process techniques, major budgetary issues, financial statement analysis, revenue sources, fund development, tax strategies, debt management, human resources, risk management, cash management, basic categories of nonprofit expenditures, organizational controls, and relevant information technology will be discussed.  A working knowledge of Excel is required for this course. </P>

<P>BUS 6012 Organizational Consulting Practice – 2 hours </P>

<P>This course introduces the task and relationship dimensions of organizational consulting and develops foundational competency in the areas of assessment, diagnosis, and problem solving relative to organizational performance.  Students will learn key aspects essential in creating and implementing effective independent consulting practices to support schools and non-profit organizations. Data collection and analysis are key components of the course to assist students in developing skills related to conducting effective organizational evaluations.      </P>

<P>EAD 8001. Symposium Planning and Development – 1 hour </P>

<P>      This course is designed as a collaborative experience with administrators and professors focusing on research and      </P>

<P>      practices relating to current educational issues. Small and large group work sessions will be designed and offered.    </P>

<P>      The focus will be on current issues in today’s educational, political and social climate.  The initial course will focus  </P>

<P>      on individualized progress in research development and planning.  The follow up will continue to further the  </P>

<P>      process, focusing on individualized methodology and statistical analysis. </P>

<P>EAD 8003. Leadership and the Law – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course examines key legal issues that govern daily and long-range decisions of educational leaders. The course focuses on understanding Missouri and federal codes, case law, policies, and significant precedent. The course emphasizes analysis of key legal concepts and application of law to major areas including finance, personnel, risk management, curriculum, student services, teacher rights, torts, student rights, sunshine law, technology, contract law and real estate law and facilities. Students will examine practical application to positively influence educational institutions is the goal of the course. A student will not have an encyclopedic knowledge of education law. Students who fully participate should gain the ability to use the law – constitutional language, statutes and legislative history, regulations, policies of local governing boards, adopted handbooks of policies and procedures – as a tool for effective and transformational leadership in their area of educational expertise.  </P>

<P>EAD 8011. Educational Symposium – 1 hour  </P>

<P>       This course is designed as a collaborative experience with administrators and professors focusing on research and      </P>

<P>       practices relating to current educational issues. Small and large group work sessions will be designed and offered.    </P>

<P>       The focus will be on current issues in today’s educational, political and social climate.  The initial course will focus  </P>

<P>       on individualized progress in research development and planning.  The follow up will continue to further the  </P>

<P>       process, focusing on individualized methodology and statistical analysis. </P>

<P>EAD 8013. Leadership in Learning – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course is designed for students to develop knowledge and skills necessary for leading an effective learning organization. Course work will focus on latest research and trends in instructional practice and effective district-level tools for assessing the effective implementation of these practices. Students will review and use various district-wide data collection tools and learn various approaches to data analysis. Students will synthesize latest research related to professional development practices and value the connection of performance data in creating a district-level Professional Development Plan.  </P>

<P>EAD 8023. Educational Advocacy – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course will introduce students to theory related to collaborative leadership, conflict resolution and communication responsibilities and the application of those concepts to educational advocacy. Designed to empower the educational leader to be an advocate, motivator, facilitator and negotiator when working with various groups including local, state and federal officials, outside agencies, media venues, and boards of education on behalf of school children. Participants will be introduced to various concepts related to developing effective communication strategies and a focus will be given to identifying successful engagement and collaboration techniques. Students will review methods for engaging community support for program initiatives and tax referendums. They will also explore methods for building positive relationships with the media and governmental officials. Students will further explore effective methods for impacting public policy and the impact of such policy on local school districts. Students will gain an understanding in how public policies are influenced by many stakeholders. The course will emphasize effective professional communication, including written texts, speeches and social networking through the use of technology.  </P>

<P>EAD 8033. Advanced Research - 3 hours </P>

<P>The course is designed to assist students in the development of the directed research pre-proposal and proposal. As part of the course students will investigate what sound research design is and how design influences the validity and credibility of the research and its findings. Students will also review and apply ethical practices of conducting research. Students will receive a possible proposal design framework and on-going assistance in developing their directed research proposal. Students should not expect to have a completed detailed directed research proposal by the end of the course.  </P>

<P>EAD 8043. Advanced Statistics and Instrument Design 3 hours </P>

<P>The focus of this course is on the development and evaluation of measurement instruments, with consideration given to the analysis of measurement data.  The fundamentals of measurement will be addressed, including but not limited to: scales, scores, reliability, and validity, development of tests, scale construction and item analysis.  Special consideration will be given to using standardized measures in decision making.   </P>

<P>EAD 8053. Ethics in Personal &amp; Professional Life – 3 hours  </P>

<P>The course seeks to challenge leaders to develop and maintain ethical behavior in their personal and professional life. Students will examine the practice of ethical decision making as it applies to real life authentic scenarios. A focal point </P>

<P>of this course will be the analysis and application of how servant leadership traits exemplified by Jesus Christ are still relevant in today’s personal and professional settings. </P>

<P>EAD 8073. Directed Research - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course involves extensive inquiry related to the development of a research proposal on a current, relevant topic in the field of education. A proposal is an agreement between the student and the student’s Directed Research Committee. Therefore, the proposal should be as specific and clearly written as possible to avoid misunderstandings between the candidate, the advisor and the Directed Research Committee. Like a pre-proposal there is no specific requirement on the number of pages or references for a proposal. The proposal and directed research will involve extensive, on-going research/writing by the candidate on a research project or topic of inquiry with advising from a faculty member. The proposal should follow the prescribed format of the final directed research paper. The proposal should be the first three chapters of a directed research paper. Students should rely on advisor’s guidance for the length, level of detail, and organization of the proposal and directed research. Proposals and directed research should be organized to research the topic effectively and present the findings in an understandable manner.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>INSTRUCTIONAL TECHNOLOGY LEADERSHIP </P>

<P>ITL 5093. Field-Based Research in Instructional Technology - 3 hours </P>

<P>In Field-Based Research in Instructional Technology the student will carry out a formal research study in Instructional Technology and prepare a written report and oral report.   Prerequisites: EDU 5083. </P>

<P>ITL 5613. The Instructional Role of Educational Media and Technology - 3 hours </P>

<P>Introduction to the skills of teaching as they relate to the role and use of educational media and technology. Students will learn how to design, develop, and evaluate an appropriate unit of instruction; develop and conduct a needs assessment; identify learning objectives; analyze learner characteristics; employ instructional strategies; and conduct evaluations. </P>

<P>ITL 5623. Multimedia Tools and Applications - 3 hours </P>

<P>Multimedia Tools and Applications cover issues in the design and development of interactive multimedia instructional lessons. Course covers the tools required for the creation of interactive multimedia, and is organized around individual student projects.  </P>

<P>ITL 5633. Instructional Material Design and Application - 3 hours  </P>

<P>Evaluation and design of computer-based instructional materials. Hands-on experiences with the design of computer-based lessons.  Instructional Material Design provides an opportunity for a student to develop a deeper understanding of the intent and design of computer-based instruction. </P>

<P>ITL 5643. Advanced Hardware and Software - 3 hours </P>

<P>Investigates hardware and software issues that arise in the development and delivery of instruction. Topics include hardware and software troubleshooting, security, networks, and distance education and communication systems. </P>

<P>ITL 5723. Advanced Media Management and Supervision - 3 hours </P>

<P>Advanced Media Management and Supervision is the study of management and supervisory techniques and their application to the instructional media program.  Includes management by objectives, staff development, and processes for change through the supervisory role of the media specialist. </P>

<P>ITL 5733. Leadership in School District Technology - 3 hours </P>

<P>This course provides an administrative perspective on instructional technology.  It surveys methods of using technology to improve administrative functions, funding sources for educational technology, knowledge and sensitivity of cultural pluralism as it impacts technological considerations and legal ethical issues surrounding educational technology. </P>

<P>ITL 5813. Technology Planning and Budgeting - 3 hours </P>

<P>Designed to have students create a strategic technology plan that provides direction as well as informs various publics how technology may be used within a school or institution.  Frameworks that set priorities for how to invest resources  in technology aligned with institutional goals will also be discussed. </P>

<P>ITL 5923.  Online Teaching in the K-12 Environment - 3 hours </P>

<P>With the realm of education constantly changing directions, online teaching has emerged on the horizon not only in </P>

<P>college, but in high school, middle school, and even grade school levels. Students will learn how to recognize and discuss methods of engagement for students in the online world, compare and contrast advantages/disadvantages for online students, facilitate an interview regarding the online education opportunity, develop a school proposal for online classes at their school, examine the road online learning/interaction is taking, and design a lesson around media for an online class. Students will need a general understanding of the online environment in order to keep up with and successfully navigate the course.</P>

<P> </P>

<H1 id="LinkTarget_3038">COLLEGE OF SCIENCE AND MATHEMATICS </H1>

<P>Perry A. Tompkins, Dean Office: Wheeler 100-B - (417) 328-1659 
<Link>http://www.sbuniv.edu/academics/colleges/cosm.php</Link>
 </P>

<P> </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_3046">Doctor of Physical Therapy </H2>

<P>Director and Department Chair:  Steven G. Lesh </P>

<P>Office: Davis 100 - (417) 328-1672 </P>

<P>Faculty: Terry Cox, Amber Fleer, Herb Hamann, Kevin Jones, </P>

<P>Sarah Jones, Josh Layman, Connie Matheny, Beverly McNeal,  </P>

<P>Becky Schoeneberg, Tom Sneed, Martaun Stockstill, Marsha Trantham </P>

<P>
<Link>http://www.sbuniv.edu/pt</Link>
 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>“Whatever you do, work at it with all your heart, as working for the Lord, not for human masters, since you know that you will receive an inheritance from the Lord as a reward. It is the Lord Christ you are serving.” </P>

<P>-Colossians 3:23-24 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Calendar</P>

<P>Fall 2018 </P>

<P>August  </P>

<P>16-17…Reg./Orientation-first-year DPT students </P>

<P>20 ...................................... Classes begin </P>

<P>September </P>

<P> 3 ........................................ Labor Day-No Classes </P>

<P>October </P>

<P> 1 ........................................ Applications accepted for entry-level DPT </P>

<P>November </P>

<P>17-25 ................................. Thanksgiving Break </P>

<P>December </P>

<P>11-14 ................................. Final examinations </P>

<P>15 ...................................... Christmas Break begin </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Spring 2019 </P>

<P>January </P>

<P>3 ......................... DPT Classes start-Jan term </P>

<P>24 ....................... DPT Classes start-Spring term </P>

<P>March </P>

<P> 1 ......................... DPT 1, 2, &amp; 3 Portfolios Due </P>

<P>       16-24 .................. Spring Break </P>

<P>May </P>

<P> 13-17 .................. Final examinations/Clin. Educ.  </P>

<P>                                    Debriefing </P>

<P> 28 ....................... Summer classes begin (tentative)</P>

<P>Program Mission and Objectives </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Entry-Level DPT Program History and Accreditation Status </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The entry-level Doctor of Physical Therapy program at Southwest Baptist University prepares students for careers in physical therapy through the development of knowledge and skills needed for patient management, education, consultation, and clinical research.  The entry-level DPT program at Southwest Baptist University is accredited by the Commission on Accreditation in Physical Therapy Education (CAPTE), 1111 North Fairfax Street, Alexandria, Virginia 22314; telephone 703-706-3245; email: accreditation@apta.org; website: 
<Link>http://www.capteonline.org</Link>
.  The entry-level DPT is also accredited by the Higher Learning Commission of the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools, 30 North LaSalle </P>

<P>Street, Suite 2400, Chicago, Illinois 60602-2504, www.ncahigherlearningcommission.org, (312) 263-0456 or (800) 621-7440. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Program Mission Statement (rev. 11.17.04) </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Our Healing Mission: The physical therapy department at Southwest Baptist University is dedicated to providing society with physical therapists who engage in the art and science of physical therapy with a Christian worldview. The graduate will be a clinician generalist who is prepared to provide physical therapy services for a diverse population in an evolving society and health care environment. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Program Goals (est. 11.17.04) </P>

<P> </P>

<P>A SBU Doctor of Physical Therapy graduate will be able to: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Integrate the Christian worldview into the practice of physical therapy. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Engage in the professional practice expectations on a diverse patient and client population throughout the lifespan. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Educate and communicate with appropriate stakeholders in the health care environment. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Serve the profession and society to promote and improve evolving health care delivery. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Reflectively practice the art and science of physical therapy by critically evaluating, integrating, and contributing to the expanding professional knowledge base. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>6. Formulate a plan for life-long learning coupled with professional, personal, and spiritual growth.  </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Assessment </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Periodic measurements of student perceptions, intellectual growth, clinical performance, and professional behaviors development are obtained as one means for the University to assess and improve its academic programs and student learning.  The information obtained is used to measure and develop student competencies and to determine and improve the quality of the educational experience for students.  Students are required to compile and maintain a formal learning portfolio by which the student demonstrates progress towards and achievement of the established program goals by the end of the final year of the curriculum. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Admission Requirements </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Physical Therapy Requirements </P>

<P>The following requirements must be met before being admitted to the physical therapy program at SBU (courses in progress during semester(s) applying must be documented and completed prior to admission): </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Completion of a baccalaureate degree </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Completion of current PT application </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Documented experience / observation in physical therapy; up to 40 hours will be counted and variety of experience is recommended </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Completion of graduate records exam (GRE) </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Earn a minimum of 2.75 overall GPA (for all previous course work or highest degree attained) OR for last 60 hours of course work earn a minimum of 3.0 overall GPA </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>6. Completion of the following prerequisite courses with a minimum of a 3.0 prerequisite GPA and at least a &quot;C&quot; in each. Prerequisites should not be taken pass/fail: </LBody>
</LI>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>a. General Chemistry - two semesters in sequence with labs; minimum 8 credit hours is expected </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>b. General Physics - two semesters in sequence with labs; minimum 8 credit hours is expected </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>c. General Biology - one semester with lab; minimum 4 credit hours is expected </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>d. Anatomy / Physiology - one semester each or full year combined sequence with labs from a science-based department; minimum 8 credit hours is expected  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>e. Statistics - one course </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>f. Psychology - three courses from a psychology department (1. general, 2. normal growth and development, and 3. abnormal development) </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</L>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>7. Completion of the following support courses (not calculated into prerequisite GPA: </LBody>
</LI>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>a. Medical Terminology - one semester is required at a &quot;B&quot; grade or higher; one credit hour minimum expected </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>b. Pathophysiology - not required, but highly recommended </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>c. Exercise Physiology - not required, but highly recommended; students demonstrating successful completion of an exercise physiology course with a &quot;B&quot; grade or higher will be exempt from completing the exercise physiology component of the DPT program </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<LI>
<LBody>8. International student need to contact the department or consult the SBU catalog for additional requirements, including the TOEFL exam </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Prerequisite science classes must be current. Completion of each course sequence must be within seven years prior to admission to the PT program. Exceptions may be granted only if the applicant can show that knowledge of the course content is current. Applicants seeking an exception must submit a written petition with rationale for approval. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>In the case of repeat prerequisite grades, the department will use the “best case” scenario for determining eligibility; however, an application penalty would be applied by reducing the overall score for each repeat grade that was present on the transcript. The grade for any science courses repeated due to the seven year rule will be substituted for the old class regardless of the first grade received. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>International Students </P>

<P>Official records of all higher education, including certificates or degrees with the dates the degrees were conferred must be submitted. All records not in English must be accompanied by an official translated record. All records should show the individual subjects studied and the grades received in each subject. International applicants are required to submit proof of adequate finances for the entire period of study before admission can be granted. Eligible applicants whose native language is not English must take the Test of English as a Foreign Language (TOEFL) and attain a score of at least 550. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Transfer Students </P>

<P>Students with previous course credit in a professional phase of a CAPTE accredited PT program will be considered for academic transfer into the professional phase of the SBU entry-level DPT program if: </P>

<L>
<L>
<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. the student completes and submits a current application </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. the application meets established minimum application standards for unconditional enrollment (as if they were enrolling for the first year of the program) </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</L>
</L>

<P>and the new student will be subject to the following conditions or standards: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>3. No prior PT school earned grades of less than a &quot;B-&quot; will be accepted for transfer credit. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. The student will automatically be placed on normal &quot;conditional&quot; enrollment. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. A maximum of 1 full year of academic credit may be transferred depending on the ability to match historic courses to pending courses in the normal SBU sequence (i.e. the student must successfully complete the second and third year of the normal DPT sequence). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>6. All considerations are on a space available basis and by taking a transfer student, it is in the opinion of the faculty, that SBU academic standards are not compromised. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>7. Potential transfer student may be required to provide extra or special documentation or interviews as deemed necessary by faculty in order to fully consider the application request. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Students who have not taken the prerequisite courses should be advised to take the specific courses or equivalents. When those courses are not available at the college / university they are currently attending, course substitutions may be allowed under the following guidelines. All substitutions submitted with the application must be made in writing and include a course syllabus or adequate description to determine equivalency. Applicants who have taken the specific prerequisite course but want to substitute another course with a higher grade may be able to do so only when the substitute course is an advanced course covering the same content. Course substitutions may be allowed when the content is met or exceeded.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Specific course substitution considerations will be handled as follows: </P>

<P> </P>

<P>General Chemistry - Upper level chemistry courses (e.g. organic or biochemistry) which require General Chemistry may be substituted assuming higher level sequence is completed (prior approval not required). </P>

<P>General Physics - Upper level physics courses (e.g. calculus based) may be substituted assuming higher level sequence is completed (prior approval not required). </P>

<P>Biology – General Zoology may also be substituted (prior approval not required). Upper level human- or animal-based biology course(s) containing appropriate content for PT may be substituted pending approval. </P>

<P>Anatomy / Physiology - only human, comparative, or vertebrate anatomy / physiology from a science-based department (e.g. biology, zoology, anatomy, physiology) may be substituted (prior approval not required). Any other course(s) must have prior approval. Applied anatomy / physiology from non-science based departments may not be substituted. </P>

<P>Statistics - Course meeting or exceeding expected foundational content may be substituted only if from social science, business, or math based department (prior approval not required). </P>

<P>Psychology - Out of department substitutions will only be considered if the university does not have the expected psychology prerequisite courses from a psychology based department. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>CLEP/Advanced Placement Considerations </P>

<P>In some cases, college credit is given for coursework (e.g. CLEP, Advanced Placement) and an actual grade is not recorded. Credit will be given if needed to meet an admissions requirement, however, if no transcripted grade can be produced, it will be omitted from GPA calculations. </P>

<P>General Admission Process </P>

<P>Applicants must apply to the Physical Therapy Program. Students must complete the courses required for entry into the program and complete a Baccalaureate Degree in another field prior to admission to the Physical Therapy Program. Students may have courses in progress in the Spring or Summer semester prior to enrolling in the physical therapy program but all requirements must be completed prior to enrollment. Important admission dates include the following: </P>

<P> July 1:   Begin receiving applications. </P>

<P> September 1:  Begin reviewing applications (Early Decision considerations). </P>

<P>October 1:  Begin reviewing applications (General Pool) </P>

<P>August: New physical therapy entry-level DPT class begins in mid-August. Students accepted into the entry-level program in physical therapy will be enrolled full-time in professional graduate courses for 33 consecutive months to finish with a Doctor of Physical Therapy degree.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Admission to the University does not guarantee admission into the graduate physical therapy program. Application priority points will be given to SBU undergraduate students and recognized undergraduate articulation school students. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Ranking of applications will consider criteria including as established by the core faculty as follows: </P>

<P>-prerequisite grade point average (30%), </P>

<P>-overall grade point average (8%), </P>

<P>-references (15%), </P>

<P>-observation experience (4%), </P>

<P>-written essay\narrative (5%), </P>

<P>-preferred attendance (8%), </P>

<P>-graduate record exam (30%) </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Applicants are strongly encouraged to communicate frequently with the Graduate Admissions Coordinator and schedule an individual visit to campus. Starting with the initial review date, applications will be acted upon on a rolling basis and designated into one of the following categories with appropriate notification to the applicant:  </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. selected for unconditional admission into the program (i.e. met all admission criteria);  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. selected for unconditional admission into the program contingent upon outstanding action items (i.e. has currently met most admission criteria with the exception of a few items, which in the opinion of the committee will not make a major negative impact upon the overall status of the application. Outstanding items must be successfully completed prior to admission in program); </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>3. placed on a waiting list to be considered for unconditional admission as space is available; </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. placed on an alternate list including but not limited to conditional enrollment status (i.e. the applicant failed to meet the established minimum GPA standards and is then scored and ranked in the applicant alternate pool. It is expected that beginning on or close to March 1 of each year, after the unconditional applicant pool has been exhausted, that applicants from the alternate pool will be considered for admission to the program);  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. held for subsequent review pending the submission of further requested or outstanding material; or </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>6. denied admissions.   </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>A student may decline SBU acceptance a maximum of one time. If student wishes to re-enter the pool for another application cycle, they must first appeal directly to the department chair establishing appropriate grounds that their new application should be considered. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>A student who is dismissed, denied the privilege of re-enrollment, or voluntarily leaves the program for any reason, and wishes to re-enter the program, must first appeal in writing to the department chair establishing appropriate grounds that their application and/or re-entry should be considered. The department chair will present appeal to core faculty for final decision (2/3 vote needed to approve). </P>

<P> </P>

<P>High School Early Acceptance Program </P>

<P>Selected High School students are eligible to apply on a competitive basis for early acceptance into the physical therapy program subject to the following parameters and guidelines: </P>

<P> </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Earn a 24 ACT or equivalent SAT score (1090). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Submit a completed High School Early Acceptance (HSEA) application with appropriate supporting evidence and documentation. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Should be a graduating high school senior or collegiate freshman with less than 30 completed undergraduate hours at the time of application. Note: This provision is aimed to not penalize students from taking dual credit courses in advance of regular collegiate admissions as an incoming freshman. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Once accepted into the HSEA program, all undergraduate classes must be taken at SBU with the successful awarding of a bachelor’s degree. The spirit of this provision is not to prevent the student from taking an occasional summer or correspondence course from a different college or university.  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. HSEA recipients must confirm their intent to matriculate into the professional phase of the physical therapy program by the end of January in their intended enrollment year and pay appropriate deposit. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>6. Must submit current overall graduate program application. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>7. HSEA recipients must earn an overall GPA of 3.00, a prerequisite GPA of 3.25, and a minimum grade of a “C” in all prerequisite courses or else forfeit their acceptance. The prerequisite GPA will be calculated with the first-time attempted course grade. Withdrawals will be considered an “F” grade. Under special circumstances, a withdrawn course can be petitioned, reviewed by the admissions committee, to be retaken for prerequisite GPA consideration.   </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>8. Document 40 hours of observation or work hours in a physical therapy setting. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>9. Participate in 50 hours of community service. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>10. Complete PTH 2523 Introduction to Physical Therapy and KIN 3073 Exercise Physiology with a minimum grade of a “B.” Note: These courses are considered support courses and are not used to calculate prerequisite GPA. Courses may be retaken if needed to earn the required grade level. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>11. HSEA applications should be submitted to the department for consideration for the upcoming fall semester: 1) on or before the middle of November or January for students participating in SBU Scholars Day, or 2) before the first of April for students not participating in SBU Scholars Day. A maximum of 20 awards will be given during any one academic year. If the 20 slots are not filled during the first selection cycle, a late cycle pool will be considered during February of the academic year just prior to the selection cycle for the next academic year. If slots are not filled for any one academic year, they will not roll over or be extended. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>The physical therapy department recommends the completion of one of the following undergraduate degrees: Biology, Exercise Science, or Psychology. Students should carefully plan their undergraduate experience such that most prerequisites are completed prior to their senior (or application) year. Students electing to take non-recommended degree paths should make those considerations for other specific purposes and with the knowledge that those elections may increase the duration of their undergraduate experience prior to entering the physical therapy program. If there are ever any questions about the most effective and efficient undergraduate path toward entering the graduate physical therapy program, please contact the program directly. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Eligibility for awarding the HSEA is established at the point of SBU undergraduate graduation and all normal requirements must be completed at the time of recognized graduation. Successful HSEA participants will receive a scholarship upon entering the professional phase of the physical therapy program subject to the following parameters and guidelines: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Students will receive credit for the scholarship by attending and documenting mentoring sessions on a semester basis during their undergraduate semesters (max 8 semesters). The scholarship amount will be earned at a rate of $375 per regular semester (Fall, Spring) enrolled at SBU in which student attends the mandatory mentoring sessions. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. The total scholarship is awarded in 3 equal installments upon entry to the SBU physical therapy program (i.e. first year, second year, and third year in equal $1000 amounts resulting in a “discount” on the annual tuition). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. The award is not distributed as a cash award. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. If the student does not accept the HSEA enrollment into the SBU physical therapy program, the award becomes null and void. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. If the student does not merit entry to the SBU physical therapy program under the established guidelines as a HSEA participant, the award becomes null and void. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>6. A deferment of up to 2 calendar years after earning of a bachelor’s degree from SBU may be granted upon request of the HSEA participant who otherwise meets established guidelines. The spirit of this provision is a variance given to HSEA participants who meet unexpected life events beyond their control. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>7. Once enrolled in the professional phase of the program, the HSEA participant must meet established unconditional matriculation requirements or the remaining award distributions will be forfeited. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>A+ Recruitment Program </P>

<P>The Doctor of Physical Therapy (DPT) program at Southwest Baptist University realizes and appreciates that the cost of earning a valuable degree continues to increase and this cost factor does play a role in the decision-making processes on where students elect to attend college. The program wishes to support Missouri A+ students who have a professional goal on becoming a physical therapist by establishing a path by which they can complete their A+ requirements and earn an automatic acceptance into the SBU DPT program. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>A+ Recruitment Program Requirements </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Successfully earn an Associate’s degree based on the existing parameters of the A+ program </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Earn a Bachelor’s of Science degree from SBU in Biology </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Have the following prerequisite courses completed by B.S. graduation and present on the transcript with at least a minimum grade of a “B” in each course (combined prerequisite GPA should be 3.25)^#: </LBody>
</LI>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>a. Biology* – one semester, human or animal-based with lab component </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>b. Chemistry* – two semesters with lab component </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>c. Physics* – two semesters with lab component </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>d. Anatomy and Physiology* – two semesters with lab component </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>e. Statistics </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>f. Three psychology courses – general, normal growth, abnormal development </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>g. Medical Terminology – housed in PTH 2523 Intro to Physical Therapy </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>h. Exercise Physiology – KIN 3073 Physiology of Exercise </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</L>

<P>  </P>

<P>^Repeated courses will be reviewed by the admissions committee for evaluation of acceptance. It is the general guideline that courses should not be repeated unless extreme circumstances are presented. </P>

<P>#Course in Pathophysiology is highly recommended, but not required. </P>

<P>*Courses must be taken in sequence from a science-based department. </P>

<P>Degree Requirements </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Doctor of Physical Therapy </P>

<P>To receive the DPT degree the student must: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. complete all the physical therapy courses and practical exams with at least a C, and have a minimum graduate GPA of 3.00; </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>2. pass all clinical education courses;  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. earn a final passing grade on learning portfolios; and </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. participate in commencement exercises unless absence is approved by the Provost. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Program of Study and Academic Regulations </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Student Orientation </P>

<P>New students enrolled in the physical therapy program attend two full days of orientation at the beginning of their first year. At this time, they receive a Physical Therapy Student Handbook which includes the policies and procedures for the graduate program in physical therapy. Students are responsible for all materials presented in the respective handbooks. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Clinical Education </P>

<P>The purpose of the clinical education component within the physical therapy curriculum is to ensure student carry-over and integration of didactic course work into the clinical setting. To ensure a broad range of clinical experiences, each student will be required to have a clinical experience in acute care, outpatient orthopedics, and neuro-rehabilitation. These experiences appear late in the curriculum totaling 34 weeks in a residency-like format. One of the final clinical education experiences may be in an area of special interest within physical therapy that has not already been experienced by the student in a prior clinical experience. Students are responsible for all expenses for travel and living during the clinical education experiences. Students with a history of criminal actions documented on a background check may have clinical education placement options severely limited or delayed. While student input to the assignment process is valued and considered, we cannot guarantee these requests for clinical assignments will be met. The final decision rests with the Academic Coordinator of Clinical Education (ACCE), with input from the Core Faculty, and the student should be readily prepared to attend a rotation that may not have been a top preferred position on the part of the student. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Specific clinical education policies and requirements are delineated in the Physical Therapy Student Handbook. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Curricular Schedule </P>

<P>Physical therapy professional courses may only be taken by those students accepted in the program and are delivered in a lock-step fashion. The following schedule may be subject to change. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 1: Fall </P>

<P>PTH 5132  Critical Inquiry </P>

<P>PTH 5013  Psychosocial Issues of Health Care </P>

<P>PTH 5047  Human Anatomy </P>

<P>PTH 5066  Clinical Kinesiology </P>

<P>PTH 5481  Christian Applications for the Healthcare Professional I </P>

<P>PTH 5631 Integrated Clinical Experience I </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 1: January </P>

<P>PTH 5221  Teaching and Learning </P>

<P>PTH 5593  Neuroscience for the Physical Therapist </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 1: Spring </P>

<P>PTH 5423  Therapeutic Exercise </P>

<P>PTH 5093  Physical Therapy Science </P>

<P>PTH 6273  Physical Therapist Management of Integumentary Disorders </P>

<P>PTH 5611 Professional Development Seminar I </P>

<P>PTH 5103 Therapeutic Modalities in Physical Therapy  </P>

<P>PTH 5403  Physical Assessment </P>

<P>PTH 6393 Motor Control and Learning </P>

<P>PTH 5641 Integrated Clinical Experience II </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 1: Summer </P>

<P>PTH 6293  Exercise Prescription in Physical Therapy </P>

<P>PTH 5233 Foundations of the Musculoskeletal System </P>

<P>PTH 6022 Today's Health Care </P>

<P>PTH 6082  Human Life Sequences </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 2: Fall </P>

<P>PTH 5382 Pharmacology for Physical Therapists </P>

<P>PTH 6245  Physical Therapist Management of Musculoskeletal Disorders I </P>

<P>PTH 6263  Prosthetics and Orthotics </P>

<P>PTH 6472  Pathology for Physical Therapists I </P>

<P>PTH 6501  Christian Applications for the Healthcare Professional II </P>

<P>PTH 6326  Physical Therapist Management of Neurological Disorders I </P>

<P>PTH 6651 Integrated Clinical Experience III </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 2: January </P>

<P>PTH 5412  Diagnostic Imaging for Physical Therapists </P>

<P>PTH 6332 Administration and Management </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 2: Spring </P>

<P>PTH 5151  Clinical Investigations I </P>

<P>PTH 6255  Physical Therapist Management of Musculoskeletal Disorders II </P>

<P>PTH 7316  Physical Therapist Management of Neurological Disorders II </P>

<P>PTH 6603 Pathology for Physical Therapists II </P>

<P>PTH 6621 Professional Development Seminar II </P>

<P>PTH 6583  Prevention, Health Promotion, Fitness, and Wellness </P>

<P>PTH 6671 Integrated Clinical Experience IV </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 2: Summer </P>

<P>PTH 7283 Physical Therapist Management of Cardiopulmonary Disorders </P>

<P>PTH 7343  Pediatric Physical Therapy </P>

<P>PTH 7353 Geriatric Physical Therapy </P>

<P>PTH 7362  Capstone  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 3: Fall </P>

<P>PTH 7158  Clinical Education I </P>

<P>PTH 7458  Clinical Education II </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Year 3: Jan/Spring </P>

<P>PTH 7459  Clinical Education III </P>

<P>PTH 7469  Clinical Education IV </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Progression in the Physical Therapy Program </P>

<P>Students are subject to the academic regulations stated in the respective SBU catalogs and handbooks. To be eligible for the clinical education component and/or matriculation to the next year of the program, students must successfully pass all prior courses in the program and maintain an overall GPA of 3.00 (on a 4.00 scale). Students must also submit an individual learning portfolio for formal annual assessment and earn a final passing grade at the end of the curriculum. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Students earning a grade of “F” or “non-credit” in any given course will not be able to enroll in courses listing the failed course as a prerequisite. Any student who is unable to meet these requirements is subject to review by the Physical Therapy Review Committee which will in consultation with the student, determine a plan for further action which may include academic probation with a specific plan for remediation or dismissal from the program. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Students will be expected to satisfactorily pass each practical examination and course. Students having difficulty will meet with course instructor and advisor to determine a plan of remediation. The Physical Therapy Core Faculty will, as part of the curriculum/program evaluation, monitor the standards. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Graduate level physical therapy repeat courses are permitted only under the supervision and recommendation of the PT Review Committee for remediation purposes. Students passing a physical therapy course will not be permitted to retake the course for academic grade or transcript purposes unless otherwise directed by the PT Review Committee. If the course is successfully repeated (as defined by the PT Review Committee), then the new earned grade will replace the previously earned failing grade for matriculation and transcript purposes and the previous grade will not enter into grade point average (GPA) calculations from that point forward. The Registrar will replace the original earned failing grade with a designation that the original grade was failing, but has now been successfully repeated (e.g. RF). </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Exams will be based on course objectives. Criteria for projects, papers, and/or assignments will be stated in the syllabus for the students. Criteria and determination of grades for each course will be established by the core or adjunct faculty member who is leading the course. The policy and expectations of each instructor will be stated in writing in the class syllabus and explained to the class within the first few class sessions. The following grading scales will be used unless otherwise directed in the specific syllabus: </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Grades </P>

<P>Academic Grading Scale </P>

<P>90.0 - 100% .................................... A </P>

<P>80.0 - 89.9 ....................................... B </P>

<P>75.0 - 79.9 ....................................... C </P>

<P>0 - 74.9 ............................................ F </P>

<P>Incomplete ...................................... I </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Clinical Education and Selected Course </P>

<P>Grading Scale </P>

<P>Pass ................................................. P </P>

<P>Fail .................................................. F </P>

<P>Incomplete ...................................... I </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Individual Learning Portfolio </P>

<P>Exceeds Expectations  .................... (E) Passing Score </P>

<P>Meets Expectations  ........................ (M) Passing Score </P>

<P>Fails to Meet Expectations ............. (F) Failing Score </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Dismissal </P>

<P>A student may be placed on probation, suspended for a specific period of time, or dismissed for either academic issues (i.e. grade-based) and/or professional behaviors issues (i.e. non grade-based) as defined in the Southwest Baptist University Professional Behavior Definitions found in the DPT Student Handbook. All decisions for dismissal, or being denied the privilege of re-enrollment, are made by the Physical Therapy Review Committee and approved by the Department Chairperson with appropriate input from the Dean of Students. Students may be dismissed from the program based on the following: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. A final grade of &quot;F&quot; in any required course prior to PTH 7362 Capstone. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. A GPA of less than 3.00 while on conditional enrollment. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. An &quot;F&quot; in any course if already on academic probation or conditional enrollment. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Non-compliance with the requirements stipulated in a remediation plan established by the ACCE or Physical Therapy Review Committee. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Cheating or plagiarism. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>6. Any misconduct listed in the SBU Student Handbook as serious offenses (class C). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>7. Serious or repeated breech of professional behaviors found in SBU Professional Behavior Definitions. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>8. A second final grade of “F” beginning with PTH 7362 Capstone through the end of terminal clinical education courses. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>9. Violation of the SBU Drug and Alcohol Policy. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P> </P>

<P>Attendance </P>

<P>Class attendance is mandatory. The student is responsible for attendance at all class sessions and meetings. A pattern of repeated absence or tardiness will be reported to the faculty advisor and may result in development of a remediation plan by the PT Review Committee. Students must notify the instructor directly in writing (e.g. email) or by calling office in advance for any absence except for emergency or unavoidable circumstances. If the instructor is not available when the student calls, a voice message should be left. In the case of unavoidable circumstances, students must contact the instructor on return from absence and if possible, prior to the next class session to ensure completion of assignments. Additional assignments may be required. Faculty will give make-up exams and modify deadlines for assignments only for excused absences with appropriate documentation. The student is responsible to get notes for any class missed whether excused or unexcused. Students missing 3 unexcused lecture or lab sessions during the regular fall or spring semesters, or 10% of total class hours in Jan term and summer courses will have their course grade reduced by one letter grade.  Each additional missed lecture or lab will result in an additional letter grade reduction. For tabulation purposes, lecture and lab sessions are counted as individual sessions (even if on same day). Any student who is late for class will be counted as missing a minimum of 1 class hour. Course specific policies are determined by each instructor and must be in compliance with the SBU Catalog and SBU Student Handbook.  The student may request excused time off for special once in a lifetime events (e.g. weddings; graduations) only if by missing the scheduled class, the otherwise unexcused absence would have a detrimental impact on a course grade (e.g. at least lowering of final course grade by one letter). </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Appeals </P>

<P>The faculty of the Department of Physical Therapy realizes that occasionally some circumstances may prevent a student from performing optimally in every course during each term. Any student wishing to appeal a decision by an individual faculty member or by the Physical Therapy Review Committee or Department Chair must first appeal to the decision maker then to the next level within the department. If the student is not satisfied with the Department's decision, he/she may appeal as described in the SBU graduate catalog. The grade appeal process is described in the SBU graduate catalog. It is plausible that the successful appeal process creates a natural delay in matriculation due to the lockstep nature of the curriculum. Under rare circumstances, a student who was normally admitted to the program, is discovered to either knowingly or unknowingly mislead, misrepresent, or falsify elements related to admission standards. If this circumstance is discovered, regardless of when it is discovered, the status of an enrolled or admitted student is automatically revoked and the student forfeits any rights to appeal and any claim on monies already paid to the institution in the form of tuition and fees. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Official Communications </P>

<P>All official notices from the department will be sent to the official student local address on file with the university and/or the official SBU email provider. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>COURSE DESCRIPTIONS </P>

<P> </P>

<P>PTH 2523.  Introduction to Physical Therapy - 45 clock hrs (Spring, even years) </P>

<P>Introduces students to the multifaceted role of the physical therapy profession. Topics include the diversity and growth of health care and physical therapy, methodologies used in physical therapy education, and the concept of the health care team.  Introduction to medical terminology will also be made, teaching the student to form medical terms, and define medical terms used in medical documents to be able to read and write these documents.  Prerequisite: none. </P>

<P>PTH 5013.  Psychosocial Issues of Health Care - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Introduction to the process of professional socialization through an understanding of the interaction between the student, health professionals, and society as it relates to Christian and worldview biases.  Psychological and sociological effects of impairments, functional limitations, and disability resulting from injury or disease, as applicable to the patient, client, family, and therapist. Communication skills are presented including conflict resolution, individual and cultural differences, interview, and group processes. Emphasis on increased awareness of self and interaction with others. Prerequisite: Admission to the PT program. </P>

<P>PTH 5047.  Human Anatomy - 105 clock hours </P>

<P>Normal human anatomy with emphasis on the musculoskeletal system and principles of articulation.  Cadaver dissection. Prerequisite: Admission to the PT program.  Course fee:  $700 </P>

<P>PTH 5066.  Clinical Kinesiology - 90 clock hrs </P>

<P>Study of biomechanical and kinesiological principles as they influence human movement of the upper &amp; lower extremities and spine with introduction to pathokinesiology; Principles and measurement techniques of goniometry; Principles and performance of manual muscle testing the upper &amp; lower extremity and trunk; Upper &amp; Lower quarter surface anatomy and palpation; and postural assessment of normal and abnormal alignment. Course Prerequisite: Admission to the PT program. </P>

<P>PTH 5093.  Physical Therapy Science - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>This course presents the first-year clinical science and skills including gait analysis, safety, universal precautions, transfer training, gait training, bed mobility, and patient positioning as well as other foundational elements to prepare the student for clinical experiences.  Prerequisite: PTH 5047 and 5066. </P>

<P>PTH 5103.  Therapeutic Modalities in Physical Therapy - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Application of external energy (heat, cold, sound, light, compression, traction, water, electricity, and other forms of electromagnetic energy) to effect therapeutic physiologic changes in human tissues.  Concepts of prescription, efficacy, safety, instrumentation, documentation and delegation are emphasized. Prerequisite: PTH 5047 and 5066. </P>

<P>PTH 5132.  Critical Inquiry - 30 clock hrs </P>

<P>The principles and foundations of clinical research in physical therapy are presented in this course. Special emphasis will be applied to research methodology, interpretation of statistical techniques, and critical analysis of published literature. Prerequisite: Admission to the PT program. </P>

<P>PTH 5151.  Clinical Investigations I - 15 clock hrs </P>

<P>This course will empower the learner to access professional databases, acquire relevant literature, and assess the quality of the published studies. Prerequisite: PTH 5132. </P>

<P>PTH 5221.  Teaching and Learning - 15 clock hrs </P>

<P>Teaching and learning theory applied to clinical practice with peers, patient/clients and their families. Special emphasis placed upon teaching strategies and techniques for patient/client education and presenting clinically based in-services. Prerequisite: Admission to the PT program. </P>

<P>PTH 5233.  Foundations of the Musculoskeletal System - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Foundational concepts and principles for application of the patient/client management model to the musculoskeletal system;  basic science issues related to musculoskeletal tissues;  introduction of medical/surgical management of musculoskeletal pathology.  Prerequisite: PTH 5047 and 5066. </P>

<P>PTH 5382.  Pharmacology for Physical Therapists - 30 clock hrs </P>

<P>This course presents the effects commonly used pharmacologic agents have on the body, how the body metabolizes and eliminates these agents, mechanisms of pharmaceutical administration, and pharmacological indications, contraindications and safety concerns as applied to patients/clients typically treated by the physical therapist. Prerequisite: PTH 5047 and 5066. </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>PTH 5403.  Physical Assessment - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>This course focuses on the physical examination and systems review process in evaluation of musculoskeletal, neuromuscular, cardiopulmonary, integumentary, GI/GU/renal and cognitive/behavioral systems. Hands-on application of assessment skills in health examination of patients. Prerequisite: PTH 5047 and 5066. </P>

<P>PTH 5412.  Diagnostic Imaging for Physical Therapists - 30 clock hrs </P>

<P>Introduces diagnostic imaging modalities relevant to physical therapists with correlation to various clinical conditions and emphasis on a systematic approach to analyzing plain film radiography. Prerequisite: PTH 5233. </P>

<P>PTH 5423.  Therapeutic Exercise - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>The principles and techniques of therapeutic exercises are presented.  Specific neurological, medical, surgical, and orthopedic conditions are studied. Prerequisite: PTH 5047 and 5066. </P>

<P>PTH 5481. Christian Applications for the Healthcare Professional I - 15 clock hrs </P>

<P>An introduction to the concept of worldview with emphasis on the Christian worldview and related perspectives on current healthcare issues. Prerequisites: Admission to the DPT Program. </P>

<P>PTH 5593. Neuroscience for the Physical Therapist - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Human neuroscience foundations and issues are presented as related to the rehabilitation process. Prerequisite: PTH 5047 and 5066. </P>

<P>PTH 5611.  Professional Development Seminar I - 15 clock hrs </P>

<P>This first-year seminar focuses on the professional responsibilities of a doctoring profession in the context of becoming a servant leader in a global society.  Prerequisites: PTH 5013. </P>

<P>PTH 5631. Integrated Clinical Experience I – 40 clock hrs </P>

<P>This first semester supervised clinical field experience introduces the doctor of physical therapy student to an integrated and interdisciplinary approach to contemporary health care. Course Fee: $500. </P>

<P>PTH 5641. Integrated Clinical Experience II – 40 clock hrs </P>

<P>This second semester supervised clinical field experience introduces the doctor of physical therapy student to an integrated and interdisciplinary approach to contemporary health care. Course Fee: $500. </P>

<P>PTH 6022.  Today's Health Care - 30 clock hrs </P>

<P>Global factors that impact today's health care systems are presented including discussions on providers, stakeholders, and beneficiaries. Prerequisite: PTH 5611. </P>

<P>PTH 6082.  Human Life Sequences - 30 clock hrs  </P>

<P>The developmental process from conception to death with emphasis on human motor performance. Sequence of study includes fetal life and infancy through the aging adult including: developmental changes in performance and musculoskeletal development in relationship to the human lifespan, life-span concepts of age-related change in motor behavior and development of posture and movement. Prerequisite: PTH 6393. </P>

<P>PTH 6245.  Physical Therapist Management of Musculoskeletal Disorders I - 75 clock hrs </P>

<P>Concepts, principles, and procedures for application of the patient/client management model specific to musculoskeletal disorders of the upper and lower extremities.  Prerequisite: PTH 5233. </P>

<P>PTH 6255.  Physical Therapist Management of Musculoskeletal Disorders II - 75 clock hrs </P>

<P>The continuation of concepts, principles, and procedures for application of the patient/client management model specific to musculoskeletal disorders. Prerequisite: PTH 6245. </P>

<P>PTH 6263. Prosthetics and Orthotics - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>This course presents the psychological reactions of limb loss and/or dysfunction. Emphasis is placed upon the patient/client management model for various levels of amputation; selection of prosthetic/orthotic materials and components including alignment; gait analysis and training; and fabrication or modification of various orthotic devices. Prerequisite: PTH 5047, 5066 and 6273. </P>

<P>PTH 6273.  Physical Therapist Management of Integumentary Disorders - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Concepts, principles, and procedures for application of the patient/client management model specific to integumentary disorders with special emphasis on wound care management. Prerequisite: PTH 5047 and 5066. </P>

<P>PTH 6293.  Exercise Prescription in Physical Therapy - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Study of appropriate exercise prescription for both healthy and pathologically involved individuals including relevant indications and contraindications. Prerequisite: PTH 5423. </P>

<P>PTH 6326.  Physical Therapist Management of Neurological Disorders I - 90 clock hrs  </P>

<P>Concepts, principles, and procedures for application of the patient/client management model specific to neurological disorders with emphasis on spinal cord, demyelinating and lower motor neuron disorders. Prerequisite: PTH 6393 and 6273. </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>PTH 6332.  Administration &amp; Management - 30 clock hrs </P>

<P>This course will focus on the administration and management of physical therapy services. Topics of organizational structure, management theory, practice management, human resource management, motivational theory, medical-legal-political issues and agendas, fiduciary responsibility, budgeting, strategic planning, business communication, and accountability will be presented. Prerequisite: PTH 6022. </P>

<P>PTH 6393.  Motor Control and Learning - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Basic neurosciences are presented with an emphasis on current theories of motor control and learning and the application of these theories and concepts to the patient/client management model in contemporary physical therapy practice. Prerequisite: PTH 5593. </P>

<P>PTH 6472.  Pathology for Physical Therapists I - 30 clock hrs </P>

<P>General pathological conditions are presented with an emphasis on the natural course of musculoskeletal, neurologic, and systemic disorders/diseases managed by the physical therapist. Prerequisite: PTH 5047 and 6273. </P>

<P>PTH 6501. Christian Applications for the Healthcare Professional II - 15 clock hrs </P>

<P>Evaluation of life and professional healthcare purposes from the Christian perspective. Prerequisites: PTH 5481 </P>

<P>PTH 6551.  Clinical Investigations II - 15 clock hours </P>

<P>This course will focus on the development of a research proposal with applicable paperwork for human subjects review. Course Prerequisite: PTH 5151.  </P>

<P>PTH 6561.  Clinical Investigations III - 15 clock hrs </P>

<P>This course will focus on the collection and analysis of data related to the research proposal. Course Prerequisite: PTH 6551. </P>

<P>PTH 6583.  Prevention, Health Promotion, Fitness, and Wellness - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>This course presents preventive practice and is offered as a guide for health, fitness, and wellness. The purpose of this course is to broaden the student’s perspective of Physical Therapy from a clinical to a community perspective. This course will establish a foundational understanding of the opportunities, obligations, and responsibilities of the physical therapy professional in health promotion. Prerequisite: PTH 5221. </P>

<P>PTH 6603.  Pathology for Physical Therapists II - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Second part of general pathological conditions is presented with an emphasis on the natural course of musculoskeletal, neurologic and systemic disorder/diseases managed by the physical therapist.  Prerequisites: PTH 6472. </P>

<P>PTH 6621.  Professional Development Seminar II - 15 clock hrs </P>

<P>This second-year seminar focuses on the professional accountabilities of a doctoring profession in the context of becoming a servant leader in a global society.  Prerequisite: PTH 5611. </P>

<P>PTH 6651. Integrated Clinical Experience III – 40 clock hrs </P>

<P>This third semester supervised clinical field experience continues to expose the doctor of physical therapy student to an integrated and interdisciplinary approach to contemporary health care with an increased focus on application of learned skills. Course Fee: $500. </P>

<P>PTH 6671. Integrated Clinical Experience IV - 40 clock hrs </P>

<P>This fourth semester supervised clinical field experience continues to expose the doctor of physical therapy student to an integrated and interdisciplinary approach to contemporary health care with an increased focus on application of learned skills. Course Fee: $500. </P>

<P>PTH 695(1-3).  Selected Topics - 15 to 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Selected issues in physical therapy science or practice. Topics will vary depending on interest and need of student(s). </P>

<P>PTH 7158.  Clinical Education I - 8 weeks of full-time clinical education </P>

<P>Each student will spend 8 - 10 weeks in each clinical experience working full time under the supervision of a licensed physical therapist implementing the patient/client management model. Each student will have four clinical experiences one each in OP orthopedics, acute/subacute care, adult neuro rehab, and elective physical therapy area of interest. The total minimum time for clinical education is 34 weeks. The length of time and the physical therapy area of interest will be negotiated with the ACCE. Prerequisite: PTH 7362. </P>

<P>PTH 7283.  Physical Therapist Management of Cardiopulmonary Disorders - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Overview of cardiac and pulmonary pathophysiology of patients. Discussions to include life-span changes, pharmacological management, and assessment and examination procedures, including ECG, stress testing, exercise prescription, and the implementation of the patient/client management model for cardiopulmonary disorders. Prerequisite: PTH 6293. </P>

<P>PTH 7316.  Physical Therapist Management of Neurological Disorders II - 90 clock hrs </P>

<P>Concepts, principles, and procedures for application of the patient/client management model specific to neurological disorders with emphasis on brain and upper motor neuron disorders. Prerequisite: PTH 6326. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>PTH 7343.  Pediatric Physical Therapy - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Systematic, problem solving approach to the pediatric client with emphasis on prevention, etiology, clinical manifestations, and the application of the patient/client management model. Prerequisites: PTH 6082 and 6393. </P>

<P>PTH 7353.  Geriatric Physical Therapy - 45 Clock hrs </P>

<P>Biological, cultural, psychological, and sociological changes with aging are discussed. Emphasis is placed upon societal attitudes, support systems, and demographics regarding the geriatric population. Systematic and comprehensive problem solving approach to the geriatric client with emphasis on prevention, etiology, clinical manifestations, and the application of the patient/client management model. Prerequisites: PTH 6255, 7283, and 7316. </P>

<P>PTH 7362.  Capstone - 30 clock hrs </P>

<P>Capstone problem solving experience to address physical, emotional, psychosocial, spiritual, equipment, educational, and fiscal needs of patients and clients with complex and/or multi-system deficits. Emphasis on problem solving, professional behaviors, team management, documentation, and effective communication skills. Prerequisites: Successful completion of all prior didactic PT courses. </P>

<P>PTH 7458. Clinical Education II - 8-10 weeks of full-time clinical education </P>

<P>Each student will spend 8 - 10 weeks in each clinical experience working full time under the supervision of a licensed physical therapist implementing the patient/client management model. Each student will have four clinical experiences one each in OP orthopedics, acute/subacute care, adult neuro rehab, and elective physical therapy area of interest. The total minimum time for clinical education is 34 weeks. The length of time and the physical therapy area of interest will be negotiated with the ACCE. Prerequisite: PTH 7362. </P>

<P>PTH 7459.  Clinical Education III - 8-10 weeks of full-time clinical education </P>

<P>Each student will spend 8-10 weeks in each clinical experience working full time under the supervision of a licensed physical therapist implementing the patient/client management model. Each student will have four clinical experiences one each in OP orthopedics, acute/subacute care, adult neuro rehab, and elective physical therapy area of interest. The total minimum time for clinical education is 34 weeks. The length of time and the physical therapy area of interest will be negotiated with the ACCE. Prerequisite: PTH 7362. </P>

<P>PTH 7469.  Clinical Education IV - 8-10 weeks of full-time clinical education </P>

<P>Each student will spend 8-10 weeks in each clinical experience working full time under the supervision of a licensed physical therapist implementing the patient/client management model. Each student will have four clinical experiences one each in OP orthopedics, acute/subacute care, adult neuro rehab, and elective physical therapy area of interest. The total minimum time for clinical education is 34 weeks. The length of time and the physical therapy area of interest will be negotiated with the ACCE. Prerequisite: PTH 7362. </P>

<P>PTH 7479. Clinical Education V – 8 – 10 weeks of full-time clinical education </P>

<P>Each student is expected to successfully complete a minimum of 34 weeks for clinical education. At times, students may present with difficulties (e.g. behavior, academic, health) that will prevent successful completion of this expectation. This on demand course is used as a final opportunity for the student successfully earn the minimum expectation of time in the clinic. This course will substitute for PTH 7158, 7458, 7459, 7469 as a degree requirement if needed. The length of time and the physical therapy clinical area will be directed by Review Committee. Prerequisite: PTH 7362. </P>

<P>PTH 7533.  Sports Physical Therapy -  45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Prepares the student for a career as sports physical therapist. Issues related to the sports epidemiology, care, prevention and emergency management of sports related injuries as well as effective venue management will be presented. Other elements will be designing and implementing strategies to enhance human performance based in sound physiological principles and issues related to appropriate counseling and education. Prerequisite: PTH 6255. </P>

<P>PTH 7543.  Practicum in Physical Therapy - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Non traditional physical therapy experiences will be presented. This elective course is negotiated between the instructor and the student to prepare a learning practicum in a non-traditional physical therapy venue. Prerequisite: By permission only.  </P>

<P>PTH 7553. Global Learning in Physical Therapy - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>A service learning experience directed at exposing the student to global healthcare issues and venues. Prerequisite: By permission only. </P>

<P>PTH 7571.  Clinical Investigations IV - 15 clock hrs </P>

<P>This course will focus on the preparation and formal presentation of collected and analyzed data from research study. Course Prerequisite: PTH 6561. </P>

<P>PTH 7633.  Advanced Orthopedics - 45 clock hrs </P>

<P>Prepares the student for a career as an advanced orthopedic physical therapist.  Issues related to current evidence based practice and manual therapy will be presented.  Focus on professional development skills and knowledge base to pursue advanced orthopedic credentials.  Prerequisites: PTH 6255. </P>

<H1> </H1>

<H1> </H1>

<H1 id="LinkTarget_3607">THE COURTS REDFORD COLLEGE OF THEOLOGY AND MINISTRY </H1>

<P>Rodney Reeves, Dean </P>

<P>Office: Jim Mellers Center 200C (417) 328-1770 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Zach Manis, Graduate Program Director </P>

<P>Office: Jim Mellers Center 200D (417) 328-1766 </P>

<P>
<Link>http://www.sbuniv.edu/redford/</Link>
 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Mission Statement  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The Courts Redford College of Theology and Ministry endeavors from a Christian perspective to teach students the Bible, our Christian heritage, and spiritual formation, and to prepare students for professional church vocations.  </P>

<P> </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_3623">Master of Arts in Christian Ministry </H2>

<P> </P>

<P>Mission of the Program </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The mission of the Master of Arts in Christian Ministry program is to prepare men and women who are called to the ministry to apply theological studies to kingdom initiatives that build up the Church and contribute to the welfare of the community. </P>

<P>  </P>

<P>Vision of the Program </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The Master of Arts in Christian Ministry is a practical theology degree.  In contrast to undergraduate programs, in which the curriculum is divided along the lines of theoretical and practical studies, the graduate program in Redford College is thoroughly integrated, combining theological studies and ministerial studies in every course.  The intent and purpose of this integration of theory and practice is to train and equip students to apply theological knowledge to practical ministry initiatives in fruitful and innovative ways.      </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Admission Requirements and Academic Regulations </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Students may be admitted to the Master of Arts in Christian Ministry program according to the following classification categories:  </P>

<P> </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Fully Admitted – The student meets all admission standards, has completed all prerequisites, and has been admitted to the program of study.  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Conditionally Admitted </LBody>
</LI>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>a. Contingent Admission  –  Students who have not completed the academic program prerequisites are conditionally admitted to graduate study.  All students admitted to the 4+1 track will be contingently admitted.  Students admitted to the 4+2 track who have completed less than thirty hours of coursework in the relevant areas (see Prerequisites, below) will be contingently admitted.  (Students must have </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</L>

<L>
<L>
<LI>
<LBody>completed at least eighteen hours of coursework – including nine hours in the areas of biblical studies, theology, and philosophy; and nine hours in the area of ministry – to be considered for contingent admission to the 4+2 program.)  Students contingently admitted to the program will have their status changed to “Fully Admitted” if/when their prerequisites are completed.  Students may take no more than twelve semester hours of graduate courses without satisfying program prerequisites.   </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>b. Academic Probationary Admission  –  Students whose grade point average is less than 2.75 overall or 3.00 in their undergraduate majors are conditionally admitted to the program.  At the end of their first semester, or the completion of nine hours of graduate work (whichever comes first), students probationally admitted to the program will have their status changed to “Fully Admitted” if the grade point average for their graduate coursework is 3.00 or higher. Students who fail to meet this benchmark may be dismissed from the program.  The final decision either to dismiss a student from the program or to extend the student’s probational period will be made by the Graduate Program Director, in consultation with both the Dean and the student’s advisor.    </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Non-Degree-Seeking Admitted – The student meets all admission standards, has completed all prerequisites, and desires to take some courses in the program for credit, but does not intend to pursue the degree.  Students admitted to non-degree-seeking status may at a later time petition the Graduate Admissions Committee, in writing, to have their admissions status changed to a degree-seeking status (either Fully Admitted or Conditionally Admitted).  Such petitions are not automatically granted, but will be decided by the Graduate Admissions Committee.  (Note: Students who wish to take courses for personal enrichment, but not for credit, may audit courses in the program without meeting admission standards or completing the prerequisites.)   </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P> </P>

<P>The following is required of students seeking full admission to the Master of Arts in Christian Ministry program: </P>

<P> </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Bachelor’s degree from a regionally accredited college or university;   </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Minimum undergraduate grade point average of 2.75, overall, and 3.00 within major (on a 4.00 scale).  </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P> </P>

<P>In addition, applicants to the program must submit the following materials: </P>

<P> </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>3. Completed “Application for Graduate Admission” to the Master of Arts in Christian Ministry Program; </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Official transcripts from all colleges, universities, or seminaries attended; </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Graduate Admission Essay; </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>6. Three letters of recommendation that speak to the character and academic ability of the applicant: one from a college professor, one from a pastor or mentor, and one from a fellow member of the applicant’s church. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P> </P>

<P>As noted above, admission to the 4+1 track is a contingent admission.  Those applying to the 4+1 program while undergraduates at SBU must submit the same materials listed above (items 3. – 6.)  However, in the case of incoming freshmen who are applying concurrently to the SBU undergraduate program and to the 4+1 track of the graduate program in Christian Ministry, a letter of recommendation from a high school teacher may be submitted in place of a letter from a college professor, and high school transcripts may be submitted in place of college or university transcripts.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>International Students </P>

<P>International students must meet the admission requirements for the M.A. program.  Official records not in English must be accompanied by an official translated record.  All records should show the individual subjects studied and the grades received in each subject.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Prerequisites </P>

<P>The Master of Arts in Christian Ministry program requires that students have prior knowledge in certain areas of study before fully pursuing the M.A.  The purpose of these prerequisites is twofold: (1) to promote a greater likelihood of student success in completing the program; (2) to facilitate instructors of graduate courses in designing course content (establishing reasonable expectations concerning the background knowledge of students enrolling in the courses).  To satisfy each prerequisite, students must have completed the course or an approved equivalent from a regionally accredited institution, having earned a grade of C or better.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The prerequisites for the M.A. in Christian Ministry are as follows: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody> Either (i) a major in biblical studies, theology, philosophy, ministry, intercultural studies, Christian studies, or religious studies, or (ii) 30+ hours of undergraduate coursework (2000-level or above) in these areas.   </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody> The coursework completed in the aforementioned areas must include the following courses or some transfer equivalency:  </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>BIB 2093 Methods of Biblical Interpretation  </P>

<P>CHR 3013 Introduction to Ministry </P>

<P>PHI 2013 Philosophical Foundations for a Christian Worldview </P>

<P>THE 3113 Christian Doctrine </P>

<P>THE 3463 History of Christianity I or THE 3673 History of Christianity II </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Transfer Credit  </P>

<P>Nine graduate semester hours completed at another regionally accredited institution may be transferred and applied to the degree. These credits must be comparable to courses offered in the M.A. program in Christian Ministry at SBU and must be approved by the Graduate Admissions Committee.    </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Academic Probation  </P>

<P>Graduate students must earn a grade of C or higher to receive credit for a graduate course towards the completion of the degree. Graduate students whose overall GPA falls below 3.00 will be placed on a status of academic probation.  Students placed on academic probation must raise their overall GPA to a minimum of 3.00 by the end of the following semester—or, in the case of a student who is taking less than nine hours per semester, at the completion of nine additional credit hours—in order to be returned to non-probational status.  Students who fail to meet this benchmark may be dismissed from the program. The final decision either to dismiss a student from the program or to extend the student’s probational period will be made by the Graduate Program Director, in consultation with both the Dean and the student’s advisor. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Degree Requirements </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Students are eligible to graduate after fulfilling the requirements described below.  Students who enroll in another college or university without prior permission of the Graduate Program Director are considered to have withdrawn from Southwest Baptist University.  Students wishing to transfer work from another institution and not withdraw from Southwest Baptist University must obtain prior approval from the Graduate Program Director as well as the Dean of the Redford College of Theology and Ministry.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Master of Arts in Christian Ministry </P>

<P>To receive the M.A. degree, a student must: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Meet all graduate admission standards, including completion of a baccalaureate degree, and completion of admission application and file.  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Complete a plan of graduate study consisting of at least 42 semester hours.   </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Maintain a graduate level GPA of at least 3.00 on a 4.00 scale with no grade below a C (2.00).  Students receiving two grades of “F” are automatically dismissed from the graduate program.  Students may reapply for admission after a mandatory one-year suspension.  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Complete all degree requirements within five years of being fully admitted to the program.  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Participate in commencement exercises unless absence is approved by the Provost.  </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P> </P>

<P>Program of Study </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The Master of Arts in Christian Ministry is a non-thesis, 42-hour degree, culminating in a Ministry Project Capstone.  The program is designed for students who have (or are seeking) a bachelor’s degree in Christian ministry, biblical studies, intercultural studies, Christian studies, religious studies, theology, or philosophy, and who desire advanced study in ministry in order to serve the Church more purposefully.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Students must complete four CORE courses (12 hours), nine electives (27 hours), and the Ministry Project Capstone (3 hours). The program of study will be designed by the student and faculty advisor, informed by the student’s ministry goals and the courses offered.  A typical full-time student will enroll in nine to twelve credit hours per fall and spring semester (with </P>

<P>a reduced course load for the final semester, in which the Ministry Project Capstone takes place), three credit hours per summer term, and three credit hours per Winterfest term.  No more than twelve credit hours of graduate coursework will be allowed in a single semester.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>There are two tracks for pursuing the M.A. degree in Christian Ministry: a “4+1” track and a “4+2” track.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The 4+2 track is for students who have already graduated with a bachelor’s degree.  On this track, the degree is designed to be completed in two years.  The following is a typical program of study for those on the 4+2 track: </P>

<P> </P>

<P>First year graduate  </P>

<P>Fall: 9 hours  </P>

<P>Winterfest: 3 hours  </P>

<P>Spring: 9 hours  </P>

<P>Summer: 3 hours </P>

<P>Second year graduate </P>

<P>Fall: 9 hours  </P>

<P>Winterfest: 3 hours  </P>

<P>Spring: 6 hours (including Ministry Project Capstone) </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The 4+1 track is for incoming or current SBU undergraduate students who anticipate getting both their bachelor’s and master’s degrees at SBU in a span of five years total.  Students may concurrently enroll in up to twelve hours of specially designated upper-level Redford courses that will count for both their undergraduate and graduate requirements (see Concurrent Enrollment Courses, below).  The following is a typical program of study for those on the 4+1 track: </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Second semester junior undergraduate (80+ hours completed) </P>

<P> Spring: 3 hours (concurrent enrollment) </P>

<P>Senior undergraduate </P>

<P>Fall: 3 - 6 hours (concurrent enrollment)  </P>

<P>Spring: 3 - 6 hours (concurrent enrollment) </P>

<P>First year graduate </P>

<P>Summer: 3 hours </P>

<P>  Fall: 9 - 12 hours  </P>

<P>Winterfest: 3 hours  </P>

<P>Spring: 9 - 12 hours </P>

<P>Summer: 3 hours (Ministry Project Capstone)  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Concurrent Enrollment Courses </P>

<P>SBU undergraduates who have been admitted to the program (4+1 track) and have completed 80+ hours of coursework and all course prerequisites are eligible to enroll concurrently in the following courses.  Students who successfully complete these courses will receive both undergraduate credit (appearing on the student's transcript as a 3000 or 4000 level course credit) and graduate credit (appearing on the student's transcript as a 5000 level course credit).  Students may earn up to twelve hours of graduate credit through concurrent enrollment.  Graduate students currently enrolled in the M.A. program are also eligible to take the following courses for graduate credit.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The list of approved concurrent enrollment courses for the M.A. program is as follows: </P>

<P>BIB 3033   / MIN 5033 Old Testament Hymnic and Wisdom Literature </P>

<P>BIB 3053   / MIN 5053 Early Pauline Epistles </P>

<P>CED 4053  / MIN 5063  Youth Discipleship and Evangelism </P>

<P>ICS 4023    / MIN 5023 Indigenous Christian Community </P>

<P>PHI 4243  / MIN 5013 The Problem of Evil  </P>

<P>THE 4043  / MIN 5043 Christ and Salvation </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>CORE Courses </P>

<P>Students are required to take four CORE courses, one from each of the following categories: Leadership, Theology, Community, and Service.  For each category, students will choose between two courses that are eligible to fulfill the requirement.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Leadership:   Leadership and the Old Testament or Preaching and Teaching the Bible </P>

<P>Theology:   Christian Theological Traditions or Contemporary Christian Theologies </P>

<P>Community:   Kingdom and Society or Church and Community </P>

<P>Service:   Theology and Practice of the Local Church or Disciple-Making in Context </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Electives </P>

<P>Students are required to take at least nine elective courses.  The M.A. in Christian Ministry is designed to be a flexible program, allowing students to select courses that emphasize areas of study that are conducive to attaining the student’s own vocational and ministry goals. Towards this end, each student will work closely with a faculty advisor in designing an appropriate schedule.  The following is the list of courses from which students will choose to fulfill the electives requirement of the M.A. program: </P>

<P> </P>

<P>MIN 5013 The Problem of Evil  </P>

<P>MIN 5023 Indigenous Christian Community </P>

<P>MIN 5033 Old Testament Hymnic and Wisdom Literature </P>

<P>MIN 5043 Christ and Salvation </P>

<P>MIN 5053 Early Pauline Epistles </P>

<P>MIN 5063  Youth Discipleship and Evangelism </P>

<P>MIN 5073 The Ministry of Worship  </P>

<P>MIN 5103 Leadership and the Old Testament </P>

<P>MIN 5113  Preaching and Teaching the Bible </P>

<P>MIN 5123 Christian Theological Traditions </P>

<P>MIN 5133 Christian Theological Ethics </P>

<P>MIN 5143 Kingdom and Society </P>

<P>MIN 5153 Church and Community </P>

<P>MIN 5163 Theology and Practice of the Local Church </P>

<P>MIN 5173 Disciple-Making in Context </P>

<P>MIN 5203 The Teaching Ministry of Jesus </P>

<P>MIN 5213 Equipping to Serve </P>

<P>MIN 5223 A Practical Theology for Youth Ministry </P>

<P>MIN 5233 Issues in Global Christian Theologies </P>

<P>MIN 5403 Knowledge and Mystery </P>

<P>MIN 5413 Good and Evil </P>

<P>MIN 5423 Heaven and Hell </P>

<P>MIN 5433 Contemporary Christian Theologies </P>

<P>MIN 5453 The Ministry of Leadership </P>

<P>MIN 5463 Patristic Theology </P>

<P>MIN 5473 Puritan Spirituality </P>

<P> </P>

<P>No single course can be counted toward both the CORE and electives requirements.  However, students who take one of the CORE classes in a certain category may then take the other class in the “pairing” as an elective: for example, a student who takes MIN 5103 (Leadership and the Old Testament) for the Leadership category of the CORE may then take MIN 5113 (Preaching and Teaching the Bible) as an elective.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Ministry Project Capstone </P>

<P>The ministry capstone course (MIN 5983) and project serves as both an application and a substantive assessment of what the student has learned from the Master of Arts in Christian Ministry program.  It is comprised of an in-class component and an off-site component.  The former is a team-taught course involving regular meetings throughout the semester in a classroom setting.  The latter is a student-designed project, developed in consultation with the student’s advisor, the Graduate Program Director, and an on-site supervisor at a church or parachurch organization where the ministry will take place, and guided and evaluated by the student’s Capstone Committee.   </P>

<P>Initially, the project proposal will be developed by the student and presented to his/her advisor at the time of the portfolio review.  The portfolio review must take place within two weeks of the beginning of MIN 5983.  The portfolio consists of all major assessments, including midterm and final papers, along with any exams that the student was allowed by his/her professors to keep.  The student will discuss the portfolio with the advisor, addressing in particular the issue of how the proposed ministry capstone project will build upon the body of knowledge and work that the students has completed up to that point.  The proposed ministry project must involve a minimum of 200 hours of field work, and the proposal must include a timetable for completion of the project.   </P>

<P>Once the advisor is satisfied that the project is viable and well-conceived, the student will consult with the Graduate Program Director, who will either approve the project, or, if the project is judged to be deficient in some way, send the student back to the advisor for further consultation.  In the event of the latter, the Director’s reservations must be expressed in writing, and copies sent to both the student and the advisor.  The process will then repeat until approval of the proposal is granted by the Graduate Program Director. </P>

<P>Once the project has been approved, the student will begin the project in accordance with the agreed upon timetable.  Guidance for the project throughout, and evaluation of the project at its completion, will come from the student’s Capstone Committee.  The Capstone Committee is comprised of the student’s advisor, the  Graduate Program Director, and one of the faculty members co-teaching MIN 5983 during the semester in which the student’s project takes place.  (In certain cases, two of these roles could be fulfilled by the same individual, in which case the student’s Capstone Committee will be comprised of only two members.)   </P>

<P>Immediate oversight for the project will come from a designated individual at the church / parachurch organization with which the student is working. Students must make arrangements with the organization for this oversight to take place, and details of the arrangement must be included in the proposal and thus approved by the student’s advisor and the Graduate Program Director. This on-site supervisor is not a part of the Capstone Committee, but will advise the Committee on the student’s progress and quality of work.  The supervisor will be asked to give a monthly report to the members of the Capstone Committee, who will consult with the student in the case of any concerns.  Further guidance will be provided by the classroom meetings of MIN 5983, in which ideas, insights, challenges, concerns, etc. associated with the students’ developing ministry projects will be shared, discussed, and addressed. </P>

<P>At the completion of the project, the student will write up an evaluation / self-assessment of the project, and will then meet with the members of the Capstone Committee for a final review. Following the review, the members of the Committee will meet to decide on a grade for the ministry project / capstone course, which the Director will then report to the student.     </P>

<P>The following is required for successful completion of the requirements of the Ministry Project Capstone: </P>

<P>1. Assemble a portfolio of all assignments for the M.A. program. </P>

<P>2. Create and implement a Master’s Ministry Project in a (typically local) church or parachurch organization. </P>

<P>3. Evaluate and present the Master’s Ministry Project. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Program Summary – M.A. in Christian Ministry (42 credit hours) </P>

<P> </P>

<P>CORE Requirements (12 hours) </P>

<P>MIN 5103 Leadership and the Old Testament or </P>

<P>MIN 5113 Preaching and Teaching the Bible ................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>MIN 5123 Christian Theological Traditions or  </P>

<P>MIN 5433  Contemporary Christian Theologies ............................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>MIN 5143 Kingdom and Society or  </P>

<P>MIN 5153  Church and Community .................................................................................. 3 hours </P>

<P>MIN 5163 Theology and Practice of the Local Church or  </P>

<P>MIN 5173  Disciple-Making in Context ............................................................................ 3 hours </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Electives (27 hours) </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Ministry Project Capstone (3 hours) </P>

<P>MIN 5983 Ministry Project Capstone ............................................................................... 3 hours</P>

<P> </P>

<P>COURSE DESCRIPTIONS </P>

<P> </P>

<P>MINISTRY </P>

<P>MIN 5013. The Problem of Evil – 3 hours </P>

<P>An exploration of the logical and evidential forms of the problem of evil and the different types of responses that have been developed to address each, with special attention given to the problem of horrendous evils. </P>

<P>MIN 5023. Indigenous Christian Community – 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of principles concerning an indigenous, culturally contextualized, biblical Christian community in terms of its worship, discipling, leadership call and roles, pastoral care, social structures, world-view formation, and cell multiplication. </P>

<P>MIN 5033. Old Testament Hymnic and Wisdom Literature – 3 hours </P>

<P>Historical and exegetical study of the hymnic and wisdom literature in the Old Testament: Job, Psalm, Proverbs, Ecclesiastes and Song of Solomon. </P>

<P>MIN 5043. Christ and Salvation – 3 hours </P>

<P>A survey of Christian understandings of Christ and salvation in their biblical, historical and contemporary expressions, including the person of Christ, atonement, justification and other dimensions of salvation. </P>

<P>MIN 5053. Early Pauline Epistles – 3 hours </P>

<P>Historical and exegetical study of Paul's epistles to the Thessalonians, Corinthians and Galatians. </P>

<P>MIN 5063. Youth Discipleship and Evangelism – 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of (1) the challenges of youth and their culture (including suicide, pregnancy, parental problems, drugs) and (2) evangelism strategies, events and programs designed to reach unchurched youth. </P>

<P>MIN 5073. The Ministry of Worship – 3 hours  </P>

<P>An introduction to the principles and practice of Christian worship, including the Biblical foundations of worship, the historical heritage and models for worship, contemporary options in worship, and praxis in worship. </P>

<P>MIN 5103.  Leadership and the Old Testament – 3 hours </P>

<P>The study of Old Testament texts and persons with the goal of formulating a biblical theology of leadership and designing a practical plan for personal growth in leadership. </P>

<P>MIN 5113.  Preaching and Teaching the Bible – 3 hours </P>

<P>An historical, biblical, and clinical study of preaching with the goal to communicate the meaning and significance of the Bible accurately, clearly, and persuasively to the contemporary audience. </P>

<P>MIN 5123.  Christian Theological Traditions – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course surveys some major traditions in the history of Christian theology, beginning with their common roots in the patristic era, and including the traditions of both East and West, up to the modern era (seventeenth century). </P>

<P>MIN 5133.  Christian Theological Ethics – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course surveys the shape of Christian ethics, including its biblical and theological basis, options for ethical decision making, moral agency and norms of justice, and specific ethical issues such as economic and ecological justice, sexuality, violence and peacemaking. </P>

<P>MIN 5143.  Kingdom and Society – 3 hours </P>

<P>Kingdom and Society is designed to introduce students to the methods Jesus used to establish the kingdom of God.  We will study the gospels in relation to how Jesus’ kingdom building work via the parables, miracles, and itinerant ministry should give guidance today in seeking justice for the marginalized of our society. </P>

<P>MIN 5153.  Church and Community – 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of Paul’s letters to determine how the apostle encouraged mutual dependence (fellowship) to forge the bonds of Christian unity and inspire community service.  In particular, we will examine the theological, social, political, and historical contexts of his letters in order to understand the source of Paul’s authority, his methods of ministry, and his understanding of the church’s mission. </P>

<P>MIN 5163.  Theology and Practice of the Local Church – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course explores the biblical and theological basis for the local church as well as church’s mission and ministry in the contemporary setting. The goal is to prepare students for ministry in a local church in a way that will contribute to the transformation of the surrounding community. </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>MIN 5173.  Disciple-Making in Context – 3 hours  </P>

<P>A study of the theology and practice of individual and corporate disciple-making in the context of both the local church and community. The purpose is to move students toward the development and application of a disciple-making process contextualized for a specific community. </P>

<P>MIN 5203.  The Teaching Ministry of Jesus – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course focuses on the teaching ministry of Jesus.  Subjects include biblical instances of Jesus’ teaching, methodologies, subjects, students, and the church. </P>

<P>MIN 5213.  Equipping to Serve – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course will focus on equipping church members to serve the Kingdom of God. </P>

<P>MIN 5223.  A Practical Theology for Youth Ministry – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course will build a theology for the importance and implementation of a theology for youth ministry.  The first half will focus on theology and the second will focus on how to teach and implement how the church, families, and youth can be theological. </P>

<P>MIN 5233.  Issues in Global Christian Theologies – 3 hours  </P>

<P>A study of key issues related to the development of Christian theology in global perspective. Particular interest will be placed on non-Western theologies from Latin America, Africa and Asia. Application will focus on preparing students for theological engagement in the developing global Christian movement. </P>

<P>MIN 5403.  Knowledge and Mystery – 3 hours  </P>

<P>A philosophical exploration of the nature and limits of theological knowledge, with special emphasis on the application of philosophical insight to spiritual formation, practical theology, and ministry.   </P>

<P>MIN 5413.  Good and Evil – 3 hours  </P>

<P>A philosophical exploration of the nature of good and evil, and the problems attending each, with special emphasis on the application of philosophical insight to spiritual formation, practical theology, and ministry.   </P>

<P>MIN 5423.  Heaven and Hell – 3 hours  </P>

<P>A philosophical exploration of heaven and hell, and the problems attending each, with special emphasis on the application of philosophical insight to spiritual formation, practical theology, and ministry.   </P>

<P>MIN 5433.  Contemporary Christian Theologies – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course surveys the shape Christian theology has taken in the West, in response to modern and postmodern challenges, beginning with the Enlightenment and continuing to the present day. </P>

<P>MIN 5453.  The Ministry of Leadership – 3 hours  </P>

<P>An introduction to the unique nature and functions of the vocational minister as a servant leader. </P>

<P>MIN 5463.  Patristic Theology – 3 hours  </P>

<P>Patristic Theology is a course designed to introduce students to the doctrine of early Christians, the exploring of which may serve as a source to enrich both personal spirituality and ministry. </P>

<P>MIN 5473.  Puritan Spirituality – 3 hours  </P>

<P>Puritan Spirituality is a course that is meant to introduce students to both spirituality and Puritanism generally, while giving primary attention to the specific beliefs and practices of the people called Puritans as a stimulus for the contemporary church. </P>

<P>MIN 5983.  Ministry Project Capstone – 3 hours  </P>

<P>A capstone course and ministry project that serves as a substantive assessment of what the student has learned in the Master of Arts in Christian Ministry program.</P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<H1 id="LinkTarget_3908">MERCY COLLEGE OF NURSING AND HEALTH SCIENCES </H1>

<P>Dean:  TBD </P>

<P>Office: 4431 S. Fremont St. </P>

<P>Springfield, MO  65804 (417) 820-2069 </P>

<P>
<Link>http://mercy.sbuniv.edu/</Link>
 </P>

<P> </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_3918">Master of Science in Nursing </H2>

<P>Interim Chair:  TBD </P>

<P>Faculty:  Cozi Bagley, Dana Hunt </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Calendar </P>

<P>Fall 2018 </P>

<P>Fall Online ............................................. August 21 </P>

<P>Fall Session #1 ....................................... August 21 </P>

<P>Last day to withdraw from classes without academic penalty (1st 8 week session) ................... September 19 </P>

<P>Last day of classes 1st 8 week session .... October 11 </P>

<P>Fall Session #2 ....................................... October 16 </P>

<P>Last day to withdraw from classes without academic penalty (2nd 8 week session) .................. November 13 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Spring 2019 </P>

<P>Spring Online ......................................... January 24 </P>

<P>Spring Session #1 .................................. January 24 </P>

<P>Last day to withdraw from classes without academic penalty (1st 8 week session) ................... February 21 </P>

<P>Last Day of classes 1st 8 week session ... March 16 </P>

<P>Spring Session #2 ................................... March 26 </P>

<P>Last day to withdraw from classes without academic penalty (2nd 8 week session) ................... April 23 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Summer 2019 </P>

<P>Summer Online ...................................... June 4 </P>

<P>First Summer Session............................. June 4 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Deadlines for Intent to Graduate Card </P>

<P>Fall 2018 ................................................ September 10 </P>

<P>Spring 2019 ............................................ February10 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Graduation Date </P>

<P>Graduate Commencement Ceremony .... May 19 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Program Mission and Outcomes </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The MSN program is designed for the registered nurse who has a bachelor’s degree in nursing. Candidates for this program must be graduates of a nationally accredited nursing program. It is a blended online and traditional seated program for nurses who want to attain a master’s degree. The program prepares nurses for advanced nursing roles with a sequence of core courses plus additional course work that allows students to specialize in one of two concentrations:  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Nursing Education </P>

<P>Nurses are prepared to function in academic, staff development, or patient education roles. The program provides an excellent foundation in nursing knowledge, leadership and research skills, and adult educational theory and strategies. For individuals who plan to teach nursing at a baccalaureate or graduate level, this program will prepare them for doctoral study.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Nursing Administration  </P>

<P>Nurses develop knowledge and skills to influence effective change in health care systems. The application of nursing and leadership theories, economic and finance principles, business management practices, and interdisciplinary collaborative strategies are explored.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>MSN Program Outcomes: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Integrate skills in critical thinking, information management, and systematic inquiry into the advanced nursing practice role (Clinical Judgment). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Utilize advanced communication processes to influence health care, health care policy, and advanced professional nursing practice (Communication). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Synthesize knowledge from concepts, theories, principles and research in nursing in the planning and delivery of holistic evidence based health care that is responsive to changing needs and societal trends for a multicultural population (Evidence Based Practice). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Assume leadership, responsibility and accountability for value based decision-making in the advanced practice role (Professionalism). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Develop a conscious application and assimilation of the principles of Christian discipleship in the implementation of the advanced practice role (Christian Discipleship). </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Assessment </P>

<P> </P>

<P>In the Master of Science in Nursing degree program, periodic measurements of student perceptions and intellectual growth are obtained as one means for the University to assess and improve its academic programs and student learning.  The information obtained is used to measure and develop student competencies and to determine and improve the quality of the educational experience for students. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>All students seeking the Master of Science in Nursing in either education or administration are required to take the Comprehensive Examination and Masters Project and Practicum for the purpose of demonstrating that the program and specialty outcomes have been met. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Comprehensive Examination </P>

<P>Each student is required to pass a comprehensive examination in the last semester of their program during NUR 5523 Master’s Project and Practicum course. The Comprehensive Exam is a synthesis and evaluation of the MSN Program level student learning outcomes and either the Nursing Education or Nursing Administration specialty student learning outcomes, which includes an oral presentation of the student’s Master’s Project. The oral presentation is evaluated by the graduate faculty. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Admission Requirements </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Admission to Unclassified Status </P>

<P>Students who do not wish to pursue a degree but who are eligible for graduate study may take up to six graduate credit hours in the College of Nursing.  The ability to transfer credit for the courses completed toward the graduate program at SBU, or another college or university, depends upon the course of study provided at the time of transfer by the receiving program.  Applicants who have not completed the application process are also placed in this status until requirements are met </P>

<P> </P>

<P>MSN Admission Requirements </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Bachelor of Science in Nursing (BSN) degree from an accredited college or university. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Cumulative GPA of 3.0 or better in nursing course work. If the student's GPA is less than 3.0 on a 4.0 scale, submission of Graduate Record Examination (GRE) scores are required.  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Verification of Current and Unencumbered License as Registered Nurse in the State of Missouri/Nurse Licensure Compact or eligible for licensure. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>4. Satisfactory completion of Background Check and Urine Drug Screening (Includes Criminal Background check, Family Care and Safety Registry Background Check, and Urine drug test). Final acceptance into the MSN program is contingent on satisfactory background check and drug screen findings.  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Submission of the following documents by all applicants: </LBody>
</LI>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>a. MSN Application </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>b. Official Transcript(s) from all prior nursing programs- must be sent directly to the Mercy College of Nursing and Health Sciences (Attn: Admissions/MSN Department) </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>c. Current CPR certification verification </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>d. Copy of Driver’s License or Photo ID </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>e. Submission of Two Professional References (from faculty, employer, or others who can address the applicant’s potential to succeed in graduate study- Reference Forms provided) </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>f. Submission of Professional Essay (No longer than two pages outlining how a MSN will facilitate the accomplishment of the applicant’s professional goals and career path.) </LBody>
</LI>
</L>
</L>

<P>Transfer Credit </P>

<P>Nine graduate semester hours completed at another regionally accredited institution may be transferred and applied to the degree.  These credits must be comparable to courses offered at Southwest Baptist University and must be approved by the MSN Faculty and Dean. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Progression in the MSN Program </P>

<P>Students must achieve a grade of “C” or better in all MSN courses. If a student fails a course with a “D” or below, they will be permitted to repeat the course one (1) time. The student is placed on academic probation by the Dean of the College of Nursing and Health Sciences. The Dean will monitor the student’s progress in the program and may prescribe additional support activities to promote student success in the program. Any MSN student who fails two (2) nursing courses or fails the same course twice may not be allowed to progress in the MSN program and can be dismissed. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Degree Requirements </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Students are eligible to graduate after fulfilling the requirements described below.  Students who enroll in another college or university without prior permission of the Dean of the College of Nursing and Health Sciences are considered to have withdrawn from Southwest Baptist University.  Students wishing to transfer work from another institution and not withdraw from Southwest Baptist University must obtain prior approval from the Dean of the College of Nursing and Health Sciences. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Program of Study and Academic Regulations </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The MSN degree program will consist of 39-42 credit hours. The nursing education specialty is 42 hours and the nursing administration specialty is 39 credit hours. The MSN program is based on the belief that graduate education builds on previous knowledge, experience and degrees. The following plan of study provides the MSN student with core knowledge and concepts from which to build a specialty practice in nursing education or administration. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Master of Science  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Master of Science in Nursing Core Classes (18 hours) </P>

<P>NUR 5013  Nursing Science ................................................................................................ 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5033  Concepts of Advanced Practice Nursing ........................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5043  Ethics and Policy Issues in Advanced Practice ................................................. 3 hours  </P>

<P>NUR 5083  Nursing Research .............................................................................................. 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5123  Information Systems ......................................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5533  Statistics and Data Analysis for Nursing ........................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Master of Science in Nursing Education (24 hours) </P>

<P>NUR 5053  Foundational Perspectives of Nursing Education ............................................. 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5213  Teaching and Learning Principles of Nursing Education .................................. 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5223  Evaluation in Nursing Education ...................................................................... 3 hours  </P>

<P>NUR 5313  Advanced Pathophysiology ............................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5323  Advanced Health Assessment and Promotion ................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5333  Advanced Pharmacology................................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 550(1-3) Nursing Education Practicum ....................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5523  Masters Project and Practicum .......................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Nurse Education Specialty Outcomes </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Utilize critical thinking skills to integrate education theories, technology, and professional standards into the design, implementation and evaluation of curriculum (Clinical Judgment).  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Determine interventions to evaluate learning and curricular outcomes in nursing education (Evidence Based Practice).  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Analyze ethical, political, organizational, cultural, technological, and professional influences on nursing education (Professionalism). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Develop research based educational strategies for multicultural diverse students (Communication).  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Integrate the principles of Christian discipleship and a Christian worldview into the development of nursing education systems (Christian Discipleship).  </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Master of Science in Nursing Administration (21 hours) </P>

<P>NUR 5023  Health Care Finance .......................................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5073  Human Resource Management in Health Care ................................................. 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5093  Organizational Analysis and Innovation ........................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5103  Health Care Organizations ................................................................................ 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5113  Advanced Health Care Leadership and Administration .................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5153  Quality and Safety in Health Care ..................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5523  Master’s Project and Practicum ......................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>Electives: </P>

<P>NUR 5053 Foundational Perspectives of Nursing Education ...…………………………... 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5213 Teaching and Learning Principles of Nursing Education …………………… .. 3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5223 Evaluation in Nursing Education ………………………………………………3 hours </P>

<P>NUR 5501-3 Nursing Education Practicum ………………………………………………..3 hours </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Nursing Administration Specialty Outcomes </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Utilize critical thinking skills to determine effective strategies that stimulate change within nursing that lead to a more effective management of health care delivery systems (Clinical Judgment). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Collaborate with interdisciplinary teams using advanced communication to promote health care systems growth and effectiveness for diverse populations (Communication). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Apply the principles of nursing and leadership theories, economic and finance principles, business management practices, and cultural competency to the delivery of health care (Evidence Based Practice). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Demonstrate leadership qualities and administrative expertise in making value based accountable decisions in the management, coordination, and delivery of nursing care (Professionalism). </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Integrate the principles of Christian discipleship and a Christian worldview into the management of personnel, health care resources, and access to care and attention to vulnerable populations (Christian Discipleship).  </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>COURSE DESCRIPTIONS </P>

<P> </P>

<P>NURSING </P>

<P>NUR 5013. Nursing Science – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course addresses nursing science and its evolution in the use of models/theories in advanced practice nursing.  Emphasis is on the study and critique of nursing and behavioral theory and frameworks, development of a concept analysis, and writing a personal philosophy of the nursing meta-paradigm.  </P>

<P>NUR 5023. Health Care Finance – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course provides students with information on the application of financial management techniques in the health care industry.  Particular emphasis is placed on understanding the unique problems facing health care in the financial relationships among hospitals, patients, physicians and other providers, insurance, capital suppliers and governmental agencies. </P>

<P>NUR 5033. Concepts of Advanced Practice Nursing – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This MSN introductory course presents foundational components of advanced nursing practice including the roles of leadership, advocacy, technology, quality and safety, evidence-based practice, interprofessional collaboration, and scholarship.  The history of advanced practice nursing and role acquisition are investigated and a framework for completion of a master’s project is introduced. </P>

<P>NUR 5043. Ethics and Policy Issues in Advanced Practice – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course provides an examination of health care policy processes and issues at organizational and governmental levels, as well as critical analysis of ethics, principal ethical theories and contemporary health care ethical issues relating to individuals and society.  Ethics from a Christian moral perspective will be analyzed and their application to public policy discussed. </P>

<P>NUR 5053. Foundational Perspectives of Nursing Education – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course provides in-depth examination of major philosophies of education and their relation to teaching practice, methods, curriculum, and educational administration. Philosophies examined include idealism, adult learning theory, behaviorism, brain-based theory, constructivism, multiple intelligences, and social learning theory. Their application to nursing education and clinical nursing education are integrated into the course. </P>

<P>NUR 5073. Human Resource Management in Health Care – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course examines the complexities and multiple issues involved in human resources management in health care organizations.  Students will examine the strategic role of human resource management in response to changes in the health care industry.  In addition, issues such as recruitment, retention, performance management, organizational development, and employee relations are examined.  Federal, state, and professional regulatory requirements specific to health care are emphasized. </P>

<P>NUR 5083. Nursing Research – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course examines methods of problem solving and decision making in nursing and explores research methodology for nursing practice.  Guidance is provided to use research knowledge and methods to identify appropriate solutions and outcomes for clinical situations.   </P>

<P>NUR 5093. Organizational Analysis and Innovation – 3 hours  </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is to learn the complex dynamics of organizational process, structure, culture and outcomes, as well as the method of organizational analysis.  Also included are large and small organizational responses and resistance to change and innovation, as well as methods of fostering creativity and positive change. </P>

<P>NUR 5103. Health Care Organizations – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course examines historical perspectives and the current U.S. health care system and health care delivery models. Factors influencing the health care delivery system including managed care, cost, access, and quality of care, health services for vulnerable populations and leadership principles are emphasized. Students analyze the U.S. health care system on a global perspective with countries offering universal health care plans.  </P>

<P>NUR 5113. Advanced Health Care Leadership &amp; Administration – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course prepares leaders who facilitate and integrate complex structures and processes in health care systems.  This course provides an understanding of partnerships, accountability, continuum-defined health care systems, self-managed teams and value-based organizations. </P>

<P>NUR 5123/4123. Information Systems – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course is an advanced course that combines knowledge of computer science, information systems, and nursing science to assist in the management and processing of nursing data, information, knowledge, and wisdom to support nursing practice and to improve the delivery of nursing care.  Students will learn how information systems design and selection, health care decision support, and clinical guidelines impact the delivery of health care. Students will </P>

<P>explore a comprehensive approach to system selection, evaluation, and implementation, project management, and regulatory policies that impact health care. Prerequisite:  Undergraduate Informatics course.  *This course is eligible for concurrent credit in the BSN program:  BSN course number NUR 4123.  </P>

<P>NUR 5153. Quality and Safety in Health Care – 3 hours  </P>

<P>The focus of this course is to examine the relationship of patient safety and quality in nursing and the health care profession.  The goal is to introduce fundamentals of patient safety, evaluation of quality, quality measures, and concepts of quality improvement.  The student is introduced to the rationale for performance management and the role of the governing body of the health care organization in ensuring compliance with the standards of regulatory and accreditation organizations.  Improving the quality, safety, and value of health care involves a multi-disciplinary approach and diverse knowledge. </P>

<P>NUR 5213. Teaching &amp; Learning Principles of Nursing Education – 3 hours  </P>

<P>The course examines current trends in nursing education, curriculum design and implementation, and the role of the nurse educator in teaching and learning. Students will explore a variety of teaching styles and the influence that technology, distance learning and alternative methods of teaching have on curricular design and implementation.  </P>

<P>NUR 5223. Evaluation in Nursing Education – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course focuses on the roles of the educator in evaluating contemporary nursing education. The opportunity to design, refine, and evaluate teaching and learning experiences for settings such as nursing programs, staff development, and/or continuing education opportunities are provided. Emphasis is on extending an understanding of adult learning principles and evidence-based teaching and evaluation strategies appropriate for nursing education.  </P>

<P>NUR 5313. Advanced Pathophysiology – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course focuses on the pathogenesis of human disease based on a molecular and cellular framework.  Regulatory and compensatory mechanisms that aim at maintaining and restoring homeostasis in response to changes in the internal and external environment are explored.  Students are encouraged to apply critical thinking processes of deduction, induction, analysis, and synthesis in integrating pathophysiologic alterations encountered in their clinical practice with the theoretical framework presented in class. Prerequisite: Undergraduate Pathophysiology course.  </P>

<P>NUR 5323. Advanced Health Assessment &amp; Promotion – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide the master’s prepared nurse with an advanced understanding of principles of physical assessment and health promotion to enhance application in advanced practice settings. Utilizing didactic and clinical practice components, this course will assist the graduate to develop refined analytical skills, connect theory and practice, and articulate viewpoints and positions based on evidence-based research and practice guidelines.  This course combines one (1) hour of clinical (= 60 clinical hours) with two (2) hours of didactic.  Completion of clinical component for the course (60 clinical hours) is required. ($100 Clinical Fee) Prerequisite: Undergraduate Health Assessment course. </P>

<P>NUR 5333. Advanced Pharmacology – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course is designed to provide the master's prepared nurse with an advanced understanding of pharmacotherapeutic principles to enhance application in advanced practice settings. This course will assist the graduate to develop refined analytical skills, connect theory and practice, and articulate viewpoints and positions based on evidence-based research. </P>

<P>NUR 550(1-3). Nursing Education Practicum – 3 hours (3 credit hours = 180 clinical hours/1 credit hour = 60 clinical hours) </P>

<P>This course prepares students for advanced nursing roles by providing opportunities to apply clinical skills, knowledge, attitudes, and values of the nurse leader and educator in an organizational context. Students will develop individual practicum goals and evaluate their learning through completion of clinical hours in advanced nursing roles. Completion of 180 clinical hours for the course is required. ($100 Clinical Fee) Prerequisites: NUR 5053. Foundational Perspectives of Education &amp; NUR 5213. Teaching &amp; Learning Principles of Nursing Education </P>

<P>NUR 5523. Master’s Project &amp; Practicum – 3 hours  </P>

<P>This course provides an application of nursing skills, leadership principles, and knowledge gained throughout the MSN program into a student centered Master’s Project. Students will develop individual practicum goals and evaluate their learning through completion of clinical hours in advanced nursing roles specific to their specialty track of nursing education or nursing administration. At the end of this course, students complete a comprehensive exam presentation as a synthesis and evaluation of the MSN Program level student learning outcomes and the Nursing Education or Nursing Administration specialty student learning outcomes.  Completion of 180 clinical hours for the course is required. One credit hour is equivalent to 60 clinical hours. Students complete this course in the last semester of the MSN program. ($100 Clinical Fee) </P>

<P> </P>

<P> </P>

<P>NUR 5533/4533. Statistics &amp; Data Analysis for Nursing- 3 hours </P>

<P>This course examines the analysis and application of statistical methods in the interpretation of biological data. The uses of descriptive and interferential statistics are included with an emphasis on advanced understanding of evidence-based research using chi-square, t-test, multiple regression, correlation, ANOVA/MANOVA, power analysis, factor analysis, and select non-parametric tests. The course focuses on the ability of the student to critically read and understand nursing research. Prerequisite: Undergraduate Statistics course. *This course is eligible for concurrent credit in the BSN program:  BSN course number NUR 4533. </P>

<P>NUR 599(1-3).  Independent Study – 1-3 hours </P>

<P>The independent study course provides the student with an opportunity to participate in the creation of academic learning experiences geared to individual needs, interests, or desired outcomes. This could take the form of self-directed reading, research, project, community service, or clinical experiences. The student and faculty mentor must agree on a topic of interest and learning objectives. The student is responsible to meet learning objectives by the end of the course. </P>

<H1> </H1>

<H1 id="LinkTarget_4144">ROBERT W. PLASTER COLLEGE OF BUSINESS AND COMPUTER SCIENCE </H1>

<P>Troy Bethards, Dean Office: Taylor 103 - (417) 328-1757 
<Link>http://www.sbuniv.edu/academics/colleges/cobacs.php</Link>
 </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Mission Statement </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The mission of the Robert W. Plaster College of Business and Computer Science is to provide educational programs in business, accounting, and computer and information sciences that integrate theories, concepts, and experiential applications with a Christian worldview. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Vision Statement </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The Robert W. Plaster College of Business and Computer Science is committed to strong academic programs, the integration of faith in discipline, and a continued pursuit of student success. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Core Values </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The Core Values of the Robert W. Plaster College of Business and Computer Science are: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody> Provide a student-focused education </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody> Integrate Christian faith in discipline </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody> Pursue continuous program review and improvement </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody> Continue partnership development with current and potential employers </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Accreditation </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The MBA program at Southwest Baptist University is accredited by the Accreditation Council for Business Schools and Programs.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Faith Integration </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Faculty in the College are committed to the University and College mission statements, which explicitly direct instruction of the College disciplines from the context of a Christian worldview.  In addition to providing a strong and rigorous curriculum in each of our specialties, our duty as Christian scholars is to help frame both our discipline and the practice of that discipline within a biblical and more specifically, a Christian context.  This commitment to integrate discipline with Christian faith and practice occurs throughout the courses taught within the College.  Furthermore, the College has adopted Psalm 15 as a guiding principle for our students.  The College is specifically dedicated to producing “Psalm 15 Professionals” for servant leadership roles in business and computer science.  Using Psalm 15 as a basis, eight character traits that should be hallmarks of students and graduates of the College have been identified.  These character traits are highlighted each semester and include: Integrity, Service, Respect, Charity, Faithfulness, Truthfulness, Humility, and Perseverance.  Psalm 15 Lectures are held each semester featuring guest lecturers who speak on the specific theme for that semester and relate personal experiences that highlight integrity and a Christian worldview for business leaders.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Assessment </P>

<P> The College faculty believes assessing educational outcomes in business is important. Outcomes assessment is a way to evaluate College programs and academic achievement of students in relation to similar colleges.   Therefore, all graduates </P>

<P>from Robert W. Plaster College of Business and Computer Science programs are required to participate in an appropriate College exit exam.  The information obtained is used to measure student competencies and provide feedback to improve the quality of the educational experience for students. </P>

<P>  </P>

<P>Each student will be required to complete both an Inbound and Outbound Assessment.  This assessment will measure their competency in the MBA core subjects (Accounting, Economics, Finance, Management, Marketing, and Statistics).  Students will complete the Inbound Assessment as part of the application process and the Outbound Assessment during their last semester of coursework.  More details about the assessment and scoring can be found under Prerequisites. </P>

<P> </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_4187">Master of Business Administration </H2>

<P>Director:  Levi Bridge </P>

<P>Office: Taylor Free Enterprise Center 102 – (417) 328-1758 </P>

<P>Faculty: Troy Bethards, Aaron Black, Levi Bridge, Angie Brown-Peterson,  </P>

<P>Allison Langford, Baochuan Lu, Jenell Wagner, Nathan Wright, John Zietlow </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Mission of the MBA program </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The mission of the Master of Business Administration program is to equip graduate students from a Christ-centered perspective, building on foundational business principles, with the interpersonal, critical thinking, and analytical skills to empower them to become servant leaders in a global community. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Admission Requirements </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Admission to Unclassified Status </P>

<P>Students who do not wish to pursue a degree but who are eligible for graduate study may take up to nine graduate credit hours in the College of Business and Computer Science. Applicants who have not completed the application process are also placed in this status until requirements are met. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Admission to Classified Status </P>

<P>Students may be fully admitted or conditionally admitted to the graduate program.  Classified status students are admitted to the program in one of four classification categories: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Fully Admitted - The student meets all admission standards and has been admitted to the program of study. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Conditionally Admitted </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>a. Contingent Admission - Any student who has not completed the academic program prerequisites is conditionally admitted to graduate study.  However, the graduate student may take no more than nine semester hours of graduate courses without satisfying program prerequisites. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>b. Academic Probationary Admission - The student meets all admission standards except that the student does not present a 2.75 grade point average.  This student may be admitted as a probationary student pending completion of nine hours of graduate level work with grades of &quot;B&quot; or better. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>c. Senior Admission – During the last year of their baccalaureate degree program, a current SBU student can apply for admission to the Master in Business Administration program.  During this same timeframe, the individual can begin taking graduate courses as a dually-enrolled student if: </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>ii. The total number of hours taken does not exceed 18 semester hours, which includes no more than nine semester hours of graduate courses. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>iii. The student has a minimum cumulative grade point average of 2.75.  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>iv. The student completes the bachelor degree at the end of a two-semester period. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>v. The student meets all other standards for admission. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>A student seeking admission to the Master of Business Administration program will need the following: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Bachelor or master degree from a regionally accredited college or university.  </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Minimum cumulative undergraduate grade point average of 2.75 on a 4.00 scale. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>3. Completed “Application for Admission to the College of Business and Computer Science Master of Business Administration Program.” </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Two recommendation forms that speak to the character and academic ability of the applicant. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Official transcripts from all colleges or universities attended.   </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>6. Complete the MBA Inbound Assessment. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>7. Additional information or interview as requested by the Program Director or Dean. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>8. Pay Application/New Student fee. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>International Students </P>

<P>International students must meet the admission requirements for the MBA program.  Official records not in English must be accompanied by an official translated record.  All records should show the individual subjects studied and the grades received in each subject. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Prerequisites </P>

<P>The Master of Business Administration program requires that students have prior knowledge in certain areas of study before fully pursuing the MBA.  The prerequisite of prior knowledge is required for three reasons: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody> It establishes a baseline level of knowledge for all MBA students. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody> Having a baseline level of knowledge helps to ensure SBU offers a quality MBA program. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody> Ensuring each student has a given level of knowledge in the vital disciplines related to the MBA translates into a greater likelihood of student success in completing the program.   </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Each student is required to take the MBA Inbound Assessment comprised of the following subjects: Accounting, Economics, Finance, Management, Marketing, and Statistics.  Based on the results of the student’s assessment results will determine whether leveling module(s) or prerequisite course(s) will be required.  Each student must earn a grade of 80% or higher in each of the subject areas to meet the prerequisite requirements. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>If a student does not earn a grade of 80% or higher in each subject, the student will be required to take the leveling module associated with that subject.  If the student earns an 80% or higher in the leveling module, they will show sufficient background knowledge to be able to succeed in the MBA program, and meet that subject’s prerequisite requirement.  If the student does not earn a grade of 80% or higher in the leveling course, that student will be required to take the prerequisite course to satisfy the prerequisite requirement. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Transfer Credit </P>

<P>Six graduate semester hours completed at another regionally accredited institution may be transferred and applied to the degree.  These credits must be comparable to courses offered at Southwest Baptist University and must be approved by the Graduate Council or the Dean of the College of Business and Computer Science. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Degree Requirements </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Students are eligible to graduate after fulfilling the requirements described below.  Students who enroll in another college or university without prior permission of the Director of the Graduate Studies in Business and Computer Science are considered to have withdrawn from Southwest Baptist University.  Students wishing to transfer work from another institution and not withdraw from Southwest Baptist University must obtain prior approval from the Director of the Graduate Studies in Business and Computer Science as well as the Dean of the College of Business and Computer Science. </P>

<P>  </P>

<P>Master of Business Administration </P>

<P>To receive the MBA degree, a student must: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody>1. Meet all graduate admission standards, including completion of a baccalaureate degree, and completion of admission application and file. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>2. Complete a plan of graduate study consisting of at least 37 semester hours. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>3. Maintain a graduate level GPA of at least 3.00 on a 4.00 scale with no grade below a C (2.00).  Students receiving two grades of “F” are automatically dismissed from the graduate program.  Students may reapply for admission after a mandatory one-year suspension.   </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>4. Complete all degree requirements within a five-year period following admission to the graduate degree program. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody>5. Participate in commencement exercises unless absence is approved by the Provost. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P>Outbound Assessment </P>

<P>As part of the degree requirements, each student is required to pass a comprehensive examination at or near the end of their study. The examination will test the extent to which the student can analyze, synthesize, and apply that which has been learned from the various graduate study experiences.   </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Program of Study and Academic Regulations </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The MBA degree program will consist of a minimum of 37 credit hours. Everyone enrolled in the MBA program will complete the MBA core.  If no concentration is pursued, a student will complete the additional MBA requirements to finish the degree.  An MBA with a concentration will complete the MBA core along with 12 additional credit hours of coursework specific to the concentration. The Master’s program of study is based upon the belief that experienced administrators should have a working knowledge of business on which to build. The following programs of study will ensure that administrators have the tools and knowledge to succeed in their careers. </P>

<P>  </P>

<P>MBA Program of Study (37 credit hours) </P>

<P> </P>

<P>MBA CORE Requirements (31 hours) </P>

<P>ACC 5113 Managerial Accounting  .................................................................................. 3 hours </P>

<P>ECO 5043 Managerial Economics .................................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>MGT 5043 Organizational Behavior and Servant Leadership ........................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>MKT 5023 Marketing Management .................................................................................. 3 hours </P>

<P>FIN 5023 Financial Management .................................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>MGT 5111 History of Management Thought .................................................................... 1 hour </P>

<P>CIS 5123  Management Information Systems and E-Commerce ..................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>MGT 5093 Organizational Strategy ................................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>MGT 5013 Managerial Communication  ........................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>MGT 5063  Entrepreneurship ............................................................................................. 3 hours </P>

<P>LDR 5063 Leadership Development  ............................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Additional MBA Requirements when no concentration is pursued (6 hours) </P>

<P>BUS 5043 Ethics and Critical Thinking in Business Administration ............................... 3 hours </P>

<P>BUS 5053 Global Business Practice and Opportunity ...................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P> </P>

<P>MBA Health Administration Concentration Additional Requirements (15 hours) </P>

<P>HAD 5013 Health Administration Law and Risk Management ........................................ 3 hours </P>

<P>HAD 5043 Ethics and Critical Thinking in Health Administration ................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>HAD 5083 Research Methods in Health Administration .................................................. 3 hours </P>

<P>HAD 5103 Health Service Systems ................................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P>HAD 5183 Health Service Organizations .......................................................................... 3 hours </P>

<P> </P>

<P>Dual-Listed Courses </P>

<P>The MBA program has three courses that are dual listed at the undergraduate level.  The dual-listed courses offer undergraduate students an opportunity to complete an MBA course before they graduate and earn credit toward their graduate degree. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>To take a dual-listed course, the undergraduate student must complete the MBA Application.  All other application requirements are to be completed upon entering the MBA program.  Eligible students must be in their last year of undergraduate study to enroll in a dual-listed course.  The dual-listed course will be a 4000 level course, but is taught at the MBA level.  Upon completion of the course, if the student wants the course to count as graduate level credit, the student will need to speak with the MBA Director who will coordinate with the Registrar’s Office to ensure it is counted as graduate credit. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>The three dual-listed courses and times offered are: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<LBody> Summer – CIS 4123 – Management &amp; Info Systems and E-Commerce </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody> Fall – ACC 4113 – Managerial Accounting </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<LBody> Spring – LDR 4063 – Leadership Development </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<P> </P>

<P>COURSE DESCRIPTIONS </P>

<P>ACCOUNTING </P>

<P>ACC 5003.  Accounting Foundations (cross-listed with ACC 2013) – 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of the basic fundamentals of Financial Accounting, concentrating on the complete accounting cycle for both the service and merchandising business.  Included in this study are inventory systems, internal control, financial reporting and financial statement analysis. This course is a leveling course, which meets an MBA prerequisite; it cannot be counted or substituted for another MBA course.  </P>

<P>ACC 5010.  Accounting Proficiency – 0 hours </P>

<P>This course is an academic leveling course in Accounting for incoming graduate students. </P>

<P>ACC 5013.  Accounting Foundations II (cross-listed with ACC 2043) – 3 hours  </P>

<P>A continuation of ACC 5003 that addresses managerial accounting and the role of accounting in the improvement of management practices.  Particular attention is given to cost accumulation, cost behavior, analysis, budgeting, management decision-making and control, time-value-of-money and capital budgeting. This is a leveling course, which meets an MBA prerequisite. Prerequisite: ACC 5003 (or undergraduate equivalent).   </P>

<P>ACC 5113.  Managerial Accounting – 3 hours </P>

<P>The application of accounting principles and techniques to managerial planning and controlling activities.  Areas emphasized will include behavior of cost, budgeting, accounting analysis, and improving managerial tools used in decision-making.  Prerequisite:  ACC 2043/5013. </P>

<P>ACC 5223.  Financial Accountability – 3 hours </P>

<P>This is a two-part course that addresses the issues typically included in graduate level courses in managerial accounting and finance principles and tools to achieve exceptional, comprehensive stewardship of all organizational resources. Prerequisite: ACC 2013/5003. </P>

<P>ACC 599(1-3).  Independent Study in Accounting – 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Independent study of some problem or area not covered in organized courses.  The study is under the direction of a department member in whose field of specialization the problem lies.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>BUSINESS </P>

<P>BUS 5000.  Continuous Enrollment </P>

<P>This course designation provides a mechanism for tracking students who have received a grade of &quot;I&quot; or &quot;IP&quot; in a graduate course and are not currently enrolled in another graduate offering at SBU. The course designation neither carries graduate credit nor requires tuition. The student is assessed a course fee utilized by the University to provide a current student identification card, allowing access to library resources at SBU and other university/college libraries, as well as providing funds to support related program record keeping. Course fee $50 per eight-week term. </P>

<P>BUS 5003.  Statistics Foundations (cross-listed with BUS 2023) – 3 hours </P>

<P>Emphasizes collection, tabulation, graphic presentation and interpretation of business and economic data.  Includes measures of central tendency and dispersion, elementary probability, sampling theory and linear correlation, computer applications.  A practical research project in business or health administration will be conducted.  This course is a leveling course which meets an MBA prerequisite; it cannot be counted or substituted for another MBA course. </P>

<P>BUS 5010.  Business Statistics Proficiency – 0 hours </P>

<P>This course is an academic leveling course in Business Statistics for incoming graduate students. </P>

<P>BUS 5023.  Business Communication and Culture – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course prepares students to deal with the challenges of language and culture in global legal, social and political settings that may vary significantly from that of the parent company. </P>

<P>BUS 5043.  Ethics and Critical Thinking in Business Administration – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course will consider biblical, traditional (classic) and contemporary methods in the field of ethics and moral philosophy and will assess their usefulness in everyday organizational life.  In analyzing contemporary organizational issues, the learner will be expected to look carefully at the factors within the work environment and society which contribute to ethical dilemmas, to think constructively about how these might be changed, and where the responsibility for such change lies.  Using established critical thinking methods, tools, and concepts, learners will explore and analyze the nature of work, the role of ethical leadership, the ethical characteristics of human organization, the relationship of the organization to society, and the development of an ethical organizational culture. </P>

<P>BUS 5053.  Global Business Practice and Opportunity – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course equips students to deal effectively with the challenges of establishing and managing international subsidiaries. It includes identifying and evaluating international opportunities and risks as well as the fundamentals of </P>

<P>international sales and distribution. It also introduces students to the important roles of international organizations such as the World Bank, IMF, WTO, EXLM, PEFCO, OPIC, OPEC, regional development banks and a variety of key trade agreements. Students enrolled in the course will either participate in an extensive course project or a structured one week international business experience. The cost of the trip will vary from year to year and will be an additional expense borne by the students choosing to participate. Prerequisite: MGT 3013/5003 and ECO 2033/5013. </P>

<P>BUS 5063.  Law of Commerce and International Trade – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course explores the key concepts, laws and application of the legal system governing international economic transactions and international economic relations.  The course examines the World Trade Organization, the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, debates centered on Trade-Related Intellectual Property Rights, the growing economic interdependence of the world, and the role of law in international affairs. </P>

<P>BUS 5083.  Quantitative Business Research – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course equips students to understand and use the principles and tools of quantitative analysis for decision making across all functional areas of the organization.  It includes decision theory and contemporary practices, including a familiarization with many of the most widely used software packages. Prerequisite: BUS 2023/5003. </P>

<P>BUS 5192.  Comprehensive Exam Review – 2 hours </P>

<P>This course is an interactive comprehensive review of all the course material in the program and includes additional contemporary readings that familiarize the students with the most recent global economic, ethical, legal, political, social and competitive challenges facing today’s enterprise. </P>

<P>BUS 598(1-3).  Internship – 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Academically planned and supervised work experience (160 hours) in area(s) of the student's specialization, approved by a graduate faculty member.  A paper will be required related to the internship experience in business.   </P>

<P>BUS 599(1-3).  Independent Study in Business – 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Independent study of some problem or area not covered in organized courses.  The study is under the direction of a department member in whose field of specialization the problem lies.  </P>

<P>BUS 6002.  Non-Profit Financial Management – 2 hours </P>

<P>This course provides an understanding of the fundamental concepts underlying financial management, controls, and analysis in the nonprofit sector. Various topics, including strategy, budgeting process techniques, major budgetary issues, financial statement analysis, revenue sources, fund development, tax strategies, debt management, human resources, risk management, cash management, basic categories of nonprofit expenditures, organizational controls, and relevant information technology will be discussed.  A working knowledge of Excel is required for this course. </P>

<P>BUS 6012.  Organization Consulting Practice – 2 hours </P>

<P>This course introduces the task and relationship dimensions of organizational consulting and develops foundational competency in the areas of assessment, diagnosis, and problem-solving relative to organizational performance.  Students will learn key aspects essential in creating and implementing effective independent consulting practices to support schools and non-profit organizations. Data collection and analysis are key components of the course to assist students in developing skills related to conducting effective organizational evaluations.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>COMPUTER AND INFORMATION SCIENCES </P>

<P>CIS 5123.  Management Information Systems and E-Commerce – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course equips students with the knowledge and skill needed to use effectively integrated (ERM, ERP) computer based information systems for planning and decision support and operational control throughout all functional areas of the organization. It also equips students to understand and interact with e-business systems and to keep up with rapidly changing technologies. Prerequisite: computer proficiency.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>ECONOMICS </P>

<P>ECO 5003.  Economic Foundations (cross-listed with ECO 2023) – 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of economic principles with emphasis upon microeconomics.  Includes a study of economics of the firm, consumer demand theory and current problems.  A practical research paper in managerial economics will be conducted.  This course is a leveling course which meets an MBA prerequisite; it cannot be counted or substituted for another MBA course. </P>

<P>ECO 5010.  Microeconomics Proficiency – 0 hours </P>

<P>This course is an academic leveling course in Microeconomics for incoming graduate students. </P>

<P>ECO 5013.  Economic Foundations II (cross-listed with ECO 2033) – 3 hours </P>

<P>A study of economic principles with emphasis on macroeconomics designed to provide a broad understanding of the economy.  Emphasis is on aggregate problems and issues considered important in society.  This course is a leveling course which provides a foundation for the MBA program; therefore, it cannot be substituted for another MBA course. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>ECO 5020.  Macroeconomics Proficiency – 0 hours </P>

<P>This course is an academic leveling course in Macroeconomics for incoming graduate students. </P>

<P>ECO 5043.  Managerial Economics – 3 hours </P>

<P>Combines basic microeconomic theory with statistical methods to provide a basis for practical application of economics attaining desired objectives.  Particular attention is given to using quantitative methods to choose optimal production, marketing, management, and finance options.  Prerequisite:  BUS 2023/5003 and ECO 2023/5003. </P>

<P>ECO 5053.  International Trade – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course equips students to initiate and sustain effective exporting and sourcing strategies. It addresses tariffs and duties, shipping, insurance, customs, clearance, bonded warehousing, Incoterms, the use of export management companies, import and export documentation, and regulations. Prerequisite: Economics proficiency ECO 2023/5003 and ECO 2033/5013. </P>

<P>ECO 599(1-3).  Independent Study in Economics – 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Independent study of some problem or area not covered in organized courses.  The study is under the direction of a department member in whose field of specialization the problem lies.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>FINANCE </P>

<P>FIN 5010.  Finance Proficiency – 0 hours </P>

<P>This course is an academic leveling course in Finance for incoming graduate students. </P>

<P>FIN 5013.  Finance Foundations (cross-listed with FIN 3053) – 3 hours </P>

<P>Study of the principles of financing short-term and long-term capital needs of business firms in keeping with an objective of maximizing the firm's value to its shareholders, i.e. stock price. Special attention given to Capital Asset Pricing Model, the various capital budget theories, computer applications, and spreadsheet analysis.  A practical research project in Business Finance will be conducted.  This course is a leveling course which meets an MBA prerequisite; it cannot be counted or substituted for another MBA course. </P>

<P>FIN 5023.  Financial Management – 3 hours </P>

<P>The study of management techniques for the effective utilization of the financial resources, personnel, and facilities of a physical resources institution.  Topics include analyzing organizational, financial performances, financial management strategies, and financial decision making for capital acquisitions.  Prerequisite: ECO 2023/5003 and FIN 3053/5013. </P>

<P>FIN 5033.  International Finance – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course prepares students to deal with the challenges and opportunities of operating in a world of multiple currencies, including the effects of IRP, PPP, IFE, methods for forecasting FX rates, estimating FX transaction and translation exposure, hedging, and short-term and long-term financing. Prerequisite: FIN 3053/5013. </P>

<P>FIN 599(1-3).  Independent Study in Finance – 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Independent study of some problem or area not covered in organized courses.  The study is under the direction of a department member in whose field of specialization the problem lies.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>HEALTH ADMINISTRATION </P>

<P>HAD 5073.  Human Resource Management in Health Care – 3 hours </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is to examine the foundation of human resource management in the healthcare environment.  Students will examine local, state, and federal health care laws, professional regulatory requirements, code of ethics, staffing, training, development, employee relations, and strategic planning.  The course also emphasizes recruitment, retention, and employee performance. </P>

<P>HAD 5093.  Organizational Analysis &amp; Innovation – 3 hours </P>

<P>The purpose of this course is to learn the complex dynamics of organizational process, structure, culture, and outcomes, as well as, the method of organizational analysis.  Also included are large and small organizational responses and resistance to change and innovation, as well as, methods of fostering creativity and positive change. </P>

<P>HAD 5113.  Advanced Healthcare Leadership &amp; Administration – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course prepares leaders who facilitate and integrate complex structures and processes in healthcare systems.  Students will gain an understanding of partnerships, accountability, continuum-defined healthcare systems, self-managed teams and value-based organizations as well as develop a plan for career development. </P>

<P>HAD 5123.  Health Care Organizations – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course examines historical perspectives and the current U.S. health care system and health care delivery models.  Factors influencing the health care delivery system including managed care, cost, access, and quality of care, </P>

<P>health services for vulnerable populations and leadership principles are emphasized.  Students analyze the U.S. health care system on a global perspective with countries offering universal health care plans. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>HAD 5153.  Quality &amp; Safety in Health Care – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course focuses on the relationship of patient safety and quality in the healthcare profession.  The goal is to introduce fundamentals of patient safety, evaluation of quality, quality measures, and concepts of quality improvement.  The student is introduced to the rationale for performance management and the role of the governing body of the healthcare organization in ensuring compliance with the standards of regulatory and Accreditation organizations.  Improving the quality, safety, and value of health care involves a multi-disciplinary approach and diverse knowledge. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>HUMAN RESOURCE MANAGEMENT </P>

<P>HRM 5033.  Human Resource Employment Law – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course explores the key concepts, theories, and application of employment law in human resources. The course examines all facets of employment law relation to Title VII, EEO, Employment-at-will, affirmative action, legal issues in compensation, benefits, performance management, and labor relations.  </P>

<P>HRM 5043.  Human Resource Compensation and Benefits – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course explores the key concepts, theories and application of compensation and benefits in human resource management. The course examines salary structure and analysis, job evaluation, incentive programs, compensation systems, development of benefit programs, executive compensation, and compliance with applicable government regulations related to benefits and compensation.  </P>

<P>HRM 5053.  Human Resource Performance Improvement – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course explores the key concepts, theories and application of employee training and development in human resource   management. The course examines strategic training and assessment, performance management, motivational theories, program design and practices, and career development.  </P>

<P>HRM 5073.  Human Resource Management – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course explores the key concepts, theories and application of human resource management. The course examines the human resources administrative environment, planning, and recruitment strategies, assessment, development and performance management, compensation and benefit design, and labor relations and collective bargaining. Additional focus will be centered on the strategic use of human resources management to gain competitive advantage in a global economy. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>LEADERSHIP </P>

<P>LDR 5063.  Leadership Development – 3 hours </P>

<P>A review of leadership theory with an emphasis given to the moral and ethical aspects related thereto.  The identification and development of leadership characteristics will be stressed with the intent to inspire moral gains on a personal and organizational level.  Various tools will be utilized throughout the course to facilitate the identification or development of a student’s leadership traits. </P>

<P>LDR 5043.  Ethical Leadership in Organizations – 3 hours </P>

<P>A significant percentage of those completing the requirements for the master program are destined for positions of authority in government, industry, NGOs and church organizations. This course equips the students to determine if they have the desire to lead, to determine if they are willing to accept the responsibility and accountability that comes with leadership and to equip them with leadership perspectives, principles and skills they will need to lead. </P>

<P> </P>

<P>MANAGEMENT </P>

<P>MGT 5003.  Management Foundations (cross-listed with MGT 3013) – 3 hours </P>

<P>The study of the process of management which is the coordination of all the resources of organizations in order to achieve organizational objectives. The management process will be described, analyzed, and applied to all types of organizations indicating the universality of management.   A research project in management will be conducted.  This course is a leveling course which meets an MBA prerequisite; it cannot be counted or substituted for another MBA course.   </P>

<P>MGT 5010.  Management Proficiency – 0 hours </P>

<P>This course is an academic leveling course in Management for incoming graduate students. </P>

<P>MGT 5013.  Managerial Communications – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course is designed to strengthen the student’s ability to effectively communicate within an organizational setting.  Emphasis is placed on effective written and oral communication within and between organizations including reports </P>

<P>and presentations.  Additional areas of emphasis relate to recruitment, selection, interviewing, development, supervision, and performance evaluation. </P>

<P>MGT 5043.  Organizational Behavior and Servant Leadership – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course integrates concepts, principles, and theories concerned with human behavior in organizations. Three core areas are addressed: factors related to the individual, factors related to groups and teams, and factors related to organizational systems and culture.  Principles of leadership are integrated into each of the three core areas, with emphasis on servant leadership attitudes and practices.  Prerequisite:  MGT 3013/5003. </P>

<P>MGT 5063.  Entrepreneurship – 3 hours </P>

<P>Explores the development of the entrepreneurial venture and the unique challenges facing these organizations.  Attention is given to determining the viability of the business, the various alternatives of financial capital, small business strategy, growth management and leadership.  The course incorporates the development of a business plan. Prerequisite:  ECO 2033/5015; FIN 3053/5013 and MGT 3013/5003. </P>

<P>MGT 5093.  Organizational Strategy – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course equips the students to deal with the complexities of managing entire organizations from the perspective of the CEO or COO. It teaches the students to deal with the competing demands for limited resources and the challenges of a competitive global marketplace. It follows up on the concepts of the Balanced Score Card and sustainable returns introduced in earlier returns introduced in earlier courses. Prerequisites:  all prerequisites to the MBA. </P>

<P>MGT 5111.  History of Management Thought – 1 hour </P>

<P>This course explores many of the contributions and contributors to the field of management from ancient times to the present. Its purpose is to help the student grasp the evolving nature of the field and to compare and contrast perspectives, principles and practices suggested by various approaches. In particular it helps the student understand the impact of the secular materialist worldview and to compare and contrast secular materialism with alternative perspectives. </P>

<P>MGT 5233.  Management for Results – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course places emphasis on acquiring the knowledge and skills typical of graduate level organization management courses. Its primary topics are business intelligence, planning, organizing, controlling and leading. The distinctive focus is teaching the student to manage self and to be accountable for measurable results of other individuals and teams. </P>

<P>MGT 599(1-3).  Independent Study in Management – 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Independent study of some problem or area not covered in organized courses.  The study is under the direction of a department member in whose field of specialization the problem lies.  </P>

<P> </P>

<P>MARKETING </P>

<P>MKT 5003.  Marketing Foundations (cross-listed with MKT 3023) – 3 hours </P>

<P>The study of the system of activities that constitute marketing with emphasis on the theories, principles, policies, and strategies utilized to identify and satisfy the needs and wants of customers.  The universal application of marketing management in all forms or organizations is stressed and a research project in marketing will be conducted.  This course is a leveling course which meets an MBA prerequisite; it cannot be counted or substituted for another MBA course. </P>

<P>MKT 5010.  Marketing Proficiency – 0 hours </P>

<P>This course is an academic leveling course in Marketing for incoming graduate students. </P>

<P>MKT 5023.  Marketing Management – 3 hours </P>

<P>This course equips students with the knowledge and skills necessary to plan and execute strategies and tactics typically assigned to the marketing function of organizations. It addresses critical factors affecting product and enterprise competitiveness, including allocating resources; designing, pricing and positioning products; creating awareness through promotion; creating accessibility through distribution strategies; and integrating the marketing function with other functions in the organization. Prerequisite: MKT 3023/5003. </P>

<P>MKT 599(1-3).  Independent Study in Marketing – 1-3 hours </P>

<P>Independent study of some problem or area not covered in organized courses.  The study is under the direction of a department member in whose field of specialization the problem lies. </P>
